Hello, and welcome to Lesson 38
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is calculus and programming.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
The main point is that there are many problems in calculus
where you have to do some operation multiple times—
tens or hundreds of times—
and a good example of that is Euler’s method.
Now in Euler’s method, you have a recurrence relation.
What that means is that you need to compute something step by step.
For example, if you want to compute y[10],
you need to work out y[9], y[8], et cetera,
and to do this correctly by hand can be very, very tedious.
You may have errors in your calculations,
or it might just take a very long time.
Of course what you can do is to set up a program
which does that for you in the Wolfram Language.
That’s the theme of this lesson.
In this lesson, you’ll learn how to make
your own programs within the Wolfram Language.
We need some preliminaries over here.
We need a few tools basically which will let us
make programs in the Wolfram Language,
and that’s just a list of functions which are useful in this context.
You need the function If to control the flow of the program.
You also need the simple semicolon character
to stop an instruction and move on to another instruction.
You need the function Print to put text on the screen
and tell you what is happening inside the program,
and that’s what is called debugging.
Here’s an example of a function which is called ifexample
which takes an input a, a number,
and says if the number a is positive, print “positive”;
otherwise, print “not positive”.
If you apply it to the list over here,
ifexample[10] should be positive, ifexample[0] should be not positive
and ifexample[–4] should also be not positive.
Here is the output,
and you see that although you don’t get back anything—
eventually you just get back Null—but on the way,
you see the positive for the 10
and the not positive for the remaining two.
Now on the next note, if you, let’s say, say a = 5
and you put a semicolon over here,
that lets you move on to the next operation,
which in this case is a + 6.
So, a is 5, so of course a + 6 is just 11.
A couple of things more.
You can put comments in your program
using this notation over here,
and of course comments are very useful
because they explain how your code works.
Most code is very hard to read, and unless you have lots of comments,
the reader will not be able to tell what’s happening inside the code.
As an example, here I’ve set c equal to 4,
then put a comment to say that we’re setting c equal to 4,
and then it gives the value of c.
Now another important function is the For function,
which will let you do a task repeatedly
like we require for the Euler method.
Here’s a program that prints the numbers from 1 to 10.
We start with i = 1 and you go all the way up to 10, not 11.
You keep going as long as the number i is less than 11,
and at every step, you increment i by 1 to go on to the next number.
Then of course you print the number
to say what’s happening inside the code.
Here is the For loop,
and you see it prints 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and then stops.
Okay. Just one more issue,
and that’s the issue of global versus local variables.
The variable over here a is a global variable in the sense that
its value was set earlier to be 5.
Now that can be a huge problem for you when you make a program.
For example, you write a function f[x] which just does x + a.
If you do f[2], you might think you’ll get back 2 + a,
but instead you get back 7, and that’s because a is 5.
What we need to do is to instead use local variables.
Now you could use different variable names,
but you might forget what they are,
so the best way out is to use local variables.
For example, over here you can use Module,
and what Module does is it localizes the variable a.
If I do f[2], then you get back 2 plus this strange kind of a, a$2415.
Now that number might change from time to time,
but basically that protects the a inside the function
from being confused with the a which is global.
This extra symbol over here indicates that
it is a local variable or a Module variable.
That’s all we need to define a function
which implements Euler’s method.
Recall that that was the one thing
we could not quite discuss fully in differential equations.
So here’s a function called eulermethod.
Now I’m using lowercase
because the Wolfram Language likes to reserve the uppercase letters
for built-in functions.
It takes the slope function, the starting point,
the end point of the interval, the initial value for the function
and the step size—how many steps you want to take as you go along.
What you do now is you set up a Module,
and the Module has some variables in it.
The first variable is m,
and what m is, is just the number of steps to be used.
It’s the end minus the start over the step size.
We also need the x values.
That’s going to be the starting value plus the step size times i,
where i will go from 0 to the number of steps.
We also need the y values, and to do that,
we first populate this table with the same constant initial value,
and then we start off with the For loop.
What the For loop does is it calculates each value of y
based on the preceding value plus the step size times the slope.
Then finally we gather all the x and y values
and do this Transpose to make them look just right.
That is Euler’s method from differential equations
now done in the Wolfram Language.
With this simple function, we can now try and do some calculations.
Here is a differential equation, y' = y given y[0] = 1,
and of course the solution for that is just e^x.
The right-hand side is y.
That’s your f.
We apply the eulermethod to f starting at 0
because that’s where you’re starting over here,
and you want the value at 2, so that’s where you’ll stop.
The initial value is 1.
That’s the 1 over here.
The 0.1 is going to be the step size.
Okay. When you do that, then you see over here that
you get back a list of values starting from the initial value
and going all the way up to 2 in steps of 0.1.
Now you see over here that the last value is 6.7275.
The estimate over here is that the value of y[2] is 6.7275.
Let’s compare that with e^2, and it looks like it’s reasonably good,
but not very accurate.
But that’s because we’re only at a step size of 0.1.
Because you’re working on a computer,
you can afford to make much smaller steps.
You could say let the step size be 0.001,
and then you get back a much smaller estimate for the error,
which is 0.007.
The point is that you can get better estimates for the values
and much smaller errors simply by decreasing the step size.
Of course because it’s all automatic, it doesn’t matter.
You can go quite a long way to get more and more accurate results.
Okay. That brings me to the end of the lesson,
and the main point is that
the Wolfram Language is great for making programs.
In fact, what you’ve done in this course
is to learn many parts of the Wolfram Language
in the context of calculus, and that’s a great thing to know.
Programming is a big plus in this age.
Now to program, you need functions like If, For, Print and Module.
Do not forget—try and put as many comments as you can
because they are crucial for understanding
what you are trying to do, both for yourself and for others.
Try to avoid global variables.
Try and use local variables to avoid confusion,
and you can do that with Module.
We saw that we can program Euler’s method,
but of course you can program other calculus operations,
like finding maxima and minima, using the Wolfram Language.
To program yourself means that you actually become
some kind of an expert on the Wolfram Language
because those programs can be quite hard to write.
That’s the end of this lesson on calculus and programming.
We’re really done with the course content.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about a sample calculus exam,
the first part of the exam, but until then,
do review this lesson and be prepared to take on an exam.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.