Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 9
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this session is numerical approximation of integrals,
average value of a function, exponentials and logarithms.
Let’s begin with the first problem on the session.
The first problem says compute the derivative of 2e^x.
Now the derivative of e^x is itself,
so the required derivative is 2e^x.
Let’s confirm that with D.
Here is a plot of the derivative.
On to number 2, which says compute the indefinite integral of 3^x.
The answer is simply 3^x/Log[3].
Let’s check that with Integrate.
That’s correct.
Let’s plot both the function and integral, and of course
they just differ by a scale factor of Log[3].
On to number 3, which says compute the derivative of 2^x^2.
Now that’s a bit harder and requires the chain rule.
You work out the as 2^x^2Log[2] times the derivative of x^2,
which is 2x.
You can check that with D.
Notice there’s a 2^(1 + x^2) over here.
That’s where the extra 2 goes.
Let’s plot the function and the derivative.
You can see over here that the 2 occurs right over here.
Okay. On to number 4, which says
compute the integral from 0 to π/2 of Cos[x]e^Sin[x].
You make a small substitution.
You let u = Sin[x].
The du = Cos[x]dx, the derivative of Sin[x].
Then you get a very simple integral
because the limits become 0 to 1 when x is 0.
Then Sin[x] is 0.
When x is π/2, Sin[x] is 1, so you get e^u from 0 to 1,
which is—Integrate gives you e – 1.
Let’s check the answer with Integrate,
and you get back the same answer.
Now let’s plot the region being integrated,
and that’s the required plot.
On to number 5, which says compute the derivative of 4Log[3x].
The answer is going to be 4 times the derivative of Log[3x],
which will be 1/3x, times 3 by the chain rule, so the answer is 4/x.
Let’s confirm that with D, and you do get back 4/x.
Here is a plot of the function and its derivative.
On to number 6, which says compute the integral
of x/(x^2 + 2) from –1 to 3.
Make a small substitution.
Let u be x^2 + 2, so du is 2xdx, the derivative of x^2 + 2.
Now when x is –1, then u is 3.
When x is 3, then 3^2 + 2 is 11, so u is 11.
You get back a much simpler integral which requires the Log function
and the answer is 1/2Log[11/3].
Let’s check with Integrate, and you do get back the same answer.
Here is a plot of the region that we just integrated.
On to number 7, which says find
the derivative of Log[x] to the base 5.
Well, that’s just going to be 1/xLog[5]
because you can rewrite the input as Log[x]/Log[5].
Let’s check the answer with D,
and here is a plot of the function and its derivative.
On to number 8, which says compute the indefinite integral of Log[2x].
Well, we need a small substitution.
Let u be 2x, so du is 2dx.
Then you get the integral of Log[u]du/2.
Remember that the integral of Log[u] is uLog[u] – u,
so the answer is xLog[2x] – x + C.
Here’s the same answer from Integrate minus the constant C,
and here is a plot of the function and its integral when C is 0.
On to number 9, which says compute the average value
of the cubed root of x from 1 to 27.
Now the average value formula is
1 over the upper limit minus the lower limit—
that’s the length of the interval—
times the integral of the function over that integral.
Compute with Integrate and you get back 30/13,
and here is a plot of the function
and its average value on the same integral.
On to number 10, which says find the point at which
the average value of this function over a certain interval
equals the function value.
Now that equals suggests that
you want to apply the mean value theorem.
Let’s do that.
We solve the equation function value at a point c
equal to the main value, and you get back that c is about 0.785.
Here is a plot of the function and its average value.
On to number 11, which says compute the average value of e^(x/2)
over the interval 3 to 5.
That’s just a computation.
It’s 1/(5 – 3) times the integral of the function over the interval.
Here is the average value.
Then finally we have a plot of the function and the average value.
On to number 12,  which says use the midpoint rule
with eight rectangles to compute the numerical approximation
for this integral over here.
For the midpoint rule, you take the midpoints
as the points of the rectangles touch the curve,
so the width of each rectangle of course is just π/24
because you have eight rectangles, and you want the sample points
to be the midpoints of each subinterval.
The sum is going to be the sum from 1 to 8
of the width of each rectangle
times the value of the function at the midpoint.
Compute it with Sum.
You get back 0.7895 approximately.
Check with NIntegrate, the built-in numerical integrator,
and your values agree quite nicely because
the midpoint rule is quite a powerful rule for approximation.
On to number 13, which says use the trapezoidal rule
to estimate the integral over here.
Now for the trapezoidal rule, of course you’ll take the height to be
just the width of these subintervals.
That’s (2π – e)/5 because you want five trapezoids.
Then you multiply that by the average, so to speak,
of the values at the two endpoints,
and you get back the approximation.
In this case, the approximation is not very good
because the trapezoidal rule is typically not very accurate.
On to number 14.
How about Simpson’s rule?
You want to apply Simpson’s rule with 10 subsections
to compute the integral of Sin[Sin[x]] from 0 to π/2.
That’s a very difficult integral,
but Simpson’s rule works really well over here.
The first step is you break up the integral into 10 subsections
and you get π/20 for each of them as the length.
Then apply the rule, which is basically you want to use
the rule 1, 4, 1—the values at f[2i – 2], f[2i – 1] and f[2i].
Compute the approximation from Simpson’s rule,
and it agrees quite well with the actual answer.
That brings me to the end of this problem session.
I hope you have learned a lot about average values
and approximations and exponentials and logs by now.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.