Hello, and welcome to Lesson 9 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is differentiation formulas. Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson.
The point is that one can find derivatives using the limit definition, but in practice
this is quite a tedious and tricky approach, and one wishes that there was some simpler way
of finding derivatives in practice. Luckily there are formulas which help us to find derivatives
of many commonly occurring functions. For example, here is a constant function f[x] = c,
and you can see over here that the derivative of this function is just 0. The derivative of
a constant function is always 0. Let’s check the graphs. Here is a graph of the function,
and the derivative is 0. In this lesson, what we’ll do is we’ll cover basic differentiation formulas
of this type, and by the end of today’s lesson, you’ll feel quite comfortable about
computing derivatives in practice.
As a first example, here are the power functions. You have a function x^n.
For different values of n, you get different power functions. Taking this function
and finding its derivative gives you n * x^(n − 1). That’s a very well-known formula
in differential calculus. For example, if n is 2, then you have a quadratic function
and its derivative is just 2x. It might be good to memorize that the derivative of x^2 is 2x.
Let’s plot the function and derivative. That’s the function, a quadratic function, a parabola,
and that’s the derivative, and clearly the derivative must be negative on the left
because the function is decreasing, so the slopes are all negative over here.
Going to the same topic, suppose you have x^−1. That’s a negative number,
but the same rule applies and you get back −1/x^2 as the answer. Again, here is a plot of the function
and its derivative. Finally let’s take an example where you actually have
a kind of negative decimal power. But the same formula applies, and you get back
a derivative in the same form, n * x^(n − 1).
Okay. To go further, let’s now talk about constant multiples of functions. Here you have
a constant and a function, and when you try to find the derivative, what you do is you simply
pull out the constant from the function where you’re trying finding the derivative.
The derivative over here is just 15x^2, which is just 5 times 3x^2, so the 15x^2 over here
the constant 5 times 3x^2, which is the derivative of x^3. Here’s a plot of the function and derivative,
and you can see that this is a very simple rule, the constant multiple rule.
To go a step further, let’s look at a very important rule named the sum rule.
If you have a function f and a function g and you find their sum, then the derivative of the sum
is just the sum of the derivatives. So you simply work out f' and g' separately,
and then when you add them up, in this case you get back 6x + 2, which is the correct answer.
The sum rule makes it quite simple to find the derivative in such cases. Once again, here’s a plot.
You have the function f[x], the function g[x], and the derivatives over here are f'[x],  g'[x],
and the sum has got a derivative, which is the sum of those two.
Okay. On to the difference rule, which is very simple and similar.
If you’ve got a function f and a function g and you define their difference,
then then derivative of the difference is the difference of the derivatives—
namely, you work out f'[x], work out g'[x] and then you subtract them, and you get back
the answer for the difference derivative. Here’s a plot of all the derivatives. Once again you see that
if you have a difference, then the derivative is really simple to compute.
Sums are simple. Differences are simple. The question is what happens to products.
Well, if you have a function f[x] and then a function g[x] and you multiply them to get the product,
you might think that the derivative of the product is the product of the derivatives,
but that is not the case. In fact, if you work it out over here you get √x in one case
and you get quite a different answer in the other. It turns out that in this case,
the correct formula is you do f * g' + g * f', and then you do get back the correct answer
for the derivative of the product. Once again, here’s a plot of all three derivatives
to give you a feeling for what’s happening over here, but notice that now things are no longer simple.
You actually do need to memorize a rule which says that the derivative of
the product of f and g is f * g' + g * f', and as if this is not complicated enough,
let’s look at the quotient rule. If you have f and g and you take their quotient,
so you divide them, then once again the derivative of the quotient is not the quotient of the derivatives.
You can check that over here. If you do f'/g', you get one answer;
if you find the derivative directly for the quotient, you get another answer.
The fact is that the quotient rule for derivatives is a lot harder. It says that
the derivative is (g * f' − f * g')/g^2. In this case, the rule gives you the correct answer,
namely, −3/2x^3. Once again you can plot all the derivatives, and you learn that the quotient rule
is significantly more complicated than the earlier rules, but in fact it does give you
the correct answer in all cases. We’ve learned the sum rule, the difference rule, the product rule
and the quotient rule, and in fact that brings us to the end of today’s lesson.
The point is that yes, derivatives are useful, but it is only when you have the rules for differentiation
that you can actually use them effectively in practice, so you do need to know all the rules we learned today.
There are rules for sums, differences, products and quotients. Of course the simplest rule is the power rule,
which lets you find the derivative of things like x^2 and x^3 and other powers of x.
In the next lesson, we’ll go on to doing something more with derivatives, namely,
talking about the trigonometric functions. But before we do that,
do make sure you review today’s lesson, try the exercises and make sure
you’re ready for the next theme, which is the derivatives of trigonometric functions.
I’ll stop over here. I hope you found this lesson really useful. This is where calculus really begins,
where it becomes a very algebraic kind of process and becomes easy to apply in practice.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.