Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 1 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is limits and functions. Now before I go on, I just want to say that
we’ll have several problem sessions, and the idea would be to try and solve problems,
but also to review the concepts done in the last few lessons. We will talk about limits,
which is kind of a fundamental topic for calculus, and also we’ll talk about functions,
which were talked about early on in the course. Let’s begin with problem number 1.
You want to find a limit of x^2 + 2 as x approaches 5. Now this is just a polynomial,
so you can plug in x = 5. 5^2 + 2 = 27, and you can check the answer with Limit.
The answer is 27. Finally, you can do a plot and make sure that
the value actually looks like it is 27. That’s a 27 over there.
On problem 2, you want to find the limit of Sin[2x − 1] as x approaches π/6.
Now just as a review and also to check things carefully, let’s first look at
the left-hand limit from below, and the answer is √3/2 − 1. You get the same answer for
the right-hand limit, and in fact Limit tells you that the answer is exactly what we got early on.
Here’s a plot, and the numerical answer is around −0.2.
Okay. Problem number 3. You want to find the limit of the Log[x] to the base 2 minus e^5x,
and if you work it out with the left-hand limit, you get the answer 3 − e^40.
That’s a large negative number. You get the same answer with the right-hand limit.
Notice I’m using FullSimplify to make it a little simpler. You get the same answer with Limit,
so that’s the answer for the limit. The numerical value is about 10^17 with a negative sign.
You can check the answer on the plot, and there it is.
The answer is about −2.35, to be more precise, times 10^17.
Okay. Now we go on to an example where things go wrong. You want to find the limit of 3/x
as x approaches 0, and clearly there’s a problem because when x is 0,
then the denominator becomes 0. If you find the left-hand limit, the answer is −∞.
The right-hand limit is ∞, so clearly the limit does not exist, and the answer is actually indeterminate.
Here’s a plot which shows that indeed the function approaches ∞ as you go to 0 from the right
and −∞ when you go to 0 from the left, so that’s the answer.
The answer of the limit is just indeterminate; it does not exist.
Okay. Number 5. Now we have a rational function. The problem over here is that if you look at
the denominator over here, it’s x^2 − 7x + 10, but at 2, the denominator is 0,
so we cannot apply the quotient law for limits directly. What you should do first
is to simplify the function—in this case, factor it. Simplify will do that for you,
and then when you plug in the value x = 2, you get back the answer −1, and that’s exactly the limit
for the function at 2. Namely, it’s −1. You can check the answer with the plot,
and you do get the answer −1 with the plot as well. For rational functions,
you may need to do a bit of simplification before you actually find the limit.
Problem number 6. You are given a rational function, but this time things are a bit simpler
because the numerator has limit 17 on plugging in, the denominator has 20 on plugging in
and you can therefore use a quotient law to get the limit by simple division.
Here’s the answer from Limit, which is exactly the same. You can plot the function,
and it does look like that’s the correct answer.
Okay. Now Let’s go on to talking about things that are more complicated. You want to find
the left-hand limit of x over its absolute value when x approaches 0 from the left-hand side.
Now when x is negative, of course, that over here is negative x. You would expect that
the answer is −1. You can confirm the answer with Limit. You get −1.
You can check the answer over here, and the answer is indeed −1.
If you approach from the left the answer is −1, and from the right it is 1.
Question number 8. You want to find the limit of x * e^1/(x − 4) when x approaches 4 from the right.
Now what happens over there is when x is slightly larger than 4, that’s a very small positive number,
so you get a very large number over here. That’s what the table tells you:
that the answer’s probably going to be ∞. Those are very, very large numbers.
You can confirm the answer with Limit and get ∞. This right-hand limit is actually ∞,
and you can check the answer with a plot. Indeed it is ∞.
Okay. Moving on now, let’s take piecewise limits. Here you have got a piecewise function,
but it’s only different at a single point, so that’s not going to affect the limit.
Here’s the function in Mathematica form, the Wolfram Language form,
and the left-hand limit is 4. If we just plug in the values, the right-hand limit is also 4,
and together, the limit is again 4. For a piecewise function, there is no difficulty
if it’s only different at a single point, and the plot confirms that. Surely the value
is different at 2 itself, but around 2, near 2, there is a nice, smooth behavior.
Okay. Things go slightly wrong in the next example because now we have got a piecewise function
with two large pieces. If you are at −3, then on the left you use that expression over there to get −8;
on the right, use the second expression and you get 6. You’ve got a left-hand limit of −8,
a right-hand limit of 6, and together they tell you that the limit does not exist.
We can confirm that with a plot. You have two pieces, but at the point of interest, they actually have
a very different limit from the right and from the left, so the answer is indeterminate.
Okay. Now the last few questions are about domains and ranges of our functions.
The question is to find the domain of this function. Well, it’s very simple because
the Cos function is defined everywhere, 2x is defined everywhere,
so together they give you the function domain as being everything, the whole real line.
FunctionDomain says True, which means that the function is defined everywhere. If you plot it,
then indeed there is no problem at all. This function has domain equal to the set of real numbers.
Going a step further, let’s try and find the domain of (x^2 − 2)/(x^2 − 4),
and clearly the problem is only when the denominator is 0. Now x^2 − 4 is 0 when x is either 2 or −2.
You can check that with Factor or with Solve. The only problematic points are 2 and −2,
so it looks like the domain is either to the left of 2 or between −2 and 2 or between 2 and ∞.
You can check that function domain, which says that the domain is either x less than −2,
or x lying between −2 and 2, or x to the right of 2. Here’s a plot,
and quite clearly there are three pieces: one to the left of −2, one between −2 and 2
and one to the right of 2.
Okay. Now on to ranges. The question is compute the range of x^3. Well, x^3 is an odd polynomial,
so its range is all real numbers. You can confirm that with the function Range, which says True.
The plot says that in fact you can cover everything below and above,
so the range is all real the numbers.
On to the last problem, which is to do the range of Sec[x]. Now because secant is the reciprocal of cosine
and because cosine goes between 1 and −1—here’s a plot to confirm that—
then clearly the range of secant must be to the left of −1, the right of 1 and of course we can have
both the values over here included. The function range is either y less than or equal to −1
or y greater than or equal to 1. Here’s a plot which confirms that, and you leave out
everything between −1 and 1 on the y axis, and the rest are all okay.
This brings me to the end of today’s problem session. I hope you have had a nice review for concepts.
Next time, in Lesson 6, we go on to continuity, but before that, do try the short quiz, Quiz 1,
which deals with the first few lessons. Review what you’ve learned so far,
and next time we’ll go on to continuity in Lesson 6. Thank you.