Hello, and welcome to Lesson 23 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is Riemann sums.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
Basically there are two fundamental aspects of calculus.
The first aspect is differential calculus,
and that’s what we’ve been talking about all the time so far.
Now the prime motivation over there is to find the slope of a curve at a point of the tangent line.
Now the second aspect of calculus is the so-called integral calculus,
and that is what we’ll cover from now on.
Now the basic motivation, the prime motivation for this part of calculus is quite simple.
Basically here is a plot of this function, and the problem is that
you’d like to find this area under the curve for the function.
In this lesson, what we’ll do is we’ll devise a precise way
of expressing this notion of area under the curve mathematically.
Okay. Let’s begin with some review of your earlier work.
If you have a rectangle, then its area is length times width.
On the other hand, if it were a triangle, then its area is base times height over 2.
But if you have a general polygon, what you’d do is you’d break it up into triangles,
then find the area of each one triangle and then add them all together.
Now the area of a circle is a bit harder because it involves the number π,
but that’s straightforward to work with.
The question now is what happens if you have a more general curve?
Let’s say you have this parabola, and you want to find the area under the parabola.
How do you work it out?
To motivate our discussion, let’s recall the idea of the slope at a point.
Let’s say if you have a differentiable function, then the slopes of
the secant lines at a point will eventually approach some value m,
which is the slope of the tangent at that point.
Here’s an example to illustrate that.
You have a curve x^2 and you have a point (1, 1) on it,
and you want to work out the slope at that point.
At the moment, the slope is 3.618 for the secant,
but what I’ll do now is I’ll try and bring the point Q closer to P,
and as I bring it closer, the value of the slope
approaches the correct value, which is eventually 2.
That’s the idea of slope at a point.
You take secant lines, and then you take the limit of those lines
as you approach the point.
A similar idea can be used for areas; namely, break up the areas
into separate rectangles, and then you add up all those rectangle areas
and then you get an approximate area for the region.
For example, if you take the same curve and you break it up
into four rectangles over here, then you see that the area approximately,
but of course a wide space tells you that
there is some error in the approximation.
Now if you take more rectangles—let’s say you take 10 rectangles—
you will get a better approximation, and then as you increase
the number of rectangles, you will get a better and better approximation, hopefully.
That’s the idea of area which we want to explore.
Let’s begin now with a parabola again and try and work with rectangles
which have the top-left corner at the point on the curve.
What you see here is that in this case, you actually have
an underestimation of the total area, so the answer which you get is less than the total area.
For example,  in this case your corners are at 0, 0.2, et cetera,
and you can work out the area.
Then you get back the answer, 0.21875.
Those over here are just the function values.
Okay. On the other hand, if you took the top-right corner for each rectangle,
then you can see you’re going to overestimate the area under the curve,
so in this case you get back the answer, 0.46875.
It looks like the answer would lie somewhere between 0.21875 and 0.46875.
That’s the conclusion from the earlier slide which I am repeating over here again.
What happens as you increase the number of rectangles?
Well, you see over here that as you have a larger and larger number
of rectangles, then the lower and the upper estimates become closer and closer,
and they are almost identical eventually.
The plots over here show you what’s happening over here.
As you have a larger number of rectangles,
you get a better and better approximation to the area,
and finally it looks like you actually get the area.
But that only happens when you take a limit.
The area will approach 1/3, but that will only actually happen if you take a limit.
Here’s a required limit. 1/n is the width of each rectangle,
and that’s the functional value, the height.
The limit over here is 1/3—that’s the upper limit—and the lower limit
would be to take the other end of the rectangle,
and then you get back 1/3 as the answer in this case as well.
Okay. Now to get a bit more general, I need to talk about so-called Riemann sums.
Now this is a fairly difficult concept, so let me go slowly.
Let’s say you have a general function f[x], not just a parabola,
and you want to work out the area under the curve between [a, b].
What you do is you first break it up into n rectangles
so each rectangle will have a width (b – a)/n.
This quantity is called Δx. Δ means very small.
Now you’ve broken up your interval [a, b] into n smaller intervals,
[x0, x1], [x1, x2], et cetera, and the left endpoint is a, the right endpoint is b.
For each subinterval, you have the endpoints given by just adding Δx every time.
What you see over here is the area of any one rectangle
will be the width of the rectangle times the height.
Let’s say if you work with the right-aligned rectangles,
then that height will be f[xi].
That’s the total area, the sum, but if you work out the left-aligned rectangles,
then you get a similar sum, but with xi – 1 as the point which you evaluate.
These sums are called Riemann sums because
they were discovered by the famous German mathematician Bernhard Riemann.
Here’s an example that shows what’s happening.
You have the curve Sin[x] + 2, and you want to see what happens
as you increase the number of rectangles.
Let’s play the animation.
You see that you get a better limit approximation
as you increase the number of rectangles.
But of course, things are not so simple because at some places,
you get a slightly smaller area, and at some others,
you overestimate the area.
Okay. Now we can make a formal definition of area.
The area under the curve is defined by
the limit of the sum of the areas of the rectangles.
Now that’s the case for right-aligned because you’re working with f[xi],
but if you want left-aligned rectangles, then you get almost the same expression,
but now you start at 0 rather than starting at 1.
The fact is that if your function f is continuous,
then both those limits will exist, and in fact, they’ll be equal.
You could work with those sums, or you could actually take the values
at any number in the subinterval for each i.
These numbers are called sample points.
In particular, if you have right-aligned rectangles,
then you have the sample points xi, and if you have left-aligned rectangles,
then you have the sample points xi – 1.
That’s the general formula for the area
with any sample points for each subinterval.
For example, here you have taken the sample points
to be the midpoints of each subinterval.
Okay. Now it’s time to work out an example,
so let’s try to work out the area of Sin[x] from 0 to b
where the number b lies between 0 and π.
Here’s a plot. Now we break up the interval into n subintervals.
We’ll work with, let’s say, right-aligned rectangles,
and you get the answer for the area as 1 – Cos[b].
Of course, you could then replace the b with π,
and you get back a much nicer answer, which is just 2.
That’s the power of the whole method; namely, it gives the exact answer
under this curve between, in this case, 0 and π.
Okay. Now a slightly more practical problem.
Let’s say a car moves on a highway, and you’re given the velocities
at different times at 10-minute intervals, and you want to work out
the total distance covered in 100 minutes.
What you do is you divide by 60 over here—
after all, you want to work with minutes—and you take the height,
so to speak, as the velocities, so you take 63, 62, 61, et cetera, from here,
and you get back the sum, which is just the distance covered.
You can also take the heights to be the velocities at the right endpoints
like I’ve done over here, in which case you get back the answer 108.33.
That’s a plot of the velocities, and we’ve worked out distance in two ways
using the left values and the right values.
But of course we could be more precise and assume that the velocity
is given by a certain function, in which case you could work out
the distance by a similar method as earlier on.
You take the limit of the sum, and then velocities must be then
found out at those values over here.
Then you get back the answer as 109.394 in this case.
That’s a plot of velocity, and the area under the curve in this case
will give you the distance covered in that interval of time.
That brings me to the end of this lesson.
Basically, finding area is a very practical matter.
You’ve done it forever, so to speak,
from, let’s say, middle school all the way up.
But to work out the area under a general curve,
you must divide into rectangles and then add those areas up.
Finally, we are doing calculus, so you must take the limit
as those rectangle numbers approach infinity,
and then you get the real area under the curve.
Now, these sums that you compute are called Riemann sums
in honor of the mathematician Riemann,
and these Riemann sums can also be used to work out
the total distance traveled when you are given only the velocity.
That’s the end of this lesson.
The next lesson will talk about Riemann sums in more detail,
but before doing that, there will be a problem session,
which you should certainly look at and understand the topic in much greater detail.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.