Hello, and welcome to Lesson 34 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is logarithmic functions.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the subject.
In the last lesson, we talked about exponential functions
like this one, 2^x.
Here is a plot of the function.
The question is suppose we want to solve the equation 2^x = 5.
The problem here is that 5 is not a power of 2 in any obvious way,
so we give it to Solve, and then Solve comes back and tells us
that x is Log[5]/Log[2].
That’s the answer given by Solve, and really speaking,
it’s the logarithm of 5 to the base 2.
That’s an example of a logarithm.
This lesson will talk about these logarithmic functions
in more detail and some of their properties.
Basically,  a logarithm is an inverse function
because it is the inverse of an exponential function a^x.
You can think of it as having the property that
a raised to the logarithm of x to the base a is x,
and so is the logarithm of a^x in the base a.
The number a is the base of the logarithm.
Now we have a function called Log in the Wolfram Language
which does these calculations.
The log of 27 to the base 3 is 3 because because 3^3 is 27,
and the logarithm of 1/4^–2 is –2.
Keep in mind that the default base for Log is e,
so the logarithm of e^2 is just 2.
That’s the natural logarithm which is implemented
in the Wolfram Language with base e.
Next let’s take the graph of a logarithm function.
Here’s the graph, and you’ll notice that it’s defined
only for positive x, and the range is all the way from –∞ up to ∞.
The function domain for the logarithm is just the positive numbers,
and the range is all the real numbers.
Now if you look at the limits when x approaches ∞,
then you see that the answer is ∞, and when it approaches 0,
the answer is –∞.
Of course the graph intersects the x axis at x = 1.
Okay. Next let’s take an example
where you have a base which is less than 1.
Now the opposite happens.
You have a function which is still defined on positive numbers,
but it shoots up to ∞ at 0 and goes down to –∞ on the other side.
Domain and range is just the same as before,
but now the limits are the opposite,
so when you approach ∞, you get –∞.
When you approach 0, you get ∞.
That’s the behavior of a logarithm whose base is less than 1.
Finally, the plot has the same x intercept at x = 1.
Now the point is that when you have inverse functions,
then their graphs are reflections of each other in the line y = x.
For example, if you take E^x and Log[x],
then they are inverse functions, and if you look at their graphs,
then they are reflections of each other in the line y = x.
Just the same happens if you take e^–x,
and you see that again you have a reflection,
but that’s slightly harder to see.
The red plot is reflected in the line y = x to give you the blue plot.
Now of course there are lots of properties
of the exponential function,
and in just the same way, you have properties of the logarithm.
So Log[x * y] is Log[x] + Log[y].
But if you have quotients like x/y, then they turn into differences.
Finally if you have powers, then they turn into multiplication.
The log of x^b is b times the log of x.
The point is that logarithms are really useful
because they convert multiplication to addition,
they convert division to subtraction
and they convert powers to multiplication.
Now an important rule is the change of base
where if you have a base x, you can change to base a
by this kind of a quotient.
The logarithm y to the base x is
the logarithm of y to the base a
divided by the logarithm of x to the base a.
Okay. For example, when you get back this answer from Solve,
then that really is the logarithm of 5 to the base 2.
Okay. At long last, we can talk about
the derivatives and integrals of logarithms.
The derivative for Log[x] is just 1/x.
That’s a very nice property, very surprising.
But the fact is that logarithms grow more slowly than polynomials.
Because you have a change of base formula,
you can work out the derivative of
the logarithm of x to the base a as 1/(xLog[a]).
You can apply the chain rule
and work out more complicated derivatives.
Here is a plot of the logarithm and its derivative.
Notice that the logarithm function is only defined for positive x
whereas its derivative is defined for all x,
and that’s an issue which we’ll come back to later in the lesson.
How about the integral of log?
Well, the integral of log is xLog[x] – x,
and that’s a bit hard to prove,
but you can check the answer by doing a derivative,
and you get back the usual function.
The integral of the natural logarithm is xLog[x] – x.
Here is a plot of the integral.
Okay. Now an important application.
The integral of 1/x is possible to compute, but for that,
you need to worry about the fact that the logarithm function
is only defined for positive x whereas 1/x is defined for all x.
To work out that difficulty, what we’ll do is we’ll introduce
a logarithm of the absolute value of x.
Now that’s nicely defined for all numbers, except of course for 0.
Once you have done that, then you can see that the integral of 1/x
is the logarithm of the absolute value of x,
but in the Wolfram Language, the Log function
can handle both positive and negative numbers.
For example, the Log[–2] is the Log[2] plus a complex number.
So in the Wolfram Language, the integral of 1/x is just Log[x].
But in fact, one could write it as Log[|x|] + C.
Okay. Finally, let’s talk about an application.
Here is an exponential decay function.
The n over here is a quantity at time t = 0, and the question is
how long would it take for the function
to reach half of its initial value?
Well, to do that, we solve the equation and get back an answer,
and this answer is called the half-life of the function.
The λ is called the decay constant.
It tells you how fast it decays.
1/λ is called the mean lifetime of the function.
Often when you do such calculations,
you will need to know the logarithm of 2.
The numerical value is approximately 0.693,
and that’s well worth memorizing.
With that, we come to the end of this lesson,
the main point being that logarithms are very useful
in solving exponential equations of this type.
Just like you have properties of exponentials,
you also have properties of logarithms.
The derivative of a logarithm of x is 1/x.
The integral is a lot harder.
It is xLog[x] – x + C.
The integral of 1/x is Log[|x|] + C.
Of course, you can use logarithms
to find the half-life of a function.
That’s a brief introduction to logarithms—
enough for us to now start talking about
the so-called L’Hospital’s rule, which we’ll do next time.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.