Hello, and welcome to Lesson 15 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is linear approximations.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of this lesson. You may recall that the derivative of a function
is calculated by zooming in on it with some limits. Typically you take some limit as,
let’s say, h→0 or some other variable, and the point is that as you get closer and closer
to a desired point, then the function begins to look like its tangent line.
For example, here’s a function f[x] = x^2, and that’s the function, that’s the tangent line.
We can see that very close to the point (1, 1), they both look essentially identical.
You can use this property to approximate a function near a point with its tangent line,
and that’s a dramatic simplification. After all, a curve is a rather complicated object,
and a straight line is perhaps the simplest of geometrical objects. If you can replace a function
with its tangent line, that’s great, and that’s the topic of this lesson. Namely, we’d like to
talk about linear approximations, but we’ll also talk about so-called differentials
and some of their applications.
Let’s begin with the topic of linear approximation. You may recall that the tangent line at any point,
x = a, is given by an equation of that type. Now, the y over here is a point on the tangent line,
but what you could do is to replace y by f[x], the function itself, and then you get
an approximate quality whereby the value of f at x can be approximated by using its derivative
at the point a. This approximation is called the linear approximation of f at a
because the tangent line is being used to approximate f. Here’s a picture. You have the function
and you have tangent line, and the tangent line is now called the linearization.
Linear approximations are a very important tool in calculus, and as an example,
let’s take this function, f[x] = Sqrt[x + 8]. What we want to do is to approximate values of
the square root at 8.98 and 9.03 within this function. Obviously when x is 1,
the square root of 9 is just 3, so what we do is we work near 1, and we get back f'[1] is 1/6.
Now you set up the equation of the tangent line. Tangent is equal to 3 + (1/6)(x − 1),
and you get back the tangent expression. Now when x is 0.98, you are at 8.98.
The next one is 1.03—then you are at 9.03. You can use the tangent line to approximate
the values over there, and those are the square roots at those two points approximately.
Here’s the picture, and in the picture, you see you have the function, the linear approximation
and the values at the nearby points. You can see that the approximations are very, very close
to the original function, though of course they are not exactly the same.
Okay. The question now is how accurate is that approximation? Suppose you want to have
an accuracy of within 0.5 units. Well, here’s the equation. That’s the exact expression
and that’s the tangent. You want that difference to be less than 0.5. What you can do is
set up an equation with the reduced function and solve. Numerically, the values
lie between −6.3 and 14.39. As long as you stay within that range of x, you’ll get an approximation
which is correct within 0.5 units. Now, let’s say you want to increase the accuracy to be less than 0.1.
Then you set up the equation with 1/10 over here, and you get back the values. In this case,
we have a much tighter range from −3.04 to 6.2, roughly.
Okay. In physics, one needs this notion of linear approximation all the time.
For example, when one studies the pendulum and you want to talk about
the period of the pendulum, you start with the equation for the acceleration.
That’s the tangential acceleration at and g is the acceleration for gravity.
θ is the angle that the pendulum makes with the vertical. The point is that
when your rate goes to 0, then sine has got a slope of 1 because cosine of 0 is 1,
and the value of sine at (0, 0)—so near 0 when θ is very small, Sin[θ] is approximately equal to θ.
If you replace the Sin[θ] over there with the θ, then you get back a much simpler equation,
and that’s the one that’s used in physics textbooks at the elementary level. As you go more advanced,
of course you might want a better approximation. Here’s a picture of the actual acceleration,
the current one, and the linear approximation. Of course, you see that they are both
very close by as long as you do not go very far away from 0.
Okay. A related notion is the notion of a differential. To understand that, remember that
the derivative is sometimes denoted as dy/dx. Now dy/dx is the same as f'[x],
so if you kind of cross-multiply, then you get the equation dy = f'[x]dx.
These quantities dx and dy are called differentials, so they represent the change in x
and the change in y respectively. Of course if you’re given dx over here, then you can
work out dy using f'[x]. That’s like a small machine where as you put in different dxs over here,
you get different dys over there. Here’s a picture. The picture is that
as you stay close to x over here, then you can use the approximation to find the change in y.
But of course that’s still approximate, so the question is how does that relate to the actual differences?
Here’s an example where you have a function, and the problem is to work out df,
the approximate change, and the actual change when x goes from 3 to 3.05. Let’s first work out
the exact change using subtraction. Now here is the approximate change given by df,
and you can see they are pretty close to each other. In general, that’s the equation for
the change in f when you make a small change in x. Here’s a picture of the function
and its approximation, and you can see, again, that as long as you stay close to 3,
the approximation is quite good.
Okay. The question is why are differentials important? The reason why they’re important is that
sometimes you may not be able to find Δf that actually is f exactly, and then you might as well
use the differential because they are really quite helpful and easy to work with.
In fact, what we’re talking about over here is exactly the same as linear approximations.
Here’s the equation for a linear approximation in the differential language:
f[x + dx] is the value of f[x] + f'[x]dx. As an example, here is the function Sqrt[x + 8] again.
That’s the differential. You plug in the value of −0.02 for dx, and then you see that it’s pretty close
to the value of the function at 0.98. The point is that differentials are
just another way of talking about linear approximations.
Okay. One important place where they are useful is when you want to estimate errors.
For example, suppose that the radius of the sphere is 11 cm and you know that
the error in measurement is about 0.1 cm. What you want to do is to find out
the maximum error when you calculate the volume of the sphere.
Now the volume of a sphere is 4/3πr^3, so you differentiate that equation. Now volume prime
is the same as dvol/dr, so you can rewrite the equation as dvol = 4π^2dr,
and then because r is 11 and dr is 0.1—that’s the error—you can work out the error in the volume.
It turns out to be 152, approximately. Now that looks like a huge number.
The question is why is it so large? Well, the point is that you really need to talk about
the relative error over here to understand what’s happening. The relative error is the error
divided by the actual volume, and then that is just 0.027, so of course things look
much better than they did before. If you do not plug in the value of r over here,
then the relative error looks like 3dr/r, but that’s just 3 times the relative error and the radius.
That says that the error in the volume is three times the error in the radius,
provided that you talk about relative elements. Now the other way to talk about these errors
is to use a percentage error. The percentage error in this case
is 2.7 for the volume and 0.9 for the radius.
Okay. That brings us to the end of this lesson, and the main point is that
linear approximations are very important in mathematics and science. All we do
in such a case is replace a function by its tangent line. As long as you stay close to the point,
then the approximation is very close to the actual function. One place where you might find them
really useful is in physics, but of course they are also useful in chemistry
and in economics and in finance. Wherever you go, you will find the need to use linear approximations.
Another way of talking about these approximations is to use differentials,
and those are particularly useful when you want to talk about errors in measurements.
That brings me to the end of this lesson. In the next lesson we’ll talk about maxima and minima,
but before doing that, we will have a problem session to go over some examples
for errors and approximations, and then we’ll get back to maxima and minima.
I hope you’ve found this lesson useful. It’s a very important lesson.
Do review it and be ready for the next session. Thank you.