Hello, and welcome to Lesson 24 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic of this lesson is the definite integral.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In the previous lesson, we talked about the Riemann sum
and the limit of said sum for a function f[x].
Usually we picked f to be positive, and if we did that,
then one could interpret the sum as being
the area under the curve corresponding to f.
But there is a slight problem to this approach
because the Riemann sum has lots of practical applications,
such as finding the area under the velocity curve.
Here’s an example.
That’s the velocity of a particle, let’s say.
Here’s a plot.
Then the area under this curve can be interpreted as
the total distance traveled by the particle,
in this case from 0 to 5 seconds, let’s say.
Now the question is what happens if f is negative?
After all, the velocity of a particle can be
either positive or negative depending upon the direction.
That’s the question that we want to answer in this lesson,
and then we will talk about some properties of the Riemann sum.
Let’s begin with a definition.
Because we use Riemann sums so often,
we have given it a special name in mathematics.
It’s called the definite integral.
In fact, there is also a special notation
for that rather cumbersome Riemann sum.
It’s just called integral from a to b f(x)d(x).
That over there, that elongated S, is the definite integral sign
with a and b, the limits, at both the ends.
The S over here, like I said,
is just the elongated S standing for “sum”.
When you find the area under a function curve from a to b,
we’ll say that we are integrating the function from a to b.
Luckily the Wolfram Language has
a very nice built-in function that integrates these functions,
and it’s called Integrate.
Integrate is the function that you’d use
to compute these definite integrals.
For example, let’s look at f[x] = x^2, and you want to integrate,
let’s say, from 0 to 1.
Here’s a Riemann sum and the limit, and you get back the answer 1/3.
But you could just as well use
the Integrate symbol that’s over here.
You integrate from 0 to 1 for x^2,
and you get back just the same answer, 1/3.
Integrate is the function to use
when you want to do definite integration.
Now, the point is that not every function is integrable.
Not every function can be integrated, and that’s because
the limit in the Riemann sum may not converge to a finite value.
Here’s an example.
You have f[x] = 1/x and you’re trying to find the integral.
Notice over here I’m using the full text over here for Integrate
rather than the symbol, and it says over here that this integral
does not converge on 0 to 1, and that’s because
the graph shows that in fact you have an ∞ near 0
because 1/x becomes infinite as you approach 0 from the right.
Luckily in this lesson, we’ll talk about
functions which can be integrated as long as you’re careful.
In general, one has the property that a function is integrable
if it is continuous—no breaks in the graph—
or it has only a finite number of jump discontinuities.
In this case, the point is you actually have
an infinite discontinuity at 0, and that’s a real problem.
Okay. Let’s go on now to talking about functions which have
a negative function value.
For example, you have the function f[x] = –x,
and you want find its area.
Well the point is because it’s negative,
what you do is you find the area from 0 to 1
as if it’s a normal triangle that’s 1/2,
and then you get the minus sign, and you get the answer, –1/2.
if you use integrate, you get back just the same result,
–1/2, for this integral.
Okay. Next point over here is what happens if you have a function
which is both positive and negative.
Let’s take a sine function.
Now we see what happens over here is that the function is
sometimes positive and sometimes negative.
It’s positive from 0 to π, and then negative from π to 2π.
In this case, what you’ll do is you’ll add
all the areas above the x axis
and then you subtract the sum of the areas below the x axis,
and you get back the net area.
Now in this case, of course, we have a positive area
and a negative area, and the net area is 0.
Let’s check that over here with Integrate,
and you do get back the answer is 0 for this area.
Okay. On to some properties of definite integrals.
If you work out the integral from a to b of a function,
then that’s the negative of the area from b to a.
For example, if you work out the integral of x^2 from 1 to 0,
that’s the negative of the area from 0 to 1,
so you have a –1/3 over here and 1/3 over there.
In particular, if a = b, then you have
something which is negative itself, so the area in this case
is just 0, and that makes sense
because there’s no area between a and a to compute.
In our particular case, if you take the integral of f from 1 to 1,
then you get back 0 as expected.
Okay. Properties two.
You see over here that if you have a constant function
and you find the integral from a to b,
then you just get back the constant value times (b – a).
If you have a sum of functions, then the integral is
the sum of f integral and the g integral.
For a difference, the integral of f – g
is the integral of f minus the integral of g.
Finally, you can always pull out constants
from inside integral signs and save yourself some computation.
For the first property, for example, if you want to find
the area from, let’s say, 1 to 5 for the function
with constant height 5, then the answer is just going to be 20.
After all, you have 5 times 4, which is equal to 20.
Okay. The final set of properties is that
if you have three points a, b and c
and you want to work out the area from a to c,
you work out the integral from a to b and then b to c,
and you get back the area from a to c.
Now obviously if a function is non-negative,
then the area also will be non-negative,
and if f is larger than g, then the integral of of f
will be larger than the integral of g.
One last point: if f is kind of sandwiched between
the limits m and the capital M over here,
then the area for f will be sandwiched between the area
for a rectangle with sides m(b – a)
and a larger rectangle with sides M(b – a).
Here’s a picture.
That’s the function f, and the area under f
is sandwiched between the areas of those two rectangles.
That brings me to the end of this lesson.
To summarize, we have given a new name to Riemann sums.
You now call them definite integrals.
These definite integrals have many nice special properties
which makes them easy to compute.
The nice thing about the definite integral is it can handle
functions with both positive values and negative values,
and then you might get answers which are positive
or negative or even 0.
We have a very nice function in the Wolfram Language
which does the work for you.
It’s called Integrate, and that is
a very popular, well-used function in the language.
In the next lesson we’ll talk about
the so-called fundamental theorem of calculus,
which connects the two branches of calculus,
integral calculus and differential calculus, together.
But before we do that, do review this lesson, go over the exercises
and be ready for the fundamental theorem of calculus.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.