Hello, and welcome to Lesson 29 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is volumes of solids.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson.
Thus far we’ve been talking about the area under curves,
and we’ve used integral calculus for doing that.
For example, if you work out this integral over here,
then what you’re really doing is
to work out the area under the curve y = x^2 between 2 and 3.
The point is that you can also use integral calculus
to find the volume of solids, and that would be
a big advancement if we could learn it.
Let’s look at a very simple example of a solid like over here.
What we can do is we can actually calculate
the volume of this solid or others using calculus.
This lesson is about one method for computing such volumes.
The solid that we spoke of just now was a cylinder of course,
and if you think of a cylinder, it can be constructed
by taking a plane region, and then you sweep out a volume.
For example, let’s say you take this disk over here
and you sweep out a volume up to a certain height
and you get a cylinder.
That’s a hint for finding the volume of a cylinder;
namely, you think of it as being composed of disks.
If you want to find the volume of a cylinder, what you do is
you take the base area
and then multiply it by the height to get the volume.
For example, here’s a disk.
You can work out its area,
and that’s a cylinder with that disk as a base and height 4,
and its volume is 4π.
Basically the volume of the cylinder is
the area of the base times the height, which is 4 in this case.
Now of course there are many more
shapes and solids in the Wolfram Language
and you can work out their volumes directly,
but what you might want to do is to work out
the volumes of even more general solids.
Here’s an example.
You have a three-dimensional region.
If you look at this region, you think of it
as being composed of square cross sections.
If you were to slice the region, you would see that
the area of each piece is 4x^2 because you have
squares with lengths and widths of 2x.
The volume of each piece would be 4x^2Δx,
and then you can add them all up, so to speak,
and get the total volume to be the integral of 4x^2dx
between the right limits.
For example, if you want to define the limits as 1 and 3,
then the volume is 104/3.
Okay. Now let’s try and generalize that a bit more.
If you have a solid with cross-section area A[x],
then its volume is the integral from a to b of A(x)dx
where a and b are the limits within which you want to find the volume.
For example, if you want to find the volume of a ball
like over here and the radius is r,
then each cross section has got a radius of √(r^2 – x^2).
So the cross sections of the left end have got very small areas.
As you go to the middle, the area increases.
Basically, the area will be π(r^2 – x^2).
You add them all up and you get the volume of the ball,
which is of course (4πr^3)/3.
You can check that with Volume and get back just the same result.
Okay. Let’s use the same idea to talk about
what are called solves of revolutions.
Here’s a function, and what you can do is
you can take the graph of this function
and revolve it around the x axis, and then you get a solid.
Here’s how we do it.
You use RevolutionPlot3D, and you get this solid
obtained by revolving the curve about the x axis.
Of course you could also revolve it around the y axis
and get a slightly different solid.
The question is how do you work out the volume in these cases?
Okay. What you do is you can again divide the volume into disks,
but in this case, each cross section is a disk whose radius is f[x],
the value of the function f at x, so the volume will be
the integral from a to b of πf[x]^2dx.
Let’s say you want to find the volume from –1 to 1.
We get back the integral over here, which is 2π/5.
Just to remind you, that was the original parabola,
and that was the solid obtained by revolving around the x axis.
Now you might, let’s say, want to revolve it around the line y = 1,
in which case you just subtract off 1
because if you look at the volume over here,
you see that you actually have different radii
depending upon where you are.
Basically you shift down the function by one
to get the correct picture.
Then the radius of each cross section is 1 – f[x],
so you can work out the volume as the integral of π(1 – f[x])^2
between the correct limits.
Similarly, if you want to find, let’s say,
the volume obtained by revolving around the line y = –1,
then you add a 1.
Here’s the picture.
Again, work out the volume with an integral
and you get back the answer.
Basically, shift the function up by 1 in this case.
Now a second method for computing volumes
is the so-called washer method.
The idea is simple.
You have two functions, f and g,
and you look at the area between them
and then you revolve it around the x axis.
Here’s a nice demonstration of that.
You revolve it. It sweeps out the volume.
The question is how do you work out a formula for that volume?
What you do is you remind yourself that now each cross section
is like a washer because it’s got a kind of outer and inner radius.
That’s the area of this washer.
We work out the integral for the volume,
and that’s the method for finding the volume using the washer method.
But of course we might have liked to go around the y axis,
in which case we do just the opposite.
You write f and g as functions of y
and then do a similar integral to get back the answer.
That brings me to the end of the lesson.
The main point is that you can use integrals
to find the volumes of solids,
and that’s quite a powerful idea.
Let’s say if you have a cylinder, then its volume is base times height,
where B is the area of the base.
If you have a more general solid with the cross-sectional area A[x],
then you’ll compute an integral to find the volume.
If you have a solid of revolution
obtained by revolving the function around a certain line,
then you can compute its volume using the formula over here.
Typically you might just want y to be 0,
so you’re revolving around the x axis.
If you have two functions
and you want to revolve the area between them,
then you apply the washer method and apply the formula over here.
Of course you can repeat the same thing
for revolving around the line x = x0.
That’s the end of this lesson about the volume of solids
using the so-called disk method and the washer method.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about another method
which is called the cylindrical shell method.
That’s a little easier in some cases, but that’s for next time.
Do review today’s lesson.
It’s quite a difficult lesson.
I’ll see you next time.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.