Hello, and welcome to Lesson 25 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is the fundamental theorem of calculus.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
So far in this course, we have talked about differential calculus
and a bit of integral calculus.
Now originally, differential calculus arose in the problem of
finding the tangent line to a curve like you see over here—
a sine curve, and you want a tangent line at a point—
and that’s what differential calculus tries to do.
It tries to find the slope of that line at a point.
Now integral calculus, on the other hand, solves the problem
of finding the area under the curve for a function.
If you look at a sine function, then it tries to find
the area under this curve between the two limits over here.
Now what the fundamental theorem of calculus does is
it ties these two ideas together.
In this lesson, what we’ll do is to go over
this very important theorem.
In fact, by far, this is the most basic fact of calculus
that you really should know in order to apply it in practice.
Okay. Let’s begin with the idea of an integral function.
Here I’m defining a function of x
which is given by the integral of t from 0 to x.
Basically what it does it is takes the function g[t] = t
and integrates from 0 to x.
Obviously if x is 0, then the value is 0
because you’re integrating from 0 to 0, so you get back 0.
In general, it calculates the area under the curve from 0 to x.
That’s the integral function f[x],
and here is a graph of the function and x.
What we notice is that as x increases,
the value of this function also increases
because the upper limit over here increases.
The integral function is increasing because the area increases,
in this case, as x increases.
Now the point is that there is actually an explicit formula
for this integral function.
What we do is we begin with the integral from 0 to x
and break it up into n parts, and then we set up the Riemann sum.
In this case, the Riemann sum is going to be g(xi)—
those are sample points—times the width of each subinterval.
Then you sum them all up and take a limit,
and what you get back is x^2/2.
But then you remind yourself that the antiderivative of g[t]
is also t^2/2 plus some constant.
Here’s a check for that.
It looks like the integral function for g[t]
is actually an antiderivative of g[t].
Now that looks very surprising,
so what we’ll do is we’ll try and go a bit deeper
and develop some intuition for why that might be the case.
Let’s begin over here with the integral function again
and think of the difference at two points, f[x + h] and f[x]—
two close-by points with h being very small.
Now that difference over here would just be
the area of a tiny strip because h is very small.
Here’s a picture.
The area of that strip is simply the width times the height,
which is just the g[x], so the area is h * g[x].
But then that is f[x + h] – f[x], so if you divide,
then you get back this relation over here.
As h goes to 0, that says that f'[x] = g[x].
In other words, f[x] is an antiderivative of g[x].
It is this remarkable fact which is summarized
in the fundamental theorem of calculus.
There are two versions.
That’s version 1 over here.
It says that if you have a continuous function g
and you define f to be an integral from 0 to x—
from a to x, in this case—then what you get back
is a function, an integral function, and this integral function
is actually an antiderivative of g.
In other words, f'[x] is equal to g[x].
Let’s try and understand that a bit more
by looking at some examples.
Let’s say you have the function f[x] given by the integral
from 0 to x for Sin(√1 + t^2)dt and you integrate it.
Then you just get back Sin(√1 + x^2).
Here’s a check; namely, if we take
the derivative of the integral function,
you will get back just the original function.
That’s the summary over here which says that
if you take a function, integrate it and then differentiate it,
you get back the original function.
Now the problem is the upper limit itself
might depend on x in some complicated way.
In that case, you must apply the chain rule.
Let’s say g[x] is the integral 0 to x^2
of the same function.
Then if you differentiate that with respect to x,
you will need to account for the x^2,
so you get back a factor of 2x over here.
Let’s check that.
You get back 2xSin(√1 + x^4).
Okay. Let’s now go on to talking about why these integral functions
are useful at all.
There is a function called the Fresnel function
which really quite useful in optics and highway design.
After all, if you design a highway or you design, let’s say,
a very long line, you need to worry about the turns,
and that’s where this Fresnel function comes in.
It’s the integral function of a sine function.
We have this in the Wolfram Language.
It’s called FresnelS.
That’s FresnelS and its derivative on the same plot.
The blue plot is the Fresnel function and the orange plot is
its derivative, which is just the sine function over here.
Another very useful function is the error function,
which is also an integral function,
and that’s used in statistics and probability.
Here is the error function with its derivative.
You have the error function, which is blue,
over here, and the derivative.
It’s just a normal probability curve.
What happens is as you approach very large values,
the probability of everything being covered is almost 1,
so that’s why the values over here are almost 1.
Okay. Now there is another more useful version
of the fundamental theorem, and that’s version 2,
which says that suppose you have a function f
and you find an antiderivative of that function by some means.
Then the value of the integral from a to b of this function f
is the antidervative at b minus the antiderivative at a.
In other words, the integral of an antiderivative
can be found quite easily by simply working out
the difference between the values at the upper and the lower limits.
That says that differentiation and integration
are actually the inverse processes of each other.
That’s quite a remarkable fact.
For example, if you’re asked to find
the integral of x^2 from 1 to 4,
then you first work out the antiderivative, which is x^3/3.
Then you plug in the upper and lower limits,
so you get 4^3/3 – 1^3/3, and the answer 21.
You can check that with Integrate and get back just the same result.
That brings me to the end of this lesson,
but the main point is that the fundamental theorem of calculus
is one of the most important theorems in calculus
because it says that differentiation and integration
are the inverse processes of each other.
In fact, its real utility is to compute integrals
by using antiderivatives
Basically, using the antiderivatives is much easier
than using Riemann sums.
Instead of calculating Riemann sums,
you would calculate antiderivatives.
The next lesson will talk about indefinite integrals.
But before that, do review this lesson over here
because we have covered one of the most important theorems in calculus,
and that’s going to be used all the time.
Let’s stop over here.
Thank you very much,
and I hope you have learned a lot in this lesson.