Hello, and welcome to Lesson 39
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is part 1 of a sample calculus exam.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In this course, we have gone over lots of topics
in both differential calculus and integral calculus.
It’s now time to talk about some exam problems
to apply what you have learned.
The questions I’ll take in this lesson
are similar to what you might see on the AP Calculus AB exam,
but equally well, you might see the questions on other exams
that you might take anywhere in the world
at an introductory calculus level.
Let’s begin with the first question,
which says find the derivative of this function over here at 2.
There are two steps over here:
first, find the derivative,
and secondly, plug in x = 2.
Now to find the derivative,
what you do is you apply the quotient rule—
after all, you have a fraction over there.
The rule says that
you find the denominator times the derivative of the numerator
minus numerator times derivative of the denominator
divided by denominator squared.
Then of course you plug in the value 2.
That’s what I’m doing over here.
Then you get back the answer, and you can check the answer with D.
You get back just the same result.
On to question 2, which says calculate the limit
of this function over here at 5.
Now each term in the function is continuous at 5.
The limit laws say that you can simply plug in the value 5
and work out the answer, so the answer is just 610 – 6Log[5].
You can check that with Limit and you get back just the same result.
Here’s a plot which confirms that you actually have
the limiting value at that point.
On to number 3, which says calculate the integral
from π to 5 of Cos[x] + 1/x.
Now if you apply the fundamental theorem of calculus,
then you first find the antiderivative, which is Sin[x] + Log[x].
You plug in the upper limit and the lower limit and you subtract,
and you get back the answer.
You can confirm the answer with Integrate,
which gives you just the same result.
Here is a plot of the region that we just integrated.
On to number 4, which says find the value of c
which satisfies the mean value theorem for this function.
What you need to do is to work out the value of c
for which you get the mean value for the slope,
basically, at that point c.
First of all, you work out the slope
of the line joining the endpoints.
That’s 13.
Solve the equation—
derivative of the function equal to 13 in the given range.
You get back x as √(7/3).
Work out the function value.
Basically you have a point
at which the mean value theorem is satisfied,
and you can check that with a plot over here.
You see that at that point,
the tangent line has got the same slope
as the line joining the endpoints.
On to number 5, which says find the general solution
of this differential equation.
Now that’s a separable differential equation
because you can separate x and y,
so what you do is think of y' as being dy/dx
and separate the two sides, and you get back the answer,
which you can rewrite as just Exp[Log[–1 + y^2]] = Exp[3x^2 + c].
You have a solution over here, which is y^2 – 1 = c * e^3x^2.
You can plot that solution for different values of c,
and here you see that there are all the different solutions.
That’s a separable differential equation
which you can solve by simple integration.
Next let’s try and find the limit of this function over here at ∞.
Now at ∞, you need to only worry about
the degrees of the numerator and denominator.
Now in this case, they’re the same.
They’re both 3, so you simply need to work with those terms.
The answer is going to be 10x^3/3x^3.
That gives you just 10/3.
You can check the answer with Limit,
and you do get back just the same result.
Here is a plot to visualize what’s happening,
and you do see that the value approaches 10/3, 3.33,
as x approaches ∞.
On to number 7, which says use the trapezoidal rule
to estimate the integral over here.
Now you are required to use five trapezoids,
so what you do is you find the width of each trapezoid
by doing upper limit minus lower limit over 5,
so you get back 8/5 as the width of each trapezoid.
You then work out the approximate integral
by adding the areas of these trapezoids.
Here is the calculation, and I get back the answer 2314.03.
Compare that with Integrate.
It’s only somewhat close, but not very precise.
Here is a plot which shows the actual area
and the trapezoidal approximation.
Okay. On to question 8, which says find the equation of the line
tangent to the graph of this function at (1, –2).
Now the first step, of course, is to find the slope at that point.
You work out the derivative, which is just e^(x – 1) – 3.
Plug in x = 1 and you get back the slope as –2.
You can check that with D.
Basically you work out the derivative and plug in x = 1,
and you do get back the same answer.
By the point-slope formula, the equation on the tangent line
is going to be y minus y1 equal to slope times x minus x1.
Here is a plot which shows that you indeed have the correct solution.
On to number 9, which says for what value of a
is this function over here continuous?
Now this is a piecewise function.
There are two pieces.
There is the part where x is less than 2 and the remaining part,
and the only question is what happens at 2 itself.
Well, for the function to be continuous, the limit from the left at 2
should be equal to the limit from the right at 2.
You solve the equation for that,
00:07:24,000
which is limit as you approach from the left
equal to limit from the right.
Solve that for a, and you get back a as –1.
If a is –1, then you actually have continuity.
Here’s a plot which shows you that
you indeed have no break in the graph when a is –1.
You see over here that a is –1.
On to number 10, which says find the approximate value
of this square root to four decimal places.
Well, keep in mind that the number given to you is very close to √144,
so that’s 12, so you need to work with the function √x
as the underlying function at the point (144, 12).
You first work out the slope at that point.
Write the equation of the tangent line,
and then use that to write the approximation,
which is going to be 12 plus the difference over here over 24.
Let’s check how it compares with the actual value.
You see over here that you actually have
an error which is in the tenth millions.
Okay. Let’s go on to number 11,
which says find the volume of the solid,
which you can obtain by rotating this function around the y axis.
Then you bound it by the y axis itself
and the line x = 2 and the x axis.
Here’s a plot of the region.
Now in this case because you’re revolving around the y,
you use the cylindrical shell method.
Basically you have cylinders of radii x and height –x^3 + 5x,
so that’s the integral to be computed over here.
There’s 2πr * hdx.
Work it out with Integrate, and you get back the volume required.
On to number 12, which says find the extrema of this function
on the interval [2, 6] using the closed interval method.
Now because you have a polynomial, it’s in fact differentiable,
so the first step is to find the critical numbers,
and those are the numbers with slope 0.
What you do is you find a derivative, set it equal to 0
and solve in the given interval for the values of x.
We just find one value, x is 3, so you must check at 2, at 3 and at 6.
Here’s the function.
Work out the value at those three points, and you see now that
you have a maximum over here and a minimum over there,
so you have a maximum at (3, –9) and a minimum at (6, –108).
You can check that with a plot.
You can see you have a maximum at 3 and a minimum at 6.
On to number 13, which says find the derivative
of this function over here.
Now the function has two terms, so for the first term,
you use the product rule, and you get back the first term
times derivative of second term
plus second term times derivative of first.
Then you work out the second-term derivative in the same way.
Get the answer, and then by the difference rule for derivatives,
you simply subtract them like over here to get back the final result.
You can check that with D,
and you see that it does just the same thing.
That brings me to the end of the first part
of the sample calculus exam.
Do review it.
These are not very difficult questions.
The next part will have some more challenging questions,
but by then,
I hope you’ll be ready to take up those more difficult questions.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.