Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 8 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this session is area between curves and volume.
The first few problems are about areas,
and the next few problems are about volumes.
Let’s begin with problem number 1,
which says compute the area between the curves f and g
given by x^2 – 2 and x^3 + x + 7 between the limits –1 and 3 for x.
Here is a plot of the functions,
and it’s clear that the orange line is above,
but that corresponds to g, so g is greater than f in the region.
The area would be the integral of g minus f from –1 to 3.
Simplify a bit, and that is the answer for the area.
Problem number 2 says find the area
enclosed by these two curves over here.
Again the functions are given to you,
but you’re not given the points of intersection,
so let’s find them with Solve.
Those are the intersection points.
Next you plot to get a geometrical picture,
and it’s clear now that the –x^2 – 2 is the one that’s dominating,
so f is greater than g, so you must do f minus g in the integral.
You do that for the given limits,
and then you get the answer for the integral.
Problem number 3 is the same kind of thing,
but now with x in terms of y.
You’ve got two functions of y, 2y + 4 and y^3 – y,
between the limits –2 and 2.
You need to use ParametricPlot to get the correct picture,
and when you do that, it’s clear that f is greater than g
because f is to the right of g.
You work out f minus g between the limits,
and here is the answer for the integral.
Problem number 4 is about two functions of y,
but again this time you’re not given the points of intersection,
so you want to find the area enclosed between them.
You use the Solve function to find where they intersect.
Here is a parametric plot showing you what happens,
and it’s clear that g this time is greater than f,
so you do g minus f and compute the integral,
and you get back the answer for the area between those two curves.
Number 5. Now we’re on to volumes.
You’re given a solid with hexagonal cross sections,
and you’re told that the area of those cross sections
is given by 6√3x^2.
The question is to find the volume of the solid from 0 to 5.
Here’s a plot, but it doesn’t really matter what the details are;
the main point is you have a formula for the volume
as the integral from a to b of the area.
In this case, you have 0 to 5 of the area,
and that’s easy to compute,
so you get back the volume in this example.
On to number 6, where you’re asked to find the volume
of this rather difficult-looking solid
which has a base which is a semicircle.
You can see it over here.
You want to compute the volume for this solid
when the cross sections are equilateral triangles.
Now that’s the difficult part.
How do you compute the area of each cross section?
Well, the area for an equilateral triangle is x^2(√3/4),
but x in this case is just the semicircle function over here,
so the area is (36 – x^2)(√3/4).
Work out the limits, but those are the limits
where the semicircle cuts the x axis, which are –6 and 6,
so that’s the area to compute.
Work it out and you get the required volume.
Okay. On to number 7, which says compute the volume of the solid
which is created when the region bounded by
this function and the x axis is revolved around the x axis.
That’s the plot of the solid, and the point over here is that
you have a semicircle of radius 2, so the endpoints of the integral
will be –2 and 2 because that’s where
the semicircle intersects the x axis.
Now apply the disk method, so you chop the solid up into small disks,
and each disk has the √(4 – x^2) as the radius, so it’s πr^2.
Work out the volume with the disk method, and that’s the answer.
Now of course in this simple case, you have a ball with a radius 2,
so its volume is 4(r^3)π/3.
That’s just the same result that we got
a little while ago using Integrate.
On to number 8, which says find the volume of the solid created
between this function over here
and the x axis-bounded rotate from –π to π.
Okay. Again over here use the disk method.
When you use the disk method, you see that each cross section
has got radius (xSin[x])^2,
so you work out the volume with the disk method in this case.
Okay. On to a similar kind of calculation, but now for y functions.
You have a region that’s bounded by 2y^2 on the y axis,
and you want to work out the volume of the solid from y = 1 to y = 3.
That’s the picture of the solid.
Apply the disk method, but this time the radius is 2y^2.
Use the formula for the disk method,
and you get back the volume.
Okay. On to number 10, which says compute the volume of the solid
created when the region bounded by 2x and (x^2)/3
from x = 0 to x = 6 is revolved around the x axis.
Now there are two functions over here.
When you plot over here, you see you’ve got a region
bounded by two functions,
and that’s a good case to apply the washer method to.
We apply the washer method.
The outer radius is 2x from here.
The inner radius is (x^2)/3.
You simply apply a difference of the radii square over here,
so you get π times the outer radius squared
minus the inner radius squared and work out the volume
with the washer method.
On to number 11, which talks about find the volume created
when the region bounded by (y^4)/8 and 2y^2 from those two limits
is revolved around the y axis.
Here’s a plot.
Once again, what you need to do is to apply the washer method
because you’ve got two functions.
Apply the washer method, compute the volume
by doing π times the difference of the squares of the radii,
and that gives the answer for the volume.
Okay. On to number 12, and that’s about computing the volume
of the solid created when the region bounded by this function
and the x axis and the lines given over here
is revolved around the y axis.
Now the point here is the y axis,
so you need to apply the cylindrical shell method.
Okay. That’s the solid over here.
You break it up into small cylinders, and keep in mind that
for a cylinder method, you have to have 2πrh
where h is the function definition.
So you do that and you get the volume back,
but this time using the cylindrical shell method
because you are revolving around the y axis, not the x axis.
Number 13 says find the volume of the solid created
when the region bounded by this, the y axis
and the two values given over here is revolved around the x axis.
Once again, that’s the plot, but apply the cylindrical shell method
because you have revolving around the x rather than the y axis.
You do 2πrh where r is y and h is the function expression.
Apply that and you get back the volume
using the cylindrical shell method.
Finally, on to number 14.
That says compute the volume of the solid created
when the region bounded by –x^2 + 2 and the x axis
is revolved around the line y = 4.
If you think about it, we’ll apply the disk method,
but this time the radii will be obtained
by subtracting the function value from 4
because 4 is the line around which you are rotating, y = 4.
Then you work out the endpoints, get the integral over here.
That’s πr^2dx.
Put in the limits, and you get back
the answer for the volume in the disk method.
That brings me to the end of this problem session.
I hope you have learned these very important ideas,
and I’ll see you next time.
Thank you.