Hello, and welcome to Lesson 22 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is antiderivatives.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
So far, we have been talking about derivatives of functions.
For example, the derivative of 3x with respect to x is just 3.
Now let’s say you want to go backward.
You want to find a function whose derivative is 3.
Now of course in this case, you already know that 3x is the answer, or it is an answer,
but in this lesson, we’ll go over that for many different kinds of functions.
This idea of going back has many applications.
For example, if you’re given the particle’s velocity function in a problem,
you could go out and work out the position of a particle.
That’s the main theme for today,
to try and go backward and figure out a function whose derivative is a given expression.
That’s the topic of antiderivatives.
The function with a given derivative f is called the antiderivative of f.
Now let’s take f equal to x.
The question is what is its antiderivative?
Then what you could do is you could actually use the power rule, but you do it in reverse.
You have x^2, so increase the exponent by one to get the x^2,
and then you would divide by the new exponent, so the answer is x^2/2.
But that’s only one possible answer you’ll see soon.
Let’s confirm with D, and you’ll see that the derivative of x^2/2 is indeed x.
We have found an antiderivative of x, and that’s x^2/2.
Here’s a plot of x and the antiderivative.
Okay. This is the function, and that’s the antiderivative we found out.
Now we said over here that x^2/2 is an antiderivative of x,
and that’s because every function has more than one antiderivative.
For example, in our case,  x^2/2 + 1 is also an antiderivative.
In general, if you have one antiderivative,
you have many more by simply adding arbitrary constants.
This expression over here gives you a family of antiderivatives.
Here’s a plot to show that for the function we just talked about, the function x:
you have x over here, the function, and all those curves are antiderivatives for x.
Notice that each of them is simply a vertical shift of x^2/2 either up or down.
Okay. Some rules for antiderivatives.
The antiderivative of a sum is the sum of the antiderivatives.
For example, if you want to work out the antiderivative of x^2 + x^3,
then you would work out the first answer, which is x^3/3, the second one, x^4/4,
and then you add the constant c and you’re done.
That’s the way to find the antiderivatives of a sum.
Next if you have a difference,
then you can simply work out the antiderivatives of each term
and then find the difference of those antiderivatives.
For example, if you have 5 – x^4,
then the answer is 5x from the 5 and x^5/5 from the x^4.
That’s the proof that the answer is correct.
These rules correspond to the sum and difference laws for differentiation.
We also have a constant multiple law which says that
if you want to work out the antiderivative of kF'[x], then the answer is kF[x] + C.
Now in just the same way, there are rules for products and quotients,
but they are much harder to use.
Okay. How about trig functions?
Let’s say you have the trig functions over here, the six basic ones—
sine, cosine, tangent, secant, cosecant and cotangent—and those are the derivatives.
For example, if you want to work out the antiderivative of Sec[x]Tan[x].
You look back over there, and the answer is Sec[x] from here plus the constant C.
Here is a table of all those antiderivatives.
The antiderivative of cosine is sine, et cetera.
Now of course in each case, you must put the +C at the end,
but I haven’t done that in this table.
Okay. As an example of how we can apply all this knowledge,
let’s try and find the general antiderivative of the function f over here.
You have a sum over here, so you can apply the sum rule,
and you see that the antiderivative of 3Sin[x] is –3Cos[x] + C.
Let’s check that. That’s correct.
Then what you do is you break up this over here into two terms by writing it as a difference.
You simply separate out the terms and then you work out the antiderivative separately,
so you get 4x^5/5 + C for the first term,
and –x^–1/2 has the antiderivative –x^1/2/(–1/2) + C.
The complete antiderivative is over here.
Here’s a check that each part is correct
so you can find the complete answer for the whole expression
by simply adding things together,
and here’s a verification that everything is correct.
In general, you will need to combine rules to get the answer for the full problem.
Okay. These antiderivatives are very useful for solving differential equations.
What are these? They are equations that involve derivatives.
Now in general, it’s pretty difficult to solve differential equations,
but one can solve some simple ones with what we’ve learned so far.
For example, if I said solve the equation f'[x] = x√x where f[1] = 3,
then what you would do is you would first work out the antiderivative over here,
and then we’ll apply the condition f[1] = 3.
The antiderivative in this case is 2x^(5/2)/5 + C.
Let’s check that. Then you want to find the value of C.
What you do is you plug in x = 1 in the equation—remember that f[1] is 3—
and work out the value of C. You have that the required solution,
the particular solution, is (2x^(5/2) + 13)/5.
Now of course we have a very nice function in the Wolfram Language called DSolve
which will do that for you automatically, but before that,
let’s just clear the function f because we defined it earlier on and call DSolve,
and you get back just the same answer.
That’s the differential equation, that’s the condition f[1] = 3,
and you simply want to solve for f[x] with variable x,
and DSolve will do that for you quite easily.
Okay. A slightly harder example.
Let’s take a second-order differential equation where you have a second derivative over here.
You’re given f'' and two conditions, f[0] and f[1].
What you do is you first of all work out f'[x] by one antiderivative computation,
and you get 4x^3 – 3x^2 – 8x + C. Let’s check that.
Then what you do is you start with the expression over here
and work out its antiderivative and you get another answer, so the answer over here.
Okay. Then you want to solve for C and D,
so you take the expression from there and you plug in the values given to you,
and you find the value of c is 5 and the value of d is 1.
You’ve worked out a particular solution as shown over here.
Of course, you can do all that with DSolve automatically
and get back the same answer as you did by hand.
Okay. Now an application to physics.
Let’s say you’re given the acceleration of a particle as 6t^2 – 10,
and you’re given that the velocity at time t[0] = –4 and the position at that time is 3.
You want to work out the position function.
For the first step, you work out the velocity by antidifferentiation as 2t^3 – 10t + C.
Here’s a check for that.
Then you work out the position function by one more antidifferentiation.
Here’s a check for that, and then you apply the given conditions
because you want to work out C and D over here. So v[0] = –4, s[0] = 3.
You plug in those values, and you find that you actually have C goes to –4 and D goes to 3,
so that’s the solution for the problem;
namely, that you have an expression with t^4/2 – 5t^2 – 4t + 3.
Now you can use the same method but automatically by calling DSolve,
and you find you get the same answer.
Okay. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson.
The main point is that the antiderivative of a function is a function g such that g'[x] = f[x].
Now these antiderivatives come in families.
You don’t always just get one;
you get lots of them, so you always add an arbitrary constant, +C.
You can find them by using the usual differentiation rules, but you need to go in reverse.
Now the most important application in practice
is to solve differential equations using these antiderivatives.
Given a differential equation, you can solve it,
but if you’re given some extra conditions,
you can actually work out a particular solution for that differential equation.
Finally these antiderivatives are really useful in physics
when you want to analyze the one-dimensional motion of a particle.
With that, we are now ready to go on into what is called integral calculus.
What we’ve done so far is called differential calculus.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about integral calculus,
but before we do that, do make sure you’ve gone through today’s lesson
and you’re ready to take on the next topic, which is integral calculus.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.