Hello, and welcome to Lesson 36
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is slope fields and Euler’s method.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
The fact is that some differential equations
are very difficult to solve by hand.
For example, here’s a differential equation that looks quite simple,
y'[x] = y[x]^2 – x, and you want to solve it
with the condition that when x = 1, then y = 0.
Now the function DSolve can certainly solve this equation,
but the solution is huge
and involves these so-called Bessel functions,
which occur in the oscillations of membranes and elsewhere.
In such cases, it is much easier to just visualize
what the solution to the curve looks like for any initial value.
In this lesson, we’ll learn how to use slope fields
to see the behavior of such differential equations.
As an introduction to slope fields,
let’s consider the differential equation y'[x] = f[x, y].
If you want to find the slope field for this equation,
what you do is you plug in the values for x and y
in the function f and then plot the slope at that point.
What does that mean?
It means that you draw a small line segment
with slope close to the value you get from the expression f[x, y].
Then you get a slope field, which gives you a very general picture
of the solutions to the differential equation.
It’s not very precise, but it’s good enough.
Luckily we have two functions in the Wolfram Language.
There’s StreamPlot and VectorPlot, which can be used for this purpose.
For example, let’s go back to the earlier differential equation,
and you can use VectorPlot by saying  over here,
or StreamPlot with the same kind of specification,
and you get back the vector field,
the slope field over here and the stream field over there.
The stream field has a solution of curves
instead of just the arrows like over here.
Now in some cases, what we really want
are the particular solutions to a differential equation.
For example, in the first case for our introduction,
we had the differential equation with the initial value y[1] = 0.
To find that out, you can use the StreamPoints option like over here
and get the particular solution curve
on the vector plot or on the stream plot.
A couple more examples.
Here is the vector field for x – y, the stream plot.
You see over here that when x is very large,
then you have a positive slope from the expression over here.
When y is very large, you have a negative slope.
The same thing can be worked out with VectorPlot over here
with the initial value y[0] = 0.
Okay. Another example.
Let’s take f to be x * y.
Now what happens over here is the stream plot
depends upon where you are.
If you are in the first or the third quadrant,
then both x and y are the same sign,
so you have positive slopes,
and just the opposite happens in the other two quadrants.
If you want the particular solution y[1] = –1,
you plug that over here in StreamPoints
and you get back the plot for that particular curve.
Okay. Now in practice, you might just want to estimate
the solution for a differential equation,
and that can be done with Euler’s method.
The idea is this.
Here’s the same example from the introduction,
and you want to find the value at 2
starting with the value at 1 equal to 0.
What you do is you start with (1, 0)
and plug it in the slope over here, so the slope is –1.
Then write down the linear approximation, which is y = –(x – 1).
If you plug in 2, then the approximate value is –1.
But of course what you could do is
you could go off a little bit on the tangent line,
then change direction,
and then that will give you a better approximation.
For example, you could go halfway from 1 to 2 up to 1.5,
and then you could change your direction with the new slope,
and you get a better approximation
from the linear approximation over here,
and you get back the solution at 2 to be –0.125.
Here’s the idea behind Euler’s method.
The idea is that when you take very short steps along tangent lines,
you get much better estimates.
Basically what you’ll do is
you’ll use an equation of this type over here
where every value of y depends upon the previous value.
Here’s a visual for the case where y' = y and y[0] = 1.
Of course in this case, the exact solution is just e^x
because its derivative is itself.
If you have only one point, then you get back just a tangent line,
the red line over here.
If you take two points, you go halfway down,
then you change direction and you get a better approximation.
Then of course you could take three points, four points, et cetera.
By the time we get to ten points like the green line over here,
then you get a really nice approximation.
Of course the top-most graph is the actual solution.
With Euler’s method, the approximation improves
as you take more and more points.
You have one point, then two points, then ten points
and then you get closer and closer to the solution.
Now Euler’s method relies on so-called recurrence relations.
What’s that?
Well, here’s the relation for Euler’s method, and what happens is
let’s say you want to find the value of y2—so n is 2.
Then that depends upon y1 and x1.
You need x1 and y1 to work out the value of y2.
Then you say I don’t know the value of y1,
so to find the value of y1, you need the value of x0 and y0.
But of course, those are just the initial conditions.
In practice, if you want to find, let’s say, y100,
you need to go around all the way to 0,
and that’s of course a very tiresome thing to do by hand.
On the other hand, it’s a perfect thing to do by computer,
so it’s very easy to program on a computer.
After a couple of lessons, we’ll talk about how to make
a program that calculates the points from Euler’s method.
That’s the end of this lesson, and the main point is
you can use slope fields to visualize
the behavior of differential equations.
We have two nice functions.
We have VectorPlot and we have StreamPlot to plot these slope fields.
You can use Euler’s method
to estimate the solution at various points,
and because that’s rather tedious to do,
we can actually program it with a computer,
but that you’ll learn very soon.
The next lesson is about separable differential equations.
Before we do that, do review today’s lesson.
It’s an important lesson for differential equations.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.