Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 10
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this session is L’Hospital’s rule
and differential equations.
Let’s begin with problem 1 for the session.
The question is find the limit of Sin[5x]/Sin[7x] as x approaches 0.
Now if you simply plug in 0 over here, you get 0/0,
so that’s an indeterminate form,
which means you should try and apply L’Hospital’s rule.
You find the derivative of the numerator and denominator,
and you plug in x as 0.
You get back 5/7, which happens to be the correct answer in this case.
Here is a plot of the function near 0
that shows the limit value as well.
On to number 2, which says find the limit as x approaches ∞
of x^2/Log[x].
If you again plug in ∞, you get ∞/∞.
That’s indeterminate, so you find the derivatives of the numerator
and denominator and plug in ∞, and now you get ∞,
which is the correct answer, as seen from Limit.
Here’s a plot that shows that
the function does approach ∞ as x approaches ∞.
On to number 3, which says find the limit
as x approaches ∞ of √(2x)e^–x.
If you plug in ∞, you get ∞ * 0 because e^–∞ is 0.
Let’s rewrite that as √2x/e^x.
That’s the quotient.
Then you find the derivatives of the numerator and denominator
and plug in ∞, and you get back 0,
which is the correct answer, as seen from Limit.
Here’s the plot that shows what happens to the function
as you approach ∞.
On to number 4, which says find the limit of 1/(x – Cot[x])
as x approaches 0 from the right.
Now if you simply plug in 0, you get back ∞ – ∞.
As we’ve done earlier in the lesson, we simply rewrite the expression
by taking a common denominator—xSin[x] in this case—
and you get back the expression over here.
Then you work out the derivatives of the numerator and denominator,
but again there’s a problem because you get back 0/0 if you plug in
because you have 0 * Sin[0],
and you have another 0 over there and a 0 over there.
So you apply L’Hospital again, and then you get back the answer 0,
which happens to be the correct limit in this case.
Here’s a plot of the function which shows the limit is indeed 0
as you approach 0 from the right.
Okay. On to number 5, which says find the limit of x^x^2
as x approaches 0 from the right.
If you simply plug in 0, you get 0^0,
so that means you must take logarithms.
If you do that, you get back x^2 * Log[x].
Plug in 0 and you get 0 * –∞ because the logarithm of 0 is –∞.
But then you rewrite that as Log[x]/x^–2,
and now you can apply L’Hospital.
You get back 0, but that’s 0 for Log[y],
so the limit itself must be 1.
You can check the answer from Limit itself, and you get back 1.
Here is a plot of the function,
which clearly shows that it approaches 1  as you approach 0.
Okay. On to number 6, which says compute the limit
as x approaches 0 from the right-hand side of (1/x)^x.
If you simply plug in 0, you get ∞^0, and so you apply logarithms.
You get y = (1/x)^x, giving you log(y) = log((1/x)^x).
Then apply the law of logarithms to get xLog[1/x].
That’s –xLog[x].
Now if you plug in 0, you get 0 * ∞ at 0.
You write the expression and then you plug in 0 again.
You get ∞/∞, so apply L’Hospital’s rule.
You get back 0, but that’s the value for log(y),
so the actual answer for the limit is 1.
You plug in that value, 1, and try Limit again, and you get back 1.
Here’s a plot around 0 which says
that the limit is indeed equal to 1.
Okay. On to number 7, which says find the limit as x approaches π/2
from the left of Sin[x]^Sec[x].
Now if you want to plug in π/2, you get 1^∞
because that’s 1 over here and ∞ over there, so apply a logarithm.
You get log(y) = log(sin^sec(x)(x)).
That’s secant times Log[Sin[x]].
Plug in ∞, π/2 and you get ∞ * 0.
Rewrite the expression as Log[Sin[x]]/Cos[x].
Plug in π/2.
You get 0/0, so you can apply L’Hospital’s rule and you get back 0,
but that’s the limit for log(y), so the actual limit is 1.
You can confirm the answer with Limit, and you do get back 1.
Here’s a plot of the function around π/2,
which actually shows the limit is equal to 1.
On to number 8, which says use Euler’s method,
the approximation method, with size 0.05
to find the approximate solution
of this differential equation over here at 0.1 given that y[0] = 1.
That’s the right-hand side.
You want to find the value at 0.05 first
because you’re going in steps of 0.05,
so you start with the initial value plus the step size
times the initial value of f, and you get back 0.95.
Then you plug in 0.1.
You start from the earlier value
and you add 0.05 times f[0.05] times value,
the earlier value, and you get back 0.899625.
NDSolveValue, which is a much more accurate function,
gives you a slightly different value,
but we can see that the answer is still quite correct,
and NDSolveValue simply improves the estimate by about 0.001.
On to number 9, which says use Euler’s method with step size 0.05
to find the value at 2.15
of this differential equation given that y[2] = 3.
That’s the right-hand side.
You first of all work out the value at 2.05.
You start with 3 plus the step size
times the value at 2 itself for the slope, and you get back 3.
Now start at this value over here,
and then you get the next value at 2.1.
Repeat the same procedure, and you get the value at 2.15.
You look at NDSolveValue and you get a pretty close answer,
which differs from it by around 0.033.
On to number 10, which
says
which of the following slope fields over here
is the field for y' = 2x – y?
Now what you do is you try and experiment at some points.
Suppose you have (0, 0).
You plug back over there and get 0 – 0 is 0, so the slope should be 0.
But now if you look at B, the slope at (0, 0) is clearly positive,
so B is out.
B cannot be the answer.
Then you go, let’s say, at (1, –1).
Plug in the values, so you get 2 – (–1).
That’s 3, so the slope should be positive.
But you see that for A at (1, –1), the slope is actually 0,
so A is out as well.
Now go to (1, 0).
The slope should again be positive, but if you look at D,
then at (1, 0)—that’s right over here—the slope is negative,
so D is out as well.
B doesn’t work, A doesn’t work, D doesn’t work,
so the correct answer is C.
You can actually check that with StreamPlot,
and you do see that the correct answer is C.
On to number 11, which says which of these, A, B, C or D,
is the slope field for y' = y^2.
Now if you plug in (0, 0), you get the answer 0 over here,
but at C, you see that there’s actually no slope
defined over here at (0, 0), so C is out.
C could not be the right answer.
For (1, 1), the slope would be positive again,
but if you look at D, at (1, 1)—that’s right over here—
the slope is negative, so D is out.
Then you look at (0, –1), another trial point.
If you plug back over there, y^2 is positive.
The slope should be positive, but for A at (0, –1)—
so (0, –1) is here—the slope is actually negative,
so A is out as well.
C doesn’t work.
D doesn’t work.
A doesn’t work.
The correct answer is B,
and you can confirm the answer with StreamPlot.
The correct answer is B.
You can see over here the match
between B over here and the StreamPlot over there.
On to number 12,
and now we’re talking about separable differential equations.
Here’s a differential equation, y' = x^4y^2.
You can separate it with two functions, f and g.
Then you rearrange, and you get back the equation over here.
Integrate both the sides.
Now if you solve for y, you get –5/(x^5 + 5C),
but that’s just a constant,
so you can check the answer with DSolveValue,
and you do get back the same result.
On to number 13, which says find the solution of y' = Sec[x]^2y
given that y[0] = 2.
Now you can separate this problem over here
because you have Sec[x]^2 over here times y over there.
You rearrange, integrate and then you solve for y,
so y = Ce^Tan[x].
Plug in the initial conditions so when x is 0, y is given to be 2.
That says that C is 2 from here, so the solution is y = e^Tan[x].
You can check the answer with DSolveValue,
and you do get back the same result.
On to number 14, which says find the solution of y' = e^(3x – y)
given that y[0] = 0.
Now in this case, to separate, what you do is
you break up the exponential into two parts as e^3x * e^–y.
You have two parts for the exponential.
You’ve got f[x] and g[y].
You can rearrange the equation like over here,
and then you can integrate.
You see over here that y must be log(C + (e^3x/3)).
We still need to find C, but keep in mind that y[0] is 0,
so when you plug in those values,
you’ll find that C is equal to 2/3 because the logarithm of 1 is 0,
so C + 1/3 = 0, so C must be 2/3.
That’s the solution from hand calculation,
and I can check the answer with DSolveValue,
and you do get back just the same result.
That brings me to the end of this problem session.
Thank you very much.