Hello, and welcome to Lesson 12 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic of this lesson is implicit differentiation.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the topic. So far, all of the functions that we have considered
are in so-called explicit form. For example, here is a function f which is defined to be x^2 – x + 1.
Every time I give you a value of x, you could work out the value of f at that x.
That’s an explicit function, but sometimes you have a function that’s defined only implicitly.
For example, here’s an equation x^2 + y^2 = 4, and surely y is a function of x—it depends on x—
but it does so in an indirect implicit way. Now of course in this case, you could solve the equation
and work out y in terms of x and you get back two solutions, so really, you have two functions of x,
and then you could plot them. What you see is that you have a circle,
and the first solution is the bottom of the circle and the second solution is the top half,
so that’s of course why you need two functions rather than one to describe the problem.
That’s solution of an implicit function, and today is what we will do is to talk about
how you can find derivatives implicitly in the Wolfram Language.
Let’s try and do this in one way. For example, you could take the two functions
from the earlier page, from the earlier slide, and try to work out their derivatives separately.
You get back two answers. Now notice that each answer is of the form minus x or y—
so that’s x, that’s y and both answers have a certain pattern to them.
But then what we’ve got to remember is that this over here is the kind of upper branch,
so the derivative for the upper branch comes from here. If you plug in, let’s say, √2 and √2,
that point, then what you get back is a slope of −1 at x = √2 for the upper branch.
You can then plot the line, the tangent line, and the circle, and you see that
that’s the correct solution. But of course this is a very roundabout way of doing things,
and what we want to do today is to try and do things in a much more clear-cut, simple way,
and that’s the notion of implicit differentiation. The idea is very simple.
Whenever you find the derivative with respect to x, you work just as before;
but if you have a y anywhere in your expression, then you also make sure to multiply by dy/dx.
For example, here’s the equation from the earlier slide and you have x^2 + y^2 = 4,
so the derivative of x^2 is 2x, and the derivative of y^2 is not just 2y, but 2y times dy/dx.
That’s just the chain rule. Okay. Once we have done that, then from the equation
you can solve for dy/dx and find the answer is negative x or y, just as we noted earlier.
That’s the technique for doing implicit differentiation, and now I’ll show you how we can do it
in the Wolfram Language. Let’s take up the circle again. There are two ways to go about it.
In the first method, what you do is you replace y by y[x]. Now the Wolfram Language knows that y is
indeed a function of x, and then you tell D to find the derivative. Then you solve that derivative
for y'[x]. What you get back is exactly what we guessed earlier on—namely, negative x or y.
Okay. Now we can plug in values for both x and y. For example, if you’re at the point (−1, √3)
where the slope is 1/√3, and you can then find a tangent and plot both the tangent and the graph,
and you see that the answer is correct. That’s the first method. The first method is replace y by y[x].
The second method is slightly different. You start with the equation, but now do not make a replacement.
Instead, you tell D that y is no longer a constant, and that’s done with the NonConstants option.
When you do that, you get back an equation for D. You solve it and you get back
just the same derivative as before, but now you only have a y instead of y[x].
There are two ways: replace x/y or use the NonConstants option. Usually we’ll work with the first way.
That’s a little more natural, but there will be another case where we’ll actually try and use
the second method, but that will be in the exercises for the lesson.
Okay. Having done this preparatory work, we can now find lots of derivatives with this method.
For example, here is a famous curve called the Folium of Descartes. That’s the equation
of the curve. We want to find the derivative, so you replace y by y[x], work out the derivative,
solve for it like over here and replace x and y with the values that you want to work with, 2 and 2,
and you get back the derivative of this curve at (2, 2). Work out the tangent line,
and then you plot the curve and the tangent, and it looks just right.
As another example, let’s take up the ellipse. That’s like a distorted circle,
and you want to find the tangent line at the point (1, (−√3/2)). Again, you do the same thing:
replace y with y[x], solve the equation, plug in the values, get back the slope, set up the equation
for tangent and you get back the plot of the ellipse with the tangent line. Okay.
From the ellipse, we go on to the hyperbola. That’s the hyperbola equation. You want to work
at a certain point that’s given to you. Again, replace y with y[x], solve for y'[x],
plug in the values and you get back the slope. Write down the equation for tangent,
and then you plot the tangent and the curve, and you get back this nice picture.
Notice that in all these plots, I’m using the ContourPlot function to plot the curve itself
while using the Plot function to plot the tangent line.
Okay. My next example is the so-called cardioid. That’s like a heart-shaped curve,
which is a pretty difficult equation. Here’s the equation of the curve. Replace y with y[x] as before,
find the derivative. It’s 1. Write our tangent equation, and then you plot the tangent of the curve,
and you get back this beautiful plot of the cardioid.
Another example is the so-called devil’s curve. Now it doesn’t matter
how difficult or easy the equation looks. You do just the same thing. You take the equation,
replace y with y'[x] everywhere. You’ve just seen it before, so now I’ll plug in
the correct x and y values, and when you do that, you get back the slope.
Write down the equation for tangent, so that’s the y1, if you like, from your work on straight lines;
that’s the slope; and that’s x − x1. Okay. You plot the tangent and the curve.
Notice one thing: the tangent line at this point might actually pass the curve again
because the curve in this case is like a loop attached to the location.
Okay. Another example is the so-called kampyle of Eudoxus. That’s the equation,
but just the same method works: replace y by y[x], solve, replace values and you get back the slope.
That’s the tangent line over here, and then you plot the tangent line and the curve,
and you get back the correct solution.
Having talked about derivatives, let’s now spend just a few minutes talking about multiple derivatives.
Here’s an equation. You want to work out not just the first derivative, but also the second derivative
with implicit differentiation. You write the equation down. Replace y by y[x],
solve and find the derivative. Then you find the second derivative by putting the two over here
for the second derivatives, and you get back the second derivative.
Unfortunately, the second derivative has the first derivative in it, but then you can use
the earlier step to plug in values. You plug in the first solution into the second one,
and you get back the second derivative now in a much simpler form
where it depends only on x and y.
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson. Basically, there are two ways
to compute the derivatives of implicit functions. In the first one, we express, let’s say,
y as a function of x. In the second one, we could use the NonConstants option.
Now both methods have got their advantages and disadvantages, but overall,
the first method is much closer to what you do by hand, and I recommend that
you follow the first method. Of course we saw lots of interesting curves, and you could plot them
and then actually work out the derivatives, and ContourPlot is a really good function
for plotting these curves. That’s the end of this lesson. The next lesson will talk about rates of change,
but before doing that, you should definitely review today’s lesson, try lots of examples
and make yourself ready for the next lesson. Of course, we’ll also have a problem session
before we go onto the next lesson. Thank you very much.
I hope you’ve enjoyed the lesson. I’ll stop there.