Hello, and welcome to Lesson 13 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is rates of change in the sciences.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
Let’s say you have a particle which moves along a straight line, for example.
The position at time t is given by this function s[t] that’s t^3 + 2t – 2. Now once you have
the position as a function of time, what you can do is to compute the derivative,
and then that will give you the velocity of the particle at time t. Here’s velocity. That’s 3t^2 + 2.
Once you have both s and v, you can then work out their values at any time. For example,
at t = 10, the values are 1,018 and 302. Having done that, you can also plot
the position and velocity as a function of time over a certain period of time—in this case,
from 0 to 20. In this very simple example, you see that the derivative gives you
a nice way of approaching a problem in mechanics. What we’ll do in this lesson is
to explore the applications of differential calculus in the sciences in various different ways.
Let’s again take up an example in mechanics where you have the position being given
as a function of time like over here. You could work out the velocity of course
as the first derivative, but you could also work out the acceleration, which is the second derivative.
Once we have done that, we could ask questions. For example, you could ask
when is the particle at rest? Well, it’s at rest when the velocity is 0. You could solve that equation
and find out that the particle is at rest when t is either 2/3 or 2. Then you can plot the position,
the velocity and the acceleration and get their graphs. You see that the position is given by
the blue graph over here. The velocity is the graph over there, and it clearly intersects
the time axis at around 2/3 and 2. The acceleration is a linear function of time.
The derivative is a very powerful way of studying problems in mechanics.
Let’s go on to another example where let’s say you want to talk about the linear density of a rod.
Now if you have a rod and, let’s say, it’s got mass m and a certain length,
then the average linear density is simply the mass divided by the length.
But of course what could happen is that the mass of the rod depends upon how far down
you are on it. Let’s say the mass might be the cube root of the length, and in that case,
you can talk about the linear density at a given length l. That is given by the derivative of the mass
with respect to l. In this case, it’s 1/(3³√(l^2)). Then of course you can work out the linear density
at any given length. In this case, if the length is 10, the answer is about 0.07.
Then you can plot both the mass and the linear density. You see that the mass sort of has
constant increase, but the linear density goes down as the length increases
because of this expression for the derivative.
Okay. Let’s go on now to current. If you have, let’s say, a wire
and some current flows through it, then the average current is the charge that flows
in a certain period of time. But of course the charge itself might depend upon the time t
like over here, and then the current at any given instant will be the derivative of that charge
with respect to t. At, let’s say, one second, the current is 4 amperes. Then what you can do is
to plot the charge and the current and get back a plot for both these quantities.
Let’s go on now to chemistry. Now in chemistry, one talks about reactions—chemical reactions.
What happens there is that one or more reactants would undergo some process
and give you some products.  For example, you might have two reactants A and B
that give you a product C. One talks about the concentration of any of these in moles per liter.
That concentration is of course a function of time as time goes by. For example, A and B might
decrease in quantity and C might go up. In that case, the rate of reaction at an instant is given by
the derivative of the concentration with respect to t. For example, suppose that
the concentration of C is given by 3t/(3t + 1). Then the rate of reaction at any given time
is a derivative, so it’s 3/(1 + 3t)^2. Then what you can do is to plot both these quantities,
and you see that as time goes by, the concentration will increase, but of course
the rate of reaction will go down as the system approaches a steady state.
Okay. Let’s go on now to biology. In biology, one talks about population models.
For example, the population at time t might be given by 2t^3 + t, and in that case,
the growth rate for that population is the derivative of that population with respect to t.
In this case, it’s just 6t^2 + 1. Then of course you can plot both the population and the growth rate
like we’ve done over here. In practice, one might have a slightly different model.
For example, if you talk about the growth of bacteria, then it might happen that
the population doubles every minute, for example, in which case
you might get a formula like the initial population times 2^t,
and that’s what is called an exponential function.
Okay. Finally, let’s go on to economics. In economics, one talks about the cost function.
Let’s say a company might talk about its cost function, which is a total cost of producing x units.
Here’s a cost function in a particular case. Now if you find the derivative of the cost function,
then that’s what is called the marginal cost. The marginal cost, roughly speaking,
is the amount of money it costs to produce an extra unit. For example, you might ask
what is the marginal cost and the actual cost of producing the 1,001st unit?
That’s going to be the derivative of the cost at that value, or you could actually find it
by subtracting off the cost in both the cases, so 1,001 – 1,000. You see that they are very close,
but not quite the same. The marginal cost gives you a very good estimate of
the cost to produce an extra unit. Once again, you can plot everything over here,
the cost and the marginal cost, to get those two plots.
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson. The main point is that derivatives are used
universally in the sciences. If you’re a physicist, you might use them to study motion.
If you’re a chemist, you might use them to study reaction rates, but if you’re a biologist,
you might use them to study growth rates. Finally, it’s not just the natural sciences,
but also the social sciences. In economics, you might use derivatives to find the marginal cost.
Of course, there are many more uses of derivatives that we haven’t spoken about in this lesson,
but you will learn them as time goes by. The key point is that wherever the quantity is changing,
derivatives will play a key role. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson.
The next lesson will talk about related rates, but before we do that, please review today’s lesson,
go over the exercises and make sure that you understand them really well
because derivatives are very import in sciences, and it’s important that you understand
how they can be used. I’ll stop over here. I hope you have enjoyed listening.
Thank you.