Hello, and welcome to Lesson 28 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is areas between curves.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the topic.
When you calculate an integral, you’re really finding the area
between the curve of a function and the x axis.
For example, here’s a function,
and when you compute the integral for that function,
then what you’re really doing is to find the area under the curve.
In this case, it’s the area between –1 and 1,
which are the limits for the integral over here.
The question is what would happen
if you want to find the area between two curves?
This lesson will go over
several examples of how we can do this using Integrate.
Okay. Let’s take an example.
Let’s say f[x] = 5 and g[x] = –x^2 + 1.
Now clearly in this case, the function f
is greater than the function g because that’s positive
and that’s going to be negative for most of the time,
but it won’t go over 1.
Now when you want to work out the area between them,
what you do is look at the Riemann sums.
Now in this case, the Riemann sums will have
a height equal to f minus g for each strip,
and the width will be (b – a)/n where b and a
are the limits of the integration interval.
Now the Riemann sum will be the sum of the heights times the widths,
which is the same as the integral of f minus g.
Basically, if you want to find the area between the preceding curves,
then all you go is you work out the integral of f minus g,
and you get back the answer—76/3 in this case.
Okay. Now two questions.
First question: what would happen if
you didn’t know the limits of integration?
Secondly, what would happen if you had to actually work out
which function, greater or less.
But before that, let’s take a simple example.
Here are two functions, and you want to work out
the area between them with x = 1 on the left and x = 5 on the right.
In this case, everything is given to you, so we can work out
the integral of f minus g and get the answer 88.
Here is a plot of the area which we just computed.
Now back to the question which I asked earlier on.
First question: what happens if you’re not given any endpoints?
Let’s say you’ve got two functions, f and g,
and you want to find the area enclosed between the curves
given by these functions.
What you do then is you work out
the points of intersection using Solve.
The curves intersect at –√3 and √3.
Here is a plot of the curves between those limits,
and you can see clearly that f is above g in all cases,
so we can work out the integral of f minus g,
and you get the answer with the area enclosed between these curves.
On the other hand, suppose you have the functions Sin[x] and Cos[x].
You can see that the functions f and g are either
above or below each other depending upon where you are.
Let’s say you want to find the area between –3π/4 and 5π/4.
That’s roughly starting over here and ending over there.
Initially, the cosine function is greater than the sine function,
and then the sine function is greater than the cosine
for the rest of the interval.
On the first interval, –3π/4 to 5π/4, you have g minus f
because g is greater than f, and then you do the opposite
for the rest of the interval.
Then you add the two answers, and you get back 4√2.
The point is you will now need to divide the integration
into two parts depending upon the behavior of f and g.
Instead of doing that, what we do is we just call Integrate
with the absolute value function,
which will take care of all the difficulties, and you get back
just the same answer from Integrate.
Given two functions f and g,
if you do not know which one is greater or less,
then you use the absolute value function to find the area.
Okay. Let’s now talk about cases where you’ve got a function of y.
So x is given as a function of y in these two functions, f and g.
To find the area in this case, you now need y limits.
Again, you work with Riemann sums, but now you have
Riemann sums with widths given by Δy.
Instead of talking about upper and below,
we talk about rightmost and leftmost functions.
In this case, if you plot the functions,
it is clear that the function g is to the right of the function f,
so the area will be given by
the integral of g minus f between –5 and 5.
Okay. Now an example where you might actually need this is
let’s say you’re given y = 3x + 1 and the parabola y^2 = x + 4.
In this case, y is not a function of x, so we try and write x
as a function of y by solving.
Set up two functions from the first solution over here
and the second solution over there.
Then you find out where they intersect.
Do a parametric plot, and it’s clear that
you actually have the function f to the right of g.
You do Integrate of f minus g between the limits (1 – √133)/6,
et cetera, and you get back the answer
for the area between those two curves.
You can either work with x limits or y limits.
They both work just fine.
It’s now time to summarize the lesson.
Basically, finding the area between curves
is really easy once you have integrals.
In case the function f is greater than the function g,
you simply do the integral of f minus g.
Now when you don’t have that information,
then what you do is you figure out
where the functions intersect using Solve,
figure out which function is above and which one is below,
and then you find the integral by doing
the integral of f minus g or g minus f,
or simply using the absolute value function.
Of course if you’re given functions of
y,
then you work with y integrals,
so let’s say you might do the integral of f minus g
in a case where you know that f is to the right of g.
That brings me to the end of this lesson.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about volume of solids.
But before that, do review this topic of area between curves.
It’s a very important and useful part of calculus.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.