Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 4 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is rates and approximations.
Let’s begin with problem 1, which talks about the approximate value of √24.9.
The problem is to find an approximate value using a linear approximation.
The relevant function over here is √x, and you want to work at x = 25
because that’s very close to 24.9. We first find the derivative of the square root function
at that value of x, and then we work out the actual approximation by doing the value at 25
plus the derivative times the difference between 24.9 and 25, and you get back the answer of 4.99.
If you check, the difference between the exact and approximate values is of the order of −5.
Here’s a graph of both the function and the approximation, and you can see
it’s quite a nice approximation close to 25.
Okay. Number 2 asks to approximate the value of −Cot[29º]. The first step is
we decide to work at 30º, which is π/6 radians. That’s close enough to 29.
Then we of course convert the 29º into radians. We work at the slope at 30 at π/6.
That turns out to be 4. Plug that 4 into the linear approximation formula. You have value at 30º
plus slope times the difference, and you get back the approximate value, and the approximation is
of the order of −3. It’s a good approximation. Here is a plot of the graph at the approximation.
Okay. Problem 3 asks you to find the approximate value of 1.001^50.
We think of this as being related to the function (1 + x)^50 around x = 0. First we find
the derivative at 0 for that function. Plug in the derivative into the approximation formula.
Get back the approximation value and check that the approximation is quite good.
Once again, here is a plot of both the function and the tangent line of the approximation at 0.
Okay. On to the next problem, number 4, which asks you to work with a spherical ball
whose radius is 5 cm. You know that the error in the radius is 0.01 cm, and you want to find
the error in the surface area. The surface area of a sphere is 4πr^2, so you want to find the error.
You work with differentials, and the differential in this case is 8πrdr—
that’s 8πr from the derivative, and dr is for the differential. You plug in the values—
r equal to 5, dr equal to 0.01—and you get back that the estimated error
is about 1.26 cm^2 for the surface area.
For number 5, we’re given a cone whose height is 5 cm and the radius is 9 cm.
Now it is known that the height has an error of plus or minus 0.02 cm, and the question is
to find the error in the volume. That’s the formula for the volume of a cone. It’s 1/3πr^2h.
Keep in mind that the radius is fixed, so to find the derivative with respect to h, I get πr^2dh/3.
Then you plug in the values given to you—r is 9, h is 0.02—and you get back that
the estimated error for the volume is around 1.70 cm^3.
On number 6, there is a 10-foot ladder, and it is falling down a wall at a rate of 0.5 ft/sec.
The question is what is the rate at which the bottom of that ladder is sliding out at the point
when it is 6 feet from the wall? That’s the picture you have over here.
That’s the bottom, and that’s the ladder falling down the wall. The length of the ladder is 10 feet.
The first point to note is that you have the Pythagorean relation—x[t]^2 + y[t]^2 = 100, in this case.
You take the derivative of that equation with respect to t. Keep in mind that you already know
that the value of x is 6 ft. The value of y is 8 ft by Pythagoras. y'[t] is given to you,
so you can plug in the values over here and work out x'[t] as 0.667, or roughly 2/3 ft/sec.
Okay. On to number 7, which talks about a melting ice cube. This ice cube has the volume decreasing
at 1 cm^3/sec. The question is to find the rate at which the sides of the cube
are decreasing at the point where the volume is 512 cm^3. Now of course, the volume of a cube
is the side cubed, so when the volume is 512, the side is 8 cm. You take a derivative of that formula
with respect to t, and then you know that V'[t] is −1 because volume is decreasing. s is 8.
You plug in the values, and you find that the sides are decreasing at the rate of −1/192 cm/sec.
Number 8 talks about a car that’s going north from an intersection at a certain speed, 50 mph,
and a truck is going west from the same intersection at 40 mph. The question is to find out
the rate at which the distance between these two is increasing after an hour.
That’s the picture you have. That’s the car going north, the truck going west
and that’s the distance between them. Of course, the Pythagorean theorem says that
the car squared plus truck squared is equal to distance squared. That’s the equation.
If we plug in the values, you’ll find that after an hour, the distance is √4100. Take the derivative,
and keep in mind that after one hour, the car has a derivative of about 50 distance and rate
With the truck, you have 40 for the same quantities, and the distance is 10√41.
If you plug in values, you get that the actual distance between them is increasing at 10√41.
Number 9 talks about a spherical balloon that’s being inflated at 30π cm^3/sec.
The question is to find the rate at which the surface area is increasing when the balloon has
a radius of 8 cm. Now the surface area is given by S = 4πr^2, so if you take the derivative,
you get S'[t] = 8πr[t]r'[t]. The problem is you need to find r', the derivative of r with respect to t,
and to do that, you use a volume formula, you find the derivative and you plug in
the given information for the rate of inflation of the balloon and the radius.
You find that the derivative for r is 15/128. You plug in that into the formula for
the derivative of the surface area, and you get back 15π/2 as the required rate.
Okay. Number 10 talks about an inverted conical tank that’s being filled with water
at a rate of 40π m^3/sec. The base of this tank has a radius of 100 m, and the height is 250 m.
The question is to find the rate at which the water level is increasing when the water is 70 m deep.
Now keep in mind that you can talk about similar triangles over here and get that the ratio
between radius and height is always constant. In fact, that ratio is 2/5. You can plug in
that ratio into the volume formula for the cone and get the volume in terms of the height and the width.
Then if you differentiate the equation, that tells you the relationship between the derivative
for the volume and the derivative for the water level. Given that V'[t] is 40 and h is 70,
what you can do is you can plug back those values and find the rate at which
the water level is increasing when the water is 70 m deep.
Okay. The remaining questions for this session are all simple, and I hope you will find that too.
I certainly think that they are much simpler than the earlier ones, and in each case,
you simply need to do a simple derivative calculation and get the answer.
A car’s position on a highway is given by the function over here for number 11, and the question is
to find the velocity function and the velocity after three hours. The velocity function is simply
the derivative of the position function. That’s the answer, and if you plug in the value of t = 3,
then you get back the velocity after 3 hours. Here is a plot of the position and velocity.
Let’s go on now to number 12, where you’re given the cost function for a company when it produces x units,
and you want the cost of making the 51st unit. That should remind you of the marginal cost,
which is the derivative of the cost function. Let’s work that out. Plug in 50
because the marginal cost when x is 50 is the cost of making the 51st unit. The answer is 0.28.
That’s approximately the cost of making the 51st unit.
Here are plots of the cost and the marginal cost for this company.
Okay. Number 13 says that the amount of charge going through a particular wire is given by
the equation over here. The question is to find the current going through it when the time is π/6.
Keep in mind that the current is simply the derivative of the charge. When t is π/6,
that’s the answer, and here are plots of the charge and the current.
On to problem number 14 where it says you have got a cannonball,
and that cannonball has got its height function given by this formula over here.
The question is to find the velocity at 1 second and when it hits the ground again.
After 1 second, the velocity is given by the derivative at that time. Now we want to find
when the cannonball hits the ground again. Well, that’s a question of solving the equation over here.
Simply put the height equal to 0. If you work it out, we get back that t is 3.06, roughly.
Then you work out the velocity at that point. That’s −30. Here’s a plot of the cannonball
and the velocity at any time t, and you can see that when t is given as time over here
when it hits the ground, then the velocity is around −30.
That brings me to the end of this problem session, and we’ll next talk about maxima and minima.
Before that, do try Quiz 4 and be ready for the next lesson. Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.