Hello, and welcome to Lesson 27 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic of this lesson is the substitution rule.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In the last lesson, we talked about
some rules for calculating integrals,
and we learned a few simple rules.
For example, we can now do the integral of x^2 and get back x^3/3,
so that’s x^a giving you x^(a + 1)/(a + 1), the power rule.
The rules we learned cannot help us in more difficult cases.
For example, if I gave you the function 10Sin[3x],
then those rules would not work, and they will not work
for this harder problem involving a square root radical.
Here are the functions and their plots.
What you notice is that these are quite interesting functions,
so surely you would like to integrate them.
The question is how do we do that,
and that is the goal of this lesson.
The goal of this lesson is to try and calculate such integrals
using what is called the substitution rule.
But to do that, I must recall the chain rule for you.
The chain rule says that if you have two functions, f and g—
so you have f[x] and g[x]—then the derivative of the composition
f[g[x]] is f'[g[x]] * g'[x].
Here’s the rule a little more formally using D,
and you get back the answer that you expected.
Now of course, every time you have
a rule for derivatives like this one,
then you have a rule for integration, so now that says that
the integral of f'[g[x]] * g'[x] is f[g[x]],
and that is the basis for the substitution rule.
Let’s go a little deeper and talk about the substitution rule.
Let’s say you want to evaluate this integral over here.
What we’ll do is to simplify things, we’ll set u to be g[x].
Now you get f'[u], and you’ll get this g'[x]dx.
But then if you think about it, the derivative of u is g'[x],
so that says that roughly speaking, du = g'[x]dx.
That’s a differential statement, but it’s correct.
Basically what we’ve done is
to reduce this rather difficult-looking integral on the left
to a rather simple-looking integral on the right,
and that is the substitution rule for integrals.
For example, if I said find the integral of 3Sin[3x]dx,
then you set u to be 3x.
So du is 3dx because that’s the derivative of 3x.
That 3 over here and the dx over there combine, and you get Sin[u]du.
Then we can’t stop over here because u is 3x,
so the answer is –Cos[3x].
You can check that directly with Integrate,
and you do get back the right answer.
That’s the rule for substitution,
namely, you set u to be g[x] and then proceed from there.
As an example, let’s take another trig function, 10Sin[3x].
Again, you set u to be 3x, so du is 3dx.
But then you have a 10 over here, so you make a small adjustment
and write it as (10/3) * 3, and so you get back that
the integral really is (10/3)Sin[u].
You integrate that, but then recall that u is 3x,
so you plug that back in and you get back the exact answer,
which is what Integrate would give you if you tried it directly.
Okay. Let’s go a step further now
and talk about an algebraic function.
That’s the second function from the introduction.
Here you think of this inside the square root sign as being u,
so u is x^3 + 3.
So du = 3x^2dx because that’s the derivative of 3x^3 + 3,
but then you think to yourself you’ve got a 2 over here,
so we need a small adjustment.
We’ll add to this 2/3 * 3, so you have that
the integral is 2/3√u with respect to u.
You plug in the expression for u
and you get back the answer in terms of x,
and of course Integrate gives just the same answer in this case.
Let’s now go on to a slightly harder example
where you have a kind of rational algebraic function.
Here you set u to be 5 – 5x^2,
so du is –10xdx because that’s the derivative of u.
Then you tell yourself that you have a 2x over here,
so we need a small adjustment, so that is (–2/10) *  –10,
and you get back the integral of u over here.
You plug in the expression for u as 5 – 5x^2,
and of course integrate will give you back
just the same answer in this case.
Okay. Slightly harder example: you have f[x] = x^3√(3 – x^2).
You set u to be 3 – x^2.
That’s what’s inside the square root sign.
So du is –2xdx.
Now another problem: you need to integrate the x^3 carefully
as the –2x bit from here and the part that’s left over,
which is x^2, but x^2 is just 3 – u,
and that’s how I get the part over here.
The integral becomes (–1/2)(3 – u)√u.
You integrate that.
You plug in the expression, and of course Integrate will give you
just the same answer in this case as well.
Well, there’s a slight difference because you have
a negative sign inside over here and outside,
but essentially they are the same answer.
Now the point is that you have two answers,
one in terms of u and the other in terms of x.
As far as this example goes, it’s the x answer that matters,
but when you go on to definite integrals,
then you want to actually plug in limits, and at that point,
we have two ways of going about it.
First of all, what you could do is
you could work with the expression involving x, the x answer,
and plug in the upper and lower limits.
Let’s say you want to go from 0 to 1.
You plug in the value of the x answer at 1 and then at 0,
and you get back the answer over here.
But you could also keep the u form, and if you do that,
you’ve got to be careful because when x goes from 0 to 1,
then u goes from 3 to 2.
That’s because u is defined in terms of x.
Here’s the answer again from the u method,
and you get back just the same result.
You can check it all with Integrate, and you have
the first answer is the u answer going from 3 to 2.
The other one is from 0 to 1 for x,
and you get back the same result in both the cases.
The point is that when you have a definite integral,
then you could either work in the u picture or the x picture,
and they are both convenient in some ways.
The u answer tends to be simpler,
but you need to change the limits.
The x answer tends to be more complicated,
but then you have the limits given to you.
You should decide which one is better in each case.
That brings me to the end of this lesson.
The main point is the substitution rule lets you
calculate integrals using the chain rule in reverse.
This rule is essentially a reverse chain rule.
What you do is you always begin by making a substitution u,
a suitable one.
Then you find du and modify the integral as required.
Then you plug back the expression for u after integrating
and you get back the result.
But of course when working with definite integrals,
you could either work with the original endpoints and x,
or change the endpoints and work with u.
That’s the essence of this rule.
In the next lesson, we’ll apply these ideas
to compute the area between two curves.
But before doing that, do review the lesson.
It’s quite a difficult lesson because you’ll need this rule
again and again, and you must have some practice with applying it.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.