Hello, and welcome to Lesson 4 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for today’s lesson is the limit of a function, and it is today that we begin formally
the study of calculus in this course. The limits are an essential topic in any calculus course.
Let’s begin with an overview of the topic.
Here are two simple plots. I’m going to plot x from −1 to 1. That is of course just a straight line,
and then I’m going to plot x^2/x in the same limits, and I again get back what looks like
essentially the same straight line. On the other hand, if we look at the function x^2/x,
then strictly speaking it’s not defined when x is 0 because you’re doing 0/0,
and that becomes clearer if we define a function g with that expression. g over here
is defined to be x^2/x, and if you try to find the value of g at 0, then you get back
the value indeterminate. The Quiet over only says that I would not like to see
any warnings that Wolfram Language would give us in this case.
Okay. The point is you have two very similar functions, but the second one has a slight issue at 0.
Now even though it is not defined at 0, you still would like to know what the behavior
of the function is near this point, and that’s what limits are all about. They are about tracking
the behavior of a function near a point. The mathematical way of doing this is called a limit.
Here’s an example to show the notion of a limit. Let’s take f[x] = x^2 − x + 2.
Again, you want to find the behavior of this function as x approaches a certain value.
Let’s say you want to focus on the value x = 1 and you make a table over here.
Don’t worry too much about how to make the table; that’s not too important for us.
As you take values close to 1, you begin from 0 and go up to 1—very close to 1, but not 1 itself—
you see the values get close to 2. Just same thing happens from the right, that the value is
very close to 2 when you are close to 1. It appears that this function gets closer and closer to 2
as the values of x grow closer and closer to 1 from both the sides. One would then say that
the limit of this function when x approaches 1 is 2. Limits are just
a way of showing the behavior of a function near a point, but not necessarily at that point.
Okay. Some examples. Let’s begin with a function which is a trigonometric function divided by
a simple polynomial. It’s a trigonometric rational function, and you want to find
the limit of this function as x approaches 0. If you look over here at the table, it’s clear that
as you approach 0 from either side, the values approach 1. In fact if you plot the function,
you get the same kind of guess that the value of the limit seems to be 1. The table says 1,
the plot says 1, but in practice it’s best to use the Limit function in Wolfram Language,
which tells you the limit is actually 1. Tables are good, plots are better, but Limit is the best.
Limit will always tell you exactly what the limit of a function is at a point.
The whole theme of our discussion will be try to move towards using Limit whenever you can.
As my second example, let’s take a rational function. That’s a rational function.
It’s a polynomial divided by a polynomial. Now notice that when x is plus or minus 1,
there’s a problem with the denominator becoming 0. Let’s say you want to talk about
the behavior near −1. Near −1, it looks like the values are very close to −0.5.
Now let’s plot the function, and it does look like when you are close to −1,
the values are close to −0.5. It looks like the function approaches −1/2 as an exact number
as x approaches −1. You can confirm that with Limit and get back that value as the actual limit.
Okay. As my next example, let’s consider this piecewise function g[x].
Now the piecewise part over here is all simple. It’s just −0.75 at x = −1,
and it’s the same rational function as before everywhere else. Now if you make a table of values,
it’s clear that as long as you stay away from −1, then there’s no problem at all
and the values approach −0.5 as before. Here’s a plot which shows that there’s a problem
at just a single point, −1, but everywhere else, things are just the same as before.
In fact, the limit does seem to be −0.5. Let’s confirm that over here, and you do get back −0.5
for this piecewise function limit.
Now, let’s go on to a slightly more complicated example; namely, an algebraic function.
Here’s an algebraic function. It’s got a square root in it and the denominator x^2, so when x is 0,
that’s a problem. But fortunately everything is removable in the sense that
there really is no problem at 0. In fact, if we make a table of values, you see that
when you are very close to 0, the value is very close to 0.25. You plot the function,
and you see that the value at 0 does seem to approach 0.25. You can confirm the answer with Limit,
and you get back the value 0.25 as an exact number, 1/4.
Okay. Let’s go on now to a slightly more tricky function. Here is a trigonometric function.
Now if we make a table of values over here, what you see is that the values all seem to be 1 mostly.
It looks like there is a problem because the limit seems to be 1. Intuition tells you that
this might be more complicated, so let’s plot. Then you do that. You see it is much more wiggly.
It’s much more complicated. What you need to take away from this is that
tables are useful, but they are not terribly reliable. The plot says that this limit
probably does not exist, but in fact you can confirm the answer with Limit, and check that
the answer is actually indeterminate. Indeterminate says that this limit does not exist.
Okay. Let’s move on now to a slightly more complicated function, and hopefully you realize by now
that we do need some different ways of finding limits. But just for now,
let’s take the same approach and make a table of values over here.
When you make a table of values and you are close to 0, you see the values
seem to approach 0.015 on either side. As an exact number, you would expect
the limit to be around 3/200. You plot the function. The limit does look like 0.015 at 0.
You can confirm the answer with Limit and get back the correct result, which is 3/200.
That’s the value of the limit function. It will tell you exactly what the limit is at a point.
Okay. Having talked about limits, it’s convenient sometimes to talk about one-sided limits.
Here’s an example where you have a piecewise function, and if you plot it, you see that
when you approach the point 0 from the left, the answer is −1. When you approach it from the right,
the limit seems to be 1. The question is how do you check that with the Limit function?
Well, we have an option called Direction, so when you say Direction→“FromBelow”,
you’re going from the left; when it’s Direction→“FromAbove”, you’re going from the right.
When you do that, you see that you get back the values −1 and 1 respectively. Of course because
you don’t have the same behavior on the left and right, you get back indeterminate
as the answer for the limit. One-sided limits are really quite useful because they let you
analyze more and more complicated functions.
Here is a piecewise function. It’s got several pieces. Notice that when you plot the function,
then there are three values of interest to us: there’s 1, there’s 4 and there’s 6.
Now 4 is not a problem at all; it’s nice over there. At 1, it’s almost okay, except that
you have a slight piece outside of the point over here given by this piecewise component.
At 6, you have a slightly more difficult problem because you actually have a jump.
It would look like when you approach 1, the value must be 3 for the limit. That’s 3 over here.
When you approach 4, the answer must be 6. That looks clear as well. Now when you approach 6 itself,
the limit does not seem to exist, and you can confirm this by using the Limit function.
Now this strange thing over here is what we call a Map function, which actually lets you find
the values of the limits at different points in one stroke. You can confirm that at 6 you actually have
separate limits on the right and left by doing the direction computation,
and you get back different answers, so surely the limit does not exist at x = 6.
Okay. Now we need to turn in a slightly different direction and talk about infinite limits.
Here’s an example where you have a rational function, and what you want to do is to use
a table of values that’s given to you to try and guess what the limit might be at the point x = −1.
Here’s the table, and what you see is that when they approach −1 on the left or right,
the values seem to blow up—they become infinite—but they become negatively infinite
on one side and positively infinite on this side. You can confirm that with the Limit function.
You see that the values become −∞ on one side and ∞ on the other,
and you can check that the limit does not exist, finally. Now we are talking about infinite limits,
and that leads us to the concept of an asymptote. What’s an asymptote? It’s a point in the graph
where things become infinite. Here’s an example. You’ve got 1/(x − 1)^2 as a function,
and whether you approach it at 1 from the left or right, the value becomes infinitely large
in a positive sense, and you can confirm that with a plot to check
the limit is actually going to be ∞ on either side. Well, if it’s infinite on either side, it is ∞,
so Limit says yes, the limit is ∞ at 1. That’s what we call a vertical asymptote.
It’s a kind of vertical line that shows you that the function will become infinite
on both sides, in this case.
But it can also have slightly different behavior. Here’s f[x] = 1/x, and if you plot it between −1 and 1,
then at 0 you have a different behavior on the left and the right—so on the right, it approaches ∞;
on the left, it approaches −∞, and you can confirm that with Limit. You see the limit does not exist,
and what you have is a vertical asymptote of a slightly different kind.
Okay. The question is how do you find asymptotes in general? Well, that’s really a hard problem,
but let’s say if I give you a cotangent function and I said find the asymptotes between −2π and 2π,
what you could do is make a plot of the function. The plot seems to say that there are
problems at 0—you can see over here—and then at π and then at 2π, et cetera. Let’s look at 0.
You see that the function values are −∞ and ∞ from the two sides, so you certainly have
a vertical asymptote at 0, and just the same thing happens at all the other multiples of π.
You can see that the limit does not exist at any of those points. Given a function,
you could try to plot it and then use Limit to figure out where the asymptotes might be.
Okay. Finally I have an example in which you actually do need to use tables.
Here is an example in which you have two variables. You have got an h and an x.
Now the problem is that because x is not known to you, you cannot graph the function,
so graphing will get you nowhere in this case. But what you could do is make a table of values,
and then what you see is—well, roughly speaking—if you expand it out, you get x^2 + 2xh + h^2 − x^2.
If you do a bit of algebra, it will be clear to you that what is going to get left over is just 2x.
Right. The point over here is the limit over here is just going to be 2x.
Okay. We’ve seen now that tables are quite useful in some cases,
but in general, you should try and avoid them.
That brings me to the end of today’s lesson. What you’ve learned is that the limits are a good way of
figuring out what happens as a function approaches a certain value of x.
Now the function doesn’t even need to be defined at the point at which you want to find the limit,
but as long as the right-hand limit and the left-hand limit both exist, you are fine.
For a limit to exist, you must have the right-hand limit and the left-hand limit to be equal.
They could both be infinite, but they must both be equal. As you saw in the last example,
tables are really useful in some cases, but in general, you want to avoid using them,
and you really want to use the Limit function. In the next lesson, we’ll talk the laws of limits,
which actually let you do limit computations very efficiently without using tables.
But before we do that, I recommend that you go over today’s lesson and carefully master all the details
from the notebook, look at the exercises and make sure you understand
the notion of a limit really well before we actually start computing them at a really fast pace.
That’s all I have to say for today’s lesson on the limit of a function. I hope you enjoyed it.
I hope you really benefit from this first introduction to calculus with limits,
and I’ll see you next time. Thank you.