Hello, and welcome to Lesson 21 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is optimization.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
We’ve learned how to find extreme values—maxima and minima—earlier on,
and those have been very useful in applications.
Now we’ve also learned that those derivatives in maxima and minima
can be used to do things like maximize profits or minimize costs,
so they have quite a few very practical uses.
This lesson will continue the approach learned earlier on
to solve some more optimization problems.
So it’s just a continuation of all the earlier work,
but this time around, we’ll develop a way for solving optimization problems.
We’ll set up a set of guidelines that should help us solve these problems in a systematic way.
Okay. Here are those guidelines.
Number one: make sure you understand the problem, perhaps by reading it more than once.
Next make a picture to get an idea of what you need to do in the problem.
Next assign a symbol like M to the quantity that is being maximized or minimized,
and of course do the same thing for all the other unknown quantities.
Now use all the information to set up an expression for M in terms of all the other variables.
Another difficulty is that if you have multiple symbols,
then you will need to find relationships so that M is a function of just one variable x.
After all, we’re doing single-variable calculus,
so you must have just one variable x on which M depends.
One last thing is find the domain of f.
Find out where f is defined because that will tell you the interval
on which you must find the maxima and minima.
For the final step, you find the absolute maximum and minimum of f
using all that you’ve learned in earlier lessons.
Let’s begin with an example.
A farmer has 3,600 feet of fencing,
and this farmer wants to build a rectangular field that borders a river,
but he doesn’t want to put any fencing on the side touching the river.
The question is find the dimensions of the field that maximize the area.
Now for the first step, let’s do an animation.
Here’s the area for particular values of x and y.
Let’s begin by starting all the way to the left over here, and let’s play the animation.
You see over here that initially the area increases, and then it starts to drop.
In other words, your configuration can neither be too thin, nor can it be too tall.
In fact, here’s a picture you have of the problem.
You have the area over here depending upon x and y, the length and the width of the field.
Okay. Let’s now start solving the problem.
The area is going to be x times y, which is the length times the width.
The problem is you have two variables, so you must eliminate one of them,
but then you know 2x + y must be the length of the fencing available—after all, y occurs only once.
Replace y by an expression involving x, and then the area depends only on one variable, x.
Now the point is that you cannot have the value of x exceeding 1,800
because otherwise the area would be less than 0 because that factor becomes negative.
So the domain of the function is from 0 to 1,800.
Then finally, let’s use the closed interval method like I’m doing over here
to find the critical points, and then here is the area at that value of x.
Another point is that you only have a single critical point,
and at the end points you have either a 0 area, which makes no sense,
or you have this maximum area over here, so you have a maximum at this value of x over here.
So the rectangle should be 900 feet long and 1,800 feet wide.
Okay. Before going on, we need to talk a little bit about absolute extreme values.
Earlier on, we mostly talked about local extreme values.
The point is that if you have a critical number c for a function and you find that the derivative is,
let’s say, positive to the left of it for all values and negative to the right of it for all values,
then that value is actually an absolute maximum for the function.
In just the same way, if you have a value c for which the derivative is
negative for all values to the left and positive for all values to the right,
then you have an absolute minimum.
That’s just a slightly more general result than the first derivative test.
We have tweaked that test slightly to find aboslute maxima and minima
instead of local maxima and minima.
As a very simple example, here’s x^2 with its derivative 2x.
You see over here that that’s the minimum, and to the left the derivative is negative,
and to the right it’s positive for all values, so you actually have an absolute minimum over here.
As an application, now let’s take up the problem of making a cylindrical can
that holds 1 liter of water, and you want to find the dimensions
that will minimize the total cost of plastic that’s used to make the can.
Now if you want to minimize the cost of plastic,
then the best way to do that is to minimize the surface area of the can.
Here is the can itself.
That’s the surface area S, the radius and the height.
The formula for the area is just the area of the two sides and the two bases,
so that’s the total area. Now you want to eliminate h, let’s say,
so remember that the volume πr^2h is 1,000.
After all, you have 1 liter of water, so h is 1,000/(πr^2).
Having done that, we can now write the surface area in terms of just one variable r,
and the domain is just from 0 all the way to ∞.
In principle, you could have any value for r.
Now the point is you cannot apply the closed interval method because the interval is infinite,
so what we do is we first of all work out the critical numbers.
There’s just one critical number, but then you note that
to the left of that value you have the derivative being negative,
and to the right you have it being positive, so actually you have an absolute minimum.
Okay. Now with that radius, you can work out the height using the solution above,
this 5.41926, and that says that the radius should be approximately 5.42
and the height should be approximately 10.84.
Okay. Now a problem about distances.
You want to find the point on the parabola y^2 = 2x which is closest to the point (1, 32).
That’s the distance formula.
You have √(x – 1)^2 + (y – 32)^2 for that point.
Because the point lies on the parabola, you have x = y^2/2 from here,
so you plug it back and you get a distance function.
Now I won’t worry about the square root sign. That doesn’t matter.
You work out the critical numbers, and you find that it’s just one critical number.
If you look at the derivative, you actually see that
the derivative is going to be negative to the left of 4 and positive to the right of 4,
so you actually have an absolute minimum.
The minimum value will occur when you are at (8, 4), and that’s the answer to the problem.
Okay. Now on to a business example.
Let’s say you have a store that sells 300 monitors a week at $200 each.
Now the store finds that for each $10 rebate, of course the sales go up,
so the number of monitors increases by the number 30 in a week.
Okay. The question is what are the demand function and the revenue function?
You also want to find the rebate that the store should offer to maximize its revenue.
The demand function is just the price per unit, so that’s given over here.
You have the base price 200 minus the discount that customers will get
depending upon how many monitors are sold.
The revenue function is just the total revenue.
That’s the number of items times the price per item.
To maximize revenue, you simply find its critical value, which is 450,
and then you can actually check quite easily that you actually have
an absolute maximum at this value.
The price at this value of x is 150.
Now the rebate should be $200, the base price, minus $150. That’s $50.
Okay. Now that’s all done manually, but in the Wolfram Language,
we have two functions, Maximize and Minimize, which can actually find
these absolute maxima and minima for a given range without any effort on our part.
For example, in the earlier case, I could use Maximize to get back
just the same answer for the revenue.
You could also specify range, and we get back the answer for that range.
That’s Maximize, and similarly, you could find an absolute minimum
by using the Minimize function.
Here is a function and you want to minimize it between 0 and 2π,
so you use Minimize and you get back an answer,
and here is a plot showing that that answer is actually correct.
That dot over here is the point at which you have a minimum.
Okay. That’s the end of this lesson.
The main point is that optimization is a very important area of applied mathematics.
A lot of people spend time just solving optimization problems.
Now to solve such problems, the first point is you must try and understand what the problem is.
To understand the problem, you draw a picture, et cetera,
and make you’ve got all of it set up right before you try and solve it.
Of course, if you are in business, then optimization is particularly important
because you want maximize the profits,
so you need some kind of quantitative way of maximizing profits.
There are two built-in functions, Maximize and Minimize,
which are really useful for solving such problems.
The next lesson will talk about antiderivatives,
but before you do that, do review today’s lesson.
It was quite a difficult lesson.
Make sure you understand all the steps, and then we’ll go on to antiderivatives next time.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.