Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 2 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is derivatives and continuity. Now being a problem session,
we’ll discuss a few problems, but the point will be to try to show you how to solve
real problems in calculus, and also how to review the concepts that you’ve learned earlier
by looking at real examples. Let’s begin with the first problem for today, and that says
find the limit of x * Sin[x] + Cos[x] as x goes to π. Now keep in mind that x is continuous
and so is Sin[x] and so is Cos[x], so the entire expression over here is continuous,
and hence what you can do is you can simply plug in the value π into it. If you do that,
then the answer is −1. You expect that the limit is going to be −1, and you can compute the limit
with the Limit function and get just the same answer. Here’s a plot of the function around π,
and you see that the value is actually −1 around there.
Okay. Let’s go onto problem 2, which asks you to compute the limit of Sin[x^2 – 3x] as x approaches 3.
Now the point is that sine is a continuous function, so you can basically take the limit
inside the bracket over here and work out that simple limit, which is just 9 – 9, so that’s 0.
You expect the limit is going to be 0 for the entire expression, and you can confirm that with Limit
and get back the same answer, 0. Here is a plot, and the plot shows you
that indeed the limit is 0 at x = 3.
Okay. Problem 3 asks you to find the limit as x approaches 9 of this function over here.
Now the point is that when x is 9, we have an issue because the denominator becomes 0 at x = 9
because that’s 81 − 81. That’s 0, so you can not evaluate the limit that the quotient law as given to you.
But what you can do is to try and cancel a common factor by first multiplying the top and the bottom
by 3 + √x, and if we do that, you see that we now have the required factor 9 – x,
which cancels with the denominator, and if you do that, you can simplify. Then you get back
an expression which no longer has any problem with computing limits. If you now plug in x = 9,
you would expect to get 54 over here, so the answer is 1/54 for this limit.
That’s a bit difficult because you had to do some work to get to the answer,
but typically limits of rational functions or rational expressions are a bit more complicated.
Problem 4 asks you to show that there is a root of this expression over here between 2 and 3.
Now that should remind you of the intermediate value theorem, which says that
the if sign of the expression is different at the two ends, then you actually have a root in the middle.
If you compute the expression at 2 you get −5 point something, and at 3 you get a positive number.
You have a negative value at one end, a positive value at the other end, so there must be
a root in the interval 2 to 3. You can confirm that with Solve, and actually you compute the value,
which is about 2.39. Here’s the plot, and you can see the function does becomes 0 around 2.4,
so that agrees with the value given by Solve. Like we said earlier on, the intermediate value theorem
is a very powerful tool for identifying roots of functions.
Okay. Problem 5 says find the value of a which will make this piecewise expression continuous,
and clearly the only problem is at 1. Now what you need to do is to fit the value of a
so the function becomes continuous at 1. Now at 1, if you work out the function value it’s 3,
and the limit from the right-hand side is also 3 because if you plug in 1 over here,
you get back 3, so you need to fit the value of a so that the left-hand limit is 3 as well.
You can do that with the Solve function, and get a to be 6. Now once you do that,
then the function becomes 6x − 3 instead of 8x − 3 for x less than 1, and if you plot it now,
it looks nice and continuous—although it does have a corner over here—but there is
no problem with the continuity. a = 6 is required for making this expression continuous at 1.
Problem 6 says find the limit of (1/x – 1/3)/(x – 3). Now that’s just a derivative
because that’s like a difference quotient. You can work out the answer using D,
or you could work out the limit directly and get back the same answer.
Here is a plot which shows that in fact you do have a tangent line at this point over here.
Working the limit in this case could be done either by using D or by doing a limit calculation.
Okay. Problem number 7 says compute the left-hand derivative of this expression at 1.
First we set up the function f[x] with the given expression. You want to find the left-hand derivative,
so you can use DifferenceQuotient with the Direction option. You say FromBelow.
You want to go from the left at x = 1, and you get back the answer. Then what you can do is
you can use that answer, which is just like the slope, to work out the tangent line,
and you see that indeed you have a tangent line at the required point.
But notice that you have a problem at 1. This is just going to be the left-hand derivative.
Okay. Let’s go on now to find the derivative of this expression at 2. Now because you have
an absolute value, what you could do is analyze the expression a bit more
and say that because 2 is less than 3, so the expression becomes 4 * (−x + 3),
and then work out the derivative of that, which is just −4. Or you can simply use D itself
on the original function and get back just the same answer. What you can do finally is
to plot the derivative and original expression, the tangent line, and what you see over here is that
in fact you have a coincidence of tangent line with the function on the left, and that’s very typical of
of the absolute value function—namely, the tangent line will overlap the graph at some stage.
Okay. Problem number 9 says compute the values of a and b for which this function
becomes differentiable. Now that’s a much a harder problem because you need to check that
that you actually have the same left-hand and right-hand derivatives, and you also need to
some kind of continuity. Okay. We’re talking about derivatives. If you work out
the derivative on the left. That’s 3x^2 + a, so at 2, the answer is going to be 12 + a.
That must be equal to the derivative that’s over here, which is 2bx – 3, so that must be 4b.
If you work out the left-hand limits, then you see over here when you plug in 2, you get 8 + 2a,
and over there you get 4b – 3. Now both those must be satisfied for getting the values of a and b,
so you solve the system and you get back a  as 1 and b as 13/4. Once you’ve got those values,
you can then plot everything and check that in fact you have a nice smooth expression over here.
Okay. Let’s go on now to number 10, which says compute the tangent line of this function at 1.
Now to compute the tangent line, you first of all need to find a value of the function at 1.
You need to compute the slope at x = 1. You’ve got both those now. Then the tangent line
is y – y1 equal to slope times (x – x1). That’s the equation of the tangent line,
and then you can do that over here to get a plot. You’ve got a plot now which shows clearly
that we’ve got the right tangent line in this case.
Okay. Problem 11 says compute the normal line to a function at 4. Now the normal line,
keep in mind, is perpendicular to the tangent line. Of course you first find the value at 4.
Then you compute the derivative at 4. The answer is −10. Now −10 is the slope of the tangent line,
so the slope of the normal must be 1/10. Use that information to work out
the equation of the normal over here, and then finally we plot the original function
along with the normal line at 4. You do see that the normal line is perpendicular to
the curve at that point, and of course it’s perpendicular to the tangent line at that point.
Problem number 12 says that you’re given the position vector of a particle s[t]
and you want to find the acceleration of that particle at a certain time, namely, t = 3π/2.
Now the acceleration is the second derivative of the position, so you compute the second derivative.
That’s the shorthand for the second derivative of the position. Then you plug in the t as 3π/2,
and you get back the value. Then you can use that to actually plot both
the position and the acceleration, and that’s the plot of both those functions.
The accretion is the second time derivative of the position.
Problem number 13 says that you’re given a table of values, and from a table of values
for a function f[x], you want to compute the average rate of change of that function
over the range 6 to 12. Now the average rate simply means the slope of the secant line
between those two points, so you work it out. The values are 14 and 10 at those two points.
We will divide (14 – 10) by (12 – 6), and you get back the average rate of change.
Here’s a plot of the points in secant line. Of course secant line is not a very good approximation,
but often all that you have is a table of values.
And finally, problem 14, which says compute the instantaneous rate of change of z
with respect to y for this function over here when y is π. Now when we say
instantaneous rate of change, what we mean is the derivative. You simply work out D at that point.
That’s the instantaneous rate of change, and then using that, you can work out the tangent line.
When you do that, you actually see that you have the tangent line over here given by
the instantaneous rate of change as its slope.
To summarize, the key concept for this problem was that the instantaneous rate of change
is the slope of the tangent line at that point. This brings me to the end of today’s problem session.
I hope that you have benefited from the discussion. Do review the problems, and then in Lesson 9,
we’ll go on to talking about differentiation rules. But before doing that,
there is a small quiz for you to take. Do take Quiz 2, and then you’ll be ready for Lesson 9.
Thank you very much. I hope that you’ve enjoyed today’s lesson. I’ll stop over here.