Hello, and welcome to Lesson 31 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is average value of a function.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
Let’s say you have a list of numbers like over here,
and you want to work out their average value.
Of course what you do is just add the numbers
and then divide by the number of numbers,
which is 10 in this case, and you get back the answer.
You also have a function called Mean in the Wolfram Language
which does just the same thing for you,
and you get back the same answer.
Now let’s say instead of a list of values,
you had a function like the one shown over here.
Here’s a plot of the function.
The question is can we work out
the average value of such a function?
The answer is yes.
Here’s some intuition.
Let’s say your function runs from a to b.
You break the interval into n subintervals,
take a sample point for each subinterval
and then work out the average value like over here.
Now we want to rewrite it as a Riemann sum,
so the n over here can be thought of as being related to Δx,
the length of each subinterval.
So  Δx is (b – a)/n, and hence n is (b – a)/Δx.
You can rewrite the average in a slightly different form
in which it’s clear that if you now let n go to ∞
so you’ve got very small subintervals,
then what you get back is the integral
divided by the length of the interval.
That’s the average value of a function.
It’s the integral of the function over an interval
divided by the length of the interval.
Let’s say in our example, if you want to work out the average value,
you simply find the integral from 0 to 5 and then divide by 5,
and you get back the answer.
Okay. Now a much deeper fact is
something called the mean value theorem, which says that
if you have a continuous function on an interval,
then there is at least one number c in that interval
such that the value of the function is equal to the average value.
That should remind you of the mean value theorem for derivatives,
which was the same thing,
but now for integrals over intervals and areas rather than slopes.
If you multiply both sides by b – a,
what you get on the left-hand side is just the area of a rectangle
with height f(c) and length b – a,
and the right-hand side is the integral.
Here is a visual interpretation of the whole thing.
Let’s say that this is your curve,
and now you have the area under the curve, and that’s the rectangle.
Now there’s a bit of area that’s common over here,
and then a bit over here which only belongs to the rectangle
and a bit that only belongs to the curve,
and what we’re saying over here is that the area of this rectangle
is equal to the area under the curve.
That’s quite a remarkable theorem.
It’s very deep and shows you how powerful calculus is.
We’re able to reduce the area under a curve
to the area of a rectangle,
which is the simplest thing one might think about in areas.
Okay. As an application, here’s a function,
and you want to find a value in the interval –2 to 3
such that the function value is equal to
the average value over that interval.
Now because the function is continuous, it’s a polynomial,
so you can certainly apply the theorem, the mean value theorem.
Let’s say you want to do that.
You solve the equation f[c] equal to the average value,
and when you do that, you get back an answer.
Here’s a plot which shows the point at which
the average value is actually retained.
That’s the mean value theorem in action.
But the main point is that sometimes you can get
more than one point at which the average value is retained.
Here’s an example.
You have a function.
You try and work out the average value, and then work out
the point at which you want to check whether
the average value equals the function value.
You get two points now, and here’s a picture which says
that you really have two points at which
the average value is attained.
As an application of these ideas,
here’s a temperature for a city t hours after noon.
You plot the temperate from 1pm to 3am,
and the question is, is there a time at which the temperature
equals the average temperature?
The answer is yes.
Just solve the equation and you get back that c is about 8.57.
That’s in hours, so that means at around 8:34pm,
the temperature will be equal to the average temperature
over the time period.
As another application, let’s look at a car on a highway.
Here is the velocity of the car, and you want to find
the average velocity over the time period.
What you do is you simply integrate
and divide by the time interval.
Here’s a plot which shows clearly that
the average value is attained at two different points,
so the average velocity is attained twice in the interval.
That brings me to the end of this lesson,
but the main point for today is that with integration,
you can find the average value of a function over an interval.
That average value is given by the integral
divided by the length of the interval.
The mean value theorem is a very powerful theorem
which says that if you have a continuous function,
then it takes on its average value at least once—
could be more than once, but at least once—in the interval.
Of course once you have this very powerful theorem,
you could apply it to temperatures or velocities
or all kinds of other fillable phenomena.
You have the mean value theorem, which tells you that
the area under the curve is equal to the area of a certain rectangle.
That’s a very powerful theorem for calculus.
In the next lesson we’ll talk about approximate values of integrals,
but for now, do review this lesson,
go over the idea for the mean value
and I’ll see you next time.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.