Hello, and welcome to Lesson 40
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is part 2 of a sample calculus exam.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
Like I said earlier on, this is the second part of the calculus exam
that I’ll present now.
As in part 1, which we presented last time,
the questions over here are very similar to what you might find
on the AP Calculus AB exam, but of course the questions over here
will be somewhat more difficult than the ones in the first part.
In fact, there are a couple of them which are really quite involved.
I’ll warn you a little more at that time,
but do pay careful attention.
This is the hard part of the exam.
Let’s begin with question 14, where we left off last time.
The question is calculate the limit
of this expression over here at h = 0.
Now the point is that it looks like a limit, no doubt,
but if you look at the expression very carefully,
it’s really a derivative,
and in fact, it’s a derivative of Sec[x] at π/3—
after all, it’s like f[x] + h – f[x]/h.
If you work out the derivative of secant,
that’s secant times tangent,
so you would expect the answer to be 2√3.
Let’s check that with D.
You find the derivative of Sec[x] and plug in x as π/3,
and you do get back the expected answer.
Or you could use Limit and find the answer,
and you get back just the same result.
Let’s move on to question 15, which says that a disk was measured
to have a radius of 9 cm.
The error was around 0.04 cm.
The question is find the error in the area.
You’ve got two variables—you’ve got the radius and the area—
and they are related by A = πr^2.
Now if that’s the relation, then the differentials, the errors
are related by dA = 2πrdr by taking derivatives,
so what you do is you recall that from the information given to you,
that r is 9, dr is 0.04—that’s the error—so now the error in the area
would be 2π times r times dr, and so the answer is 2.26 roughly.
Okay. On to number 16, which says find the derivative of Log[x^2 – 3].
Now that looks like something for which you need the chain rule,
so what you do is you find the derivative of log,
which is 1/(x^2 – 3),
and then multiply by the derivative of x^2 – 3, which is 2x.
That’s the final answer.
You can check it with D, and you do get back just the same result.
On to number 17, which says calculate the third derivative
of the expression over here, 3x^4 – Cos[x] + e^2x.
What you do is you work out the first derivative,
which is 12x^3 from 3x^4, plus Sin[x] from the second term
and 2e^2x from the third term.
Check that with D, then start here and work out the second derivative,
which is Cos[x] from the Sin[x], then 36x^2 from the from the 12x^3
and 4e^2x from the first term over here.
Let’s check that with D again, the second derivative,
then work out the third derivative
as the derivative of this expression over here.
Then you get back –Sin[x] from the Cos[x],
you get back 72x from here
and you get back an 8e^2x from the first term.
Then you check that with D, taking the third derivative,
and you get back the answer.
Okay. On to number 18, which says that the region bounded by x + 2
and the quadratic over here is rotated around the x axis.
The question is to find the volume of the solid
made by this rotation.
Here is a plot.
You have a straight line and a parabola, an upward parabola,
and the question is where do these two intersect?
Well, what you do is you use Solve
and find out where the straight line and the curve intersect.
You get a lower limit and an upper limit.
Now if you let f be the first function and g be the second function,
then clearly f is below g.
Because you are rotating around the x axis,
you might want to use the washer method over here.
That tells you you must use π(g(x)^2 – f(x)^2)dx inside.
If you do the integral over here using Integrate,
you get back the final answer for the problem.
On to number 19, which says find the limit of this quotient over here.
Now as a first step, what you could do is you’re working at 0,
so you plug in 0 for both the numerator and the denominator,
and what you find is that in fact, you have a 0/0 situation.
That’s an indeterminacy,
so that should remind you of L’Hospital’s rule,
which says that you work out the derivatives of
the numerator and denominator separately,
plug in x goes to 0, and you get back 5/3,
which is the correct answer, as you can check with Limit.
Here is a plot which confirms that you indeed have
the correct answer for the limit.
On to number 20, which says to calculate
the integral over here from 2 to 3.
Now that looks like the case of the substitution rule
because you need to put the denominator u equal to x^2 – 1.
If you work out the derivative, you get du = 2xdx.
Then you need to change the endpoints—
after all, you’re going from x to u.
When x is 2, then u is 3.
When x is 3, then 3^2 – 1 is 8,
so that’s the new integral over here,
which turns out to be 3/2 * Log[8/3].
You can check the answer with Integrate,
and you do get back just the same result.
Here is a plot which shows the area which you just computed.
On to number 21, which says find y' if y^2 + x * y = 2.
The point is because you need to work with y^2,
we should use implicit differentiation.
What you do is you work out the derivative
of each term in the equation separately.
That’s the derivative of y^2,
and the second term over here has got
a derivative with the product rule,
and of course the right-hand side has the derivative 0.
You work out the derivative for each term separately,
so you get 2ydy/dx from here,
and then you try and simplify the answer.
You get dy/dx = –y(2y + x).
Of course you can do the same thing in the Wolfram Language,
and you get back the value for y' at the point (x, y),
which is –y[x]/(x + 2y[x]).
On to number 22, which says find the equation
of the normal to this curve at (–2, –4).
Now keep in mind that the normal is really
the perpendicular to the curve at the point,
so you first work out the slope at that point.
When I say slope, I mean the derivative,
and the derivative of this curve is just x + 3,
so you plug in the value for x and you get the slope as 1.
But that’s for the tangent,
so the normal line will have slope –1 from here.
You write down the equation of the normal at that point,
and you get the equation y = –x – 6.
Here is a plot which shows the given normal.
You have the curve over here and the normal over there.
Okay. On to number 23, which says for what value of a and b
will this function over here become differentiable?
Basically you have a piecewise function
because there are two pieces over here,
and they both meet at –1 provided a and b have got the right values.
Now you want your function to be differentiable,
so there are two conditions.
First of all, the left-hand derivative at –1
should equal the right-hand derivative, and secondly,
the left-hand limit at –1 should equal the right-hand limit.
Now for the first condition, if you differentiate over here,
you get a = 3b(–1)^2 – 4(–1),
and the second relation over here for the limits
will just be obtained by putting in x = –1.
You solve those two for a and b,
so that says that a is 11/2 and b is 1/2.
Then the function is differentiable.
Here is the graph of this function,
and you can see that it’s nice and smooth at the required point, –1.
On to number 24, which says a particle moves
according to the velocity v(t) = 4sin(t)cos(t).
The question is find the total distance that it travels
from 0 to π in seconds.
To do that you must work out the integral,
but you must ignore the sign because you want a distance,
so you have an absolute value over here.
Use the Integrate function with the absolute value,
and you get back the answer as 4.
Here’s a plot which shows the distance that you have found.
Of course keep in mind that the negative area, in this case,
was counted as positive because we want the distance traveled.
On to one of the most difficult questions for this exam, number 25,
that will occupy two slides, so do pay careful attention.
The question is a cylindrical can has got a volume of 216 cm^3.
The question is find a value for the radius
that will minimize the amount of material used.
Now if you make a can, then the material will cover the surface,
so you’re talking about surface area of the can.
Now surface area has got two parts.
One is the top and bottom areas, which give you 2πr^2,
and the side area, which is 2πrh,
so the total surface area is 2πrh + 2πr^2.
But keep in mind that you have two variables, r and h,
so you must eliminate one of them.
You know that πr^2h is 216—after all, that’s given to you over here.
You can solve for h in terms of r,
and now the surface area no longer depends upon h.
It only depends upon r,
and that is the starting point for the second part of the problem.
Now what we do is we start with the expression for the surface area
and try and minimize it with respect to r.
What you do is you take the derivative, set it equal to 0
and you solve, and you get back r as roughly 3.25
and exactly it is 3 times the cubed root of 4/π.
Now let’s check that you have a minimum,
so work out the second derivative at that value of r.
It looks positive, so you have a minimum.
Basically the can will use the least amount of material
when the radius is around 3.25 cm.
On to the final question for the exam, this sample exam.
You have a spherical balloon that’s losing air at a certain rate.
The question is find the rate at which the radius is decreasing
when the radius is 10 cm.
Now keep in mind that you actually have a relation
volume and radius, which is V = 4πr^3/3 for the sphere.
If you find the derivative, you get dV/dt from there
equal to 4πr^2 dr/dt.
That’s just the differential version of the relation.
Okay. Now you know the value of dV/dt as –2,
so you can work out the value of dr/dt by solving,
and you get back the answer as –1/200π.
The radius is decreasing—after all, you have a negative answer—
at a rate of 1/200π cm/sec.
Okay. That brings me to the end of this sample exam,
and also to the end of the course.
It’s been a great pleasure to teach you.
From here on, we wish you all the best.
From all of us here at Wolfram U,
good luck, and thank you.