Hello, and welcome to Lesson 14 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is related rates.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson. In most problems, there will be
more than one thing that is changing in relation to something else. For example,
you might have—of course time varies, but then two other things vary with time.
As a good instance of that, let’s talk about a ladder that’s falling along a side of a wall.
That’s the ladder. It’s falling along the wall, and there are two things that are changing:
there’s the height of the ladder from the top and the distance from the base of the ladder
to the base of the wall. Both of these are changing as the ladder falls.
Of course, the rate at which the height is dropping and the rate at which
the distance is increasing are related. That’s the theme for today’s lesson: related rates problems.
Let’s begin with an example, and that’s exactly the one we talked about earlier on of the falling ladder,
but now we’ve got numbers in it. We have a ladder that’s 5 feet long, and it’s resting initially
against a wall, and then it starts to slide down. Let’s say it slides down away from the wall
at a rate of 0.5 ft/s and the bottom of the ladder is 4 feet away from the wall at a certain point.
The question is how fast is the ladder sliding down at that time instant? The first step
in this case is to assign variables to whatever is changing in the problem. There are two things
that are changing. There is the height—y, let’s say—and the distance x.
Next I draw a picture of what’s happening. The picture is over here.
That’s the distance of the base, that’s the height and that’s the actual ladder over here.
Okay. Now to find a relationship between x, y and 5 over here, you recall
the Pythagorean theorem from geometry, and that says that x^2 + y^2 = 5^2.
That’s the relationship that we require between x and y. Now because we want to find the rates,
we differentiate that relation with respect to t. What you get back is 2x[t]x'[t] + 2y[t]y'[t] = 0.
Now keep in mind that x is 4 at that point, x' is 0.5, so you get back an equation which is
simpler than the earlier one, but it still ignored y’s. Then you recall the Pythagorean theorem,
and that lets you find y as being 3. Once we’ve got y, we can plug that back in over here
to the earlier equation—that’s this one—and you get back the rate of change of y as being −0.666667.
The ladder is sliding down the wall at a rate of 0.67 ft/sec approximately. The question is
why is that sign negative? Well, it’s negative because the top of the ladder is actually going down.
Having solved that one problem, let’s set up a general strategy for solving such problems.
First, always try to understand the problem. Make sure you know what you are asked to do.
Next, assign symbols to all variables—x, y, et cetera—in the problem.
Now to help yourself understand the problem better, draw a picture. It doesn’t have to be very elegant,
but it should be just enough for you to understand what you need to do. Next, the creative part:
find an equation that relates all the variables in the problem. Usually something from geometry
is going to help you to do that. Next differentiate the equation with respect to time using the chain rule.
That’s the key rule for today’s lesson. Now you already know a few variables,
but you need to find any remaining unknown variables before you proceed. Once you have done that,
then you substitute all the information that you’ve found out and solve for the true
unknown quantity in the problem. That’s the general strategy for this lesson.
Let’s try and apply it to a few more problems. Here you have a spherical balloon
that’s being filled at a rate of 50 cm^3/sec. The question is find the rate at which
the radius is increasing when the diameter is 25 cm. Now in this case, the volume and the radius
are both functions of time. Here’s a picture. It has the radius and the volume as being
the variables for the problem. Next, you know from geometry that the volume of a sphere is (4/3)πr^3,
so that’s the relation. Next you differentiate that relation, and you get back an equation
relating v', r and r'. Of course you need to find what r is at that time t, but you know the diameter
is twice the radius and the diameter is 25, so the radius at that time is 12.5.
You plug back all the information that’s known to you, and you find that
the radius is increasing at roughly 0.025 cm/sec.
For the third problem, let’s talk about a watchdog. There is a cat that is walking down a street
at 3 feet per second. Now, a dog is sitting and sees this cat and stays focused on it.
It doesn’t actually move, but then the dog is known to be 6 feet from the street
and the cat is 8 feet from that point. The question is how fast is the dog’s head turning?
There are two things that are changing: the dog’s head is turning and the cat is moving away.
The question is what do you do over here? Well, you first draw a picture.
That’s the angle of turning of the dog’s head, that’s the distance traveled by the cat down the street
and this distance over here is given to us to be 6 feet. Now in this case
we have a right-angle triangle, so we can use the tangent of θ as the function x[t]/6.
Once we have the relation over here, then you can differentiate it and you find that
you have another relation for θ' now, but now you need to know what the secant of θ is.
Well, the point is that you have the Pythagorean theorem, so you use that to work out
the hypotenuse of the triangle at that time. It turns out to be 10. Use that to find the secant
like we’ve done over here. Once we’ve done that, you can plug in all the values
and work out the rate at which the dog’s head is turning.
The dog’s head is rotating at 9/50 radians/sec or about 10.313 degrees/sec.
Okay. On to the final problem for the lesson. Oil is being poured into an inverted cone
at a rate of 3 m^3/sec. That’s the rate of change of the volume. Given that the cone’s height is 10 m
and the radius is 5 m, the question is find the rate at which the oil level is rising
when the oil is 5 m deep. You’ve got two variables over here: the volume and the height.
That’s the picture for the problem. Now, you know from geometry that the volume of a cone
is given by (1/3)πr^2h, so that’s the equation for the problem.
Notice that you in fact have v, h and r, and in fact you want to work only with v and h,
so we need to do a bit more work. Recall that when you studied similar triangles,
then you could find a relationship between the base and height. In this case,
the radius is going to be half the height in the oil tank because by similarity,
any cone in the tank has a radius equal to half the height because you have the initial ones
and the same ratio. Here’s the volume equation with that relationship.
You differentiate it and plug in values, and you find that oil level is rising at 12/25π m/s.
Okay. That brings me to the end of the lesson, but our main objective over here
was to solve problems which involved related rates. What we did was we set up
a general strategy for these problems. Then we solved a few of them, but in each case,
what you need to do is to use the given information and then apply some geometry
typically to get the equations required for the problem. That’s the end of this topic.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about linear approximations, but before we do that,
do review this lesson. This was a pretty advanced application of calculus.
It’s just that we now know calculus so well that we can apply things quite easily,
but do review this lesson, look at the exercises and you should be ready for the next one
on linear approximations. I’ll stop over here. Thank you.