Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 3 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this session is special derivatives, and what we’ll do is to take up several examples
to review the rules for derivatives and also get some extra practice on this topic.
Let’s begin with problem number 1, which says compute the derivative of 7x^3 − 2.
Now that is a polynomial, so things are quite simple. What you do is you apply
the power rule to 7x^3, and the answer is 21x^2. That’s a constant, −2, so the derivative is 0.
You can confirm the answer with D and check that it’s actually 21x^2.
Here is a plot of the function and the derivative. The blue part is the function
and the orange part is the derivative. You can see that the function is increasing,
so the derivative stays non-negative all the time.
Problem number 2 says compute the derivative of Sin[x]/x^2. Now this requires the quotient rule,
so what you do is you do denominator times derivative of numerator minus numerator
times derivative of denominator over denominator squared. When you do that,
you get (xCos[x] − 2Sin[x])/x^3. You can check the answer with D, and you get back
almost the same thing, except that you might need to take an x here to get both of them
to agree exactly. Here’s a plot of the function and its derivative. Let’s go on to number 3.
It says find the derivative of xSec[x] − 2x^2. Now for the first term over here, xSec[x],
what you do is you work out the derivative with the product rule, so you get
x * Sec[x]' + Sec[x] * (x)', and that’s the answer over here. You can check the answer with D.
And then for the 2x^2, the derivative is 4x by the power rule. Then you combine them with
the difference rule, and you get the answer. You can confirm that with D to check that it’s correct,
and finally, here is a plot of the function and its derivative.
On to number 4, which says compute the derivative of √Csc(x).
Over here apply the chain rule, which says that you have the derivative being
1/2 * Csc(x)^(−1/2) * Csc(x)'. You do a bit of work and you get back −1/2Cot[x]√Csc[x].
You can check the answer with D, and you get back almost the same thing except that
D has simplified a bit more and replaced the cotangent over here by cosine over sine. You can then
plot the derivative and the function and get this nice visual for the whole problem.
Okay. On to number 5, which says find the derivative of 4 * (3)√6 − Sin[5x]. This is a composition,
so you need to be a bit careful. What you do is you do constant 4 * 1/3(6 − Sin[5x])^(−2/3).
That’s 1 − 1/3^−1, and then you get the derivative over here of 6 − Sin[5x]', which is −5Cos[5x].
That’s the final answer over here. You can check it with D, and you get back the same result.
Then you can plot the function derivative and get back a plot of the whole problem.
Okay. On to number 6, which says find the second derivative—so this time,
it’s the second derivative of this quotient. It’s a quotient, (2x + 3)/(8x − 1), so you apply
the quotient rule. It’s, again, denominator times derivative of numerator minus numerator
times derivative of denominator, and you get back a result. You can check the answer with D
for the first derivative. Then apply the power rule to the answer and you get back the second derivative.
You can confirm the answer with D and check that you get the same result.
Here’s a plot of the function and its derivative.
Let’s go on to number 7, which says find the second derivative of this product.
You apply the product rule: first function times derivative of second plus second function
times derivative of first. Get the answer with D to check. Then you need to apply two rules:
the product rule over here for each of these parts separately, and then the sum rule.
After we do some work, you get the answer over here by hand. You can confirm with D
and check that the answer is correct, and then finally, we plot the function and derivative.
Notice we are talking about the second derivative over here, and it turns out that in this case,
this second derivative is all non-negative.
Okay. Let’s go on now to problem number 8, which says find the third derivative of Sin[x^2].
You apply the chain rule to get the first derivative. That’s going to be Cos[x^2] * 2x.
That’s from the x^2 over here. Check the answer with D. Apply the chain rule
and the product rule over here, so you get 2x times the derivative of the second factor, et cetera,
and check the answer with D. Then finally you can apply three rules—the chain rule,
the product rule and the difference rule—to find the third derivative, and confirm the answer with D.
Here’s a plot of the function and the third derivative.
On to problem number 9, which says find the third derivative of 4x^3 − 1/x.
For the first derivative you can apply the power rule and the difference rule, so you get 12x^2
from the 4x^3 and 1/x^2 from the −1/x. Check the answer. Apply the same rule again,
so you get 24x − 2/x^3. Check the answer with D. Then find the third derivative,
which would be 24 from here and plus 6/x^4 from there, and you get back
the same result from D. Finally you plot the function and the third derivative.
Okay. On to problem number 10. Now this is about the topic of implicit differentiation,
so keep in mind that the derivative of y is going to be y'. The equation is y Cot[x] = Cos[y]
and you want to find the derivative at (π/2, π/2), so x and y are both π/2. When you apply the rule,
you get y times the derivative of cotangent, which is −Csc[x]^2, plus Cot[x] times y',
and on the right-hand side you get −Sin[y] times y'. Check the answer with D.
Then you solve for y'[x] like I’ve done over here, and finally you plug in the value of x and y,
and you get back π/2 as the derivative at that point. Once we have the derivative,
you can compute the tangent line, y = π/2 + π/2(x − π/2). Plot the curve and the derivative,
and you get back this beautiful plot over here.
On to number 11, which says compute the derivative for this implicit function.
You have a y^2 over there, so you get 2y * y' = 6x − 1 for the derivative. Check that with D.
Solve for y'. You get back the answer. Plug in the values 1/2 and 1/2 for x and y, and you get back 2 as
the slope of the derivative. You plot the tangent line like I’ve done over here,
and you get back the curve and the tangent line at the given point.
Okay. On to number 12, which says find the normal line to this curve at (1, 1).
The normal line is perpendicular to the tangent line, so you must first find the slope of the tangent
and then work out the slope of the normal. If you find the derivative over here,
you get 8x + 4y + 4xy'—that’s from this middle term over here—plus 2y * y' = 0.
Check with D. Solve for y'. You notice that you get back this −2, and we’ll see why this is
the case in a minute. The slope of the normal line will of course be 1/2 because it is
perpendicular to the tangent line. That’s the equation of the normal. Then you can plot the curve
and the normal, and in fact, this curve is just a pair of straight lines, and that’s why you have
a constant slope for the curve. The normal line of course is perpendicular to the curve,
so that’s the normal line.
Okay. On to number 13, which says find the second derivative for this implicit equation.
If you find the derivative, you get 2y * y' − 2x = 0. Check the answer with D.
Solve for the derivative, and you get back x/y basically. Now work out the second derivative
starting from the equation we got earlier on over here, and you get back a simple result.
You get back 2y * y'' + (y')^2 − 2 = 0. Check with D. Solve for y'', and then you notice that
you still have a y' inside the answer, so you plug in y'[x] equal to x or y like I have done over here,
and you get back the final result for y''.
And finally, we go on to number 14, which says find the second derivative of this implicit equation.
We’ve got Sin[y] = Tan[x]. Work out the derivative on both the sides. Check the answer with D.
Solve for y'. Take a second derivative starting from the equation over here, so we get
the expression over there. Check the answer with D again. Solve for y''.
Then you still have a y'[x] inside the result, so you plug in y'[x] as Sec[x]^2Sec[y]
and you get back the result for the second derivative.
This brings me to the end of today’s problem session. I hope you have learned something
about how to compute derivatives of all kinds. We’ll then go on to Lesson 13,
which is about rates of change, but before we do that, do make sure that you understand
today’s problem session quite well and do practice a lot before we go on to the next topic.
Thank you. I’ll stop over here.