Hello, and welcome to Lesson 37
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is separable differential equations.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
The fact is that most differential equations cannot be solved easily.
For example, here’s a nonlinear equation.
What I mean by that is that you’ve got y[x]^2 over here,
and DSolve can solve the equation, but the solution is rather messy
and involves these so-called Bessel functions,
which occur in the oscillations of drums and elsewhere.
In contrast to that, there are other equations
where you actually can find a simple solution.
Here’s an example where the solution is quite simple,
and if you look over here, in part it’s because
the differential equation itself is a bit simpler.
This is an example of a separable differential equation.
The theme of this lesson is to talk about
these separable differential equations.
The question is what is a separable differential equation?
Well, a separable differential equation is
an equation of the form y', the derivative of y,
equal to some function of x times some function of y.
Okay. Now if you look at this,
the right-hand side is certainly what you’d call separable.
You can separate x and y.
The question is how about the left-hand side?
Well, recall that y' is dy/dx,
so we can think of that as a separation for y'.
For example, here is the differential equation
that we spoke about in an earlier slide, and if you want to solve it,
you replace y' by dy/dx
and then you separate your variables like over here.
You have (1/y)dy = xdx like you do in algebra.
Then you integrate both the sides.
Then you say that this y is e^(C + (x^2/2)),
but that’s the same as e^C * e^(x^2/2),
and then that itself with e^C
is another constant which we will call K.
The solution is y equal to some constant times e^(x^2/2).
That is the general solution of the differential equation.
Okay. On to another example.
Let’s try and solve the differential equation y' = y.
In this case, you can think of f[x] = 1 and g[y] = y,
so that’s the separation of the right-hand side.
Keep in mind that y' is dy/dx, so you separate your variables,
rearrange and you get dy/y = 1dx.
Then you integrate both sides.
I haven’t put the constant, but it’s certainly there in the background.
So y is e^(x + C) where C is a constant,
so you get e^C * e^x.
That’s K * e^x.
You can confirm the answer with DSolveValue,
and you get back just the same result.
Okay. On to a slightly harder example
where you have y' = 3x^3/(4y + Sin[y]).
In this case, f is just the numerator,
and for g, you can take 1 over the denominator.
That’s the differential equation,
and then you separate the variables and rearrange.
Integrate both the sides separately, and now we see that
the solution is going to be 2y^2 – Cos[y] = (3x^4)/4 + C.
Here is a plot of the solution with ContourPlot.
Okay. The question is what happens when there are initial values?
Let’s take the equation y' = x * y
with the initial condition y[0] = 1.
That’s an initial value problem with a value of y given at 0.
The question is can you then find a particular solution
of this differential equation?
Let’s rearrange the equation as earlier.
Solve it, so you get y equal to K, where K is a constant,
times e^(x^2/2).
Now we plug in the initial values.
You get y[0] = 1, so you get 1 = K * e^0, so K = 1.
The solution is y = e^(x^2/2).
You can confirm that with DSolve.
You can also check the solution plot by doing a StreamPlot.
Okay. On to some applications, and we’ll take two of them.
The first one is for current.
Here’s an equation that describes a circuit
in which there’s some charge flowing, some resistance,
some capacitance and some voltage—that’s supposed to be circuit.
That’s the equation, the differential equation, for the charge q.
Now of course if v depends on t, that’s much harder,
so we’ll assume that v itself is a constant,
so we’ve got constant resistance, capacitance and voltage.
In that situation where v does not depend upon t,
you can solve for q', and then you see that
things are separable over here.
You separate the equation and get an expression for t
in terms of everything else, but we want to solve for q.
You solve for q.
The Normal here just means you’re ignoring some conditions on q.
The solution is c times v
minus e raised to that expression over there,
but if you think about this, it’s really e^(–k/c) * e^(–t/r).
That’s just K * e^–t(c * r).
One final point.
As the time approaches ∞ as more and more time goes by,
the value of e^–∞ = 0, so this term, drops out,
and the final solution is that the charge approaches c * v
as t approaches ∞.
A second example is for Newton’s law of cooling.
Here is a differential equation for the temperature
when an object at temperature t0 initially is placed in a medium
where the temperature is held constant at s.
What happens is that the rate of change of temperature
is proportional to the difference between the current temperature
and the temperature of the surroundings.
As time goes by and the difference becomes small,
the rate falls down as well.
You need to determine k.
We’re given the initial condition that the temperature at 0 is t0.
Now of course over here we have a separable equation,
so you separate the variables and you get back
an expression for t in terms of temperature,
but you want to solve for temperature,
so you do that and you get an answer.
Now the point is that e^(c * k) is a constant,
so again you can call that some c and you solve for that constant.
The final solution is that the solution for the temperature at time t
is (–s + t0)e^(k * t) + s.
You can check the answer with DSolve,
and you get back the same expression.
Now the question is how to determine k.
To find k, what you need is the temperature t1 at some later time τ.
Suppose we know that temperature.
Then we plug the values in into the solution
and you solve for k, and that is the expression for k.
The constant k is Log[(s – t1)/(s – t0)]/τ.
As an application, let’s say you have got
a cup of boiling coffee at 100 ºC.
It’s boiling.
You put it in a room in which the temperature is 22 ºC.
Let’s say an hour later, the temperature of the coffee is 60 ºC.
Then what you can do is you can model the coffee temperature
by the equation over here where I’ve plugged in the value of k
based on the given information.
That is the starting temperature, that’s the room temperature,
and you want to model the coffee over a period of time.
Let’s see what happens to it over a period of, let’s say, 10 hours.
You can see that the temperature slowly approaches
the room temperature, which is 22, and in fact,
you can use Limit to check that the answer is actually 22
when you have let infinitely many hours pass by.
That’s Newton’s law which models the cooling of objects
which are placed in a room with a higher temperature
than room temperature.
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson,
and the main point is that separable equations are,
in general, rather easy to solve.
The way that you solve them is to note that
the right-hand side is a function of x times a function of y,
and then you can replace y' by differentials dy and dx
and then solve the equation.
Now of course you can use that to model the various phenomena.
For example, you can model the charge in a circuit
by a separable differential equation,
or you can model the temperature over time for a hot object
using separable differential equations.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about how we can make programs
that help to solve calculus problems
when doing differential equations.
But before that, do revise today’s lesson.
It’s quite an important topic, separable differential equations.
I’ll see you in the next lesson.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.