Hello, and welcome to Lesson 8 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is the derivative as a function.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson. In Lesson 7, you learned about
finding the derivatives at particular points for a function. Now the fact is that
you can go beyond that and the derivative itself can be regarded as a function.
Starting with a function, you can find the derivative, and then that gives you another function.
The way to do that in the Wolfram Language is to use to the function D. Let’s say you have
a function f[x] like over here. You can work out the derivative using D, and you get back
another function. Now you can plot the function and the derivative on the same plot,
and you get back this picture of the function in blue and its derivative in orange.
The point over here is that the derivative is a function just like the earlier one,
and you can keep on doing the same process, and that’s the plan for today, to talk about
derivatives as functions and higher derivatives.
Okay. A simple example. Let’s say I ask you to find the derivative of x^3 + x.
You can work out the derivatives in D—that’s 3x^2 + 1—and then you can also use f'[x].
that’s another way to do the same thing. You can plot the function derivative
and you get back the result, which is the plot for both these functions. Now the difficulty is that
there are many ways to write derivatives. Let’s talk a little bit about derivative notation.
Some people prefer to write f[x] for the function then f'[x] for the derivative. Others prefer D.
Some prefer y’, some use dy/dx, some use df/dx, et cetera. In fact, mathematicians like
to think of D and d/dx as being as being differentiation operators which work on functions
and give you their derivatives. The whole process of calculating derivatives is called differentiation.
There is a lot of terminology over here, but as far as we are concerned, if you know D and f',
that’s good enough for you. So here I’ve got D[f[x]] and f'[x], and you get back
just the same result in both the cases. For this lesson, if you know D and f',
that’s enough to do all the calculations.
Okay. One issue with derivatives is that they are defined by limits. If they are limits,
and because you can talk about left-hand and right-hand limits, you can also talk about
left-hand and right-hand derivatives at a point. Here’s a function g
defined using the RealAbs function, the absolute value function, and clearly there will be
an issue at 5 where the sign changes. If you find the derivatives from the right and left at 5,
then what you see is that they are different, so you have a problem
because the left-hand and right-hand derivatives at the point 5 do not agree.
If you plot the function derivative, you see a little more clearly. That’s the original function,
and the derivative is 3 on the right and −3 on the left. That’s one way in which things can go wrong,
namely that the left-hand limit and the right-hand limit do not agree,
and you do not have a derivative at that point.
Let’s talk about differentiability. A function is differentiable if f'[a] exists for a point a,
and of course if you were to have a whole range of values from a to b, then it’s differentiable
if it’s differentiable at every point, every number in that interval. Here’s a function.
Let’s find the derivative. The question is where is it differentiable? Well, the only difficulty
would be at 0 because then you have a 0 in the denominator over here, and in fact,
if you work out the left- and right-hand derivatives at this point at 0, then you do see
that they are very different. In fact if you plug in 0 into f'[x], you get back an indeterminate answer.
Here’s a function which we just showed you which is differentiable everywhere except at 0.
The question arises in what way can a function be non-differentiable? When can things go wrong?
One way that they can go wrong is if you’re at a corner. Here’s an example.
You have the absolute value function times 3, and if you plot it with the derivative, you see that at 0
the calculation and graph both show that you have a problem at 0. You have a corner over there
which leads to the differentiability being lost. Here’s a corner for the function,
and that’s an issue for differentiability. Another thing that can go wrong is that you are at a cusp.
Here’s a cube root function, and at 0 again the problem is because you actually have a cusp.
That’s a cusp over there, a change in shape, and that’s going to cause you problems with derivatives.
You can see the derivative does not exist at 0.
A third way in which things can go wrong is if you are at a discontinuity of a function.
Here’s a function. It’s piecewise, and it changes form at 0. That’s the function.
Work out the derivative, and its 0 is a problem. You get indeterminate. If you plot it,
you can see quite clearly that everything’s fine everywhere except at 0.
One last thing that can go wrong is if you are at a vertical tangent. Here’s the cube root function again,
and if we look at 0, you actually have a problem because you have a vertical tangent over there.
That’s the way in which things can go wrong, but for the most part, functions will be differentiable,
and if they are not, it will only happen at a few isolated points.
Now starting with a function, you cannot just work out the first derivative like over here,
but you can go a step further and work out the second derivative. The second derivative is
the derivative of the first derivative. We with start with 4x^3. You get 12x^2 and then you get 24x,
and you can get the same result by using D with this notation, which says differentiate f
with respect to x two times, and you get back just the same answer. That’s the shorthand
for computing the second derivative. Here are the plots of all three. There’s f, there’s the first derivative
and the second derivative. The point is starting from a function, you can work out the derivative.
Then you can work its derivative, and they are all just as good as functions.
Now of course you can go on with that, and in the Wolfram Language you can work out the nth derivative
for any value of n, whether it be 1 or 2 or 6 or 100 or whatever. Here’s a simple function x^6.
You can work out the first six derivatives. The first expression over here is just the function itself,
and the last one is 720, which means that you are almost at the edge
where things are going to start becoming 0. Okay. Here’s a plot of the first six derivatives.
You have the function over here, first derivative, second derivative, et cetera.
You can see over here that the nth derivative is a function just like the earlier one.
Okay. Now in physics, there are some special names for nth derivatives.
Here’s a position function s[t], and if you work out the first six derivatives, they’ve got names.
They’re called the velocity, the acceleration, the jerk, snap, crackle, pop.
That’s first derivative, second derivative, third derivative, fourth, fifth and sixth.
If you plot them, then just like in the earlier case you get back a plot, but now this shows you
the variation of the position and velocity, et cetera as time goes by.
High derivatives are really quite useful. They occur in physics, they occur elsewhere
and in fact they are what makes calculus so applicable in real life.
Okay. Now we’re at the end of today’s lesson, and what you’ve learned is that you can
work out derivatives not just at points, but for entire functions, and what you get then is
a new function. Because a derivative is a limit, you can compute left and right derivatives.
Now if it happens that the left and right derivatives are not equal, then the derivative
does not exist at the given point. If it does exist, then the function is differentiable at that point.
You’ve got differentiable functions and non-differentiable functions which can occur in many ways,
like you are at a corner, you are at a cusp, et cetera. As I said earlier on,
most functions will be differentiable almost everywhere. Now you can go a step further from derivatives
and work out higher-order derivatives—the first, second, third, fourth, et cetera—
and those are quite useful. For example, they’re useful for studying the motion of a particle.
That’s a lot of stuff over here. We talked about higher derivatives, left derivatives, right derivatives.
That’s a whole bag of ideas, and in the next lesson we’ll try and make things look much simpler
by talking about the rules for finding derivatives. It might all look a little bit difficult right now,
but once you have rules of derivatives, then things will become much simpler.
That’s for Lesson 9, but before that we will have Problem Session 2 and you can take a small quiz,
and that should put you in good shape for Lesson 9. But I’ll stop over here for Lesson 8.
I hope you have enjoyed it. Thank you.