Hello, and welcome to Lesson 35
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is L’Hospital’s rule.
Let’s being with a brief overview of the lesson.
Let’s say you have a continuous function like x^2
and I ask you to find the limit as x approaches 5.
What you could simply do is to plug in the value 5
in the function expression and you’ll get back the correct answer,
which is of course 25 in this case.
But if the function has a point discontinuity,
then this would not work.
For example, over here for g, there is an issue at 1
because the denominator becomes 0.
If you try and find the value at 1,
then you get back an indeterminate answer.
Now of course in this case, what you could do is
to simplify the function algebraically like I’ve done over here,
and then things work just fine.
If I now plug in x = 1,
I get back the limit of the function g when x goes to 1.
But there are functions for which this will not work.
For example, you have h over here, which is Log[x – 1]/(x – 2),
and simplifying h makes no difference.
The question is what do you do in such a case?
In such a case, you can apply something called L’Hospital’s rule,
and that is the theme for this lesson, L’Hospital’s rule.
Okay. Before going on to the rule itself,
let’s talk about so-called indeterminate forms.
Let’s say you have a function f which is Sin[x] and g which is x.
Now you try and work out the ratio f[0]/g[0],
and you get back an indeterminate.
That’s an indeterminacy of the form 0/0
because both the values are 0 at 0.
If you take the function h over here, then that’s (2x – 1)/(3x + 2),
and if you plug in x = ∞, you get back something like ∞/∞,
so that’s again an indeterminacy.
Next if we take the function y over here,
then at 0 you have a 0 times ∞ over here,
so that’s an indeterminacy of the type 0 times ∞.
When you try and evaluate it, you get back indeterminate.
Finally if you take the function z—that’s Csc[x] – Cot[x]—
and again at 0, you have ∞ – ∞.
That’s a problem.
When you try and evaluate it, you get back indeterminate.
The point is that you will have situations in which
the system gives you back indeterminate,
and then the question is how do you find limits in such cases?
As I said earlier on, the way to do that
is to find the limits using L’Hospital’s rule.
L’Hospital’s rule says that if you have a ratio f[x]/g[x]
and you want to work out the value of that limit as x approaches a,
then what you do is you simply work out the limit of f'[x]/g'[x]
at that value a—assuming of course that that limit exists.
You can reduce a problem to a problem of computing
the limit of a quotient of derivatives.
For example, in our function from the introduction,
you had Log[x – 1]/(x – 2) when x approaches 2,
and you see over here that when you actually take
the derivative and take the ratio of those two,
things are much better.
You can plug in x = 2, and you get back the answer of 1.
You can confirm the answer with Limit,
and you do get back the same result, 1.
L’Hospital’s rule is a very powerful rule which says
if you need to find the value of the limit f[x]/g[x],
you simply find the derivatives of the numerator
and denominator separately and then plug in the values if that works.
Okay. As an example of 0/0,
let’s go back to our ratio f[x]/g[x], Sin[x]/x.
Now you see over here that individually you have 0/0,
but then if you take derivatives, things get much better
and you get back Cos[x], which has a nice value at 0,
namely, it has 1.
The limit of f[x]/g[x], Sin[x]/x, is just 1.
That’s a very nice and important result.
Okay. Next.
If you go on to ∞/∞ like with the function h,
then you have (2x – 1)/(3x + 2).
You work out the limits, and they are both ∞.
But if you could take derivatives and take a quotient,
then you just get back 2/3,
and so the limit of the function h is just 2/3.
Next, go on to the type 0 * ∞ for the function y[x].
Now in this case you don’t really have f[x]/g[x],
so you write it as e^(1/x)/(1/x) and take the derivatives.
Then if you plug in x = 0, you do get back the answer ∞ from above.
That’s the limit for y at 0 from above.
Here’s a plot which shows quite clearly that at 0,
the function does approach ∞ if you go from the right,
if you go from above.
Okay. On to ∞ – ∞ for the function z[x].
Now in this case, what you do is you first of all simplify.
Write the cosecant as 1/Sin[x] and cotangent as Cos[x]/Sin[x]
and get back a ratio.
If you work out those two limits separately, you get back 0/0,
but then if you work them out in terms of derivatives,
you get back Tan[x], which is just 0 at 0,
so the answer for the limit is just 0.
Okay. Now in some cases, you apply L’Hospital’s rule
more than once to get the answer.
For example, here’s a function f defined to be e^x/3x^2.
If we try and apply L’Hospital’s rule once at ∞,
then you get back ∞/∞ again.
That’s again indeterminate, so what you do is
you apply L’Hospital again, and now things look good
because you get back ∞/6, which is ∞,
so the answer for the limit is ∞.
You can apply L’Hospital’s rule repeatedly,
but of course it’s going to be more time-consuming
and more expensive to do so.
Okay. Now some more indeterminate forms.
We have ∞^0 to begin with.
Here’s an example.
Let’s say we have x^(1/x).
If you plug in x goes to ∞, you get ∞^0, so that’s an indeterminacy.
What you do in this case is you apply a logarithm,
and when you do that, then you get back
something which is going to be much more tractable
because the law of logarithms says this is Log[x]/x.
Then what you do is you plug in the derivatives over here,
and you get back 1/x.
When x approaches ∞, the answer is just 0, so Log[y] = 0,
which says that the limit is going to be just 1.
That’s a plot of the function
showing you it approaches 1 as x approaches ∞.
As another example, let’s take 0^0.
When you take x^x and apply 0 to it, you get back 0^0,
but then again, you think of it as being a logarithmic case,
so apply logarithms and you get back xLog[x] like over here.
Then write that as Log[x]/(1/x), apply L’Hospital
and you get back that when x = 0, the answer is 0,
so the original limit is just going to be e^0 = 1.
Finally, let’s take the case where you’ve got 1^∞.
When you’re at π/2, this function becomes 1—Sin[π/2] is 1—
raised to Tan[π/2] is ∞, so that’s 1^∞.
Again, you need to to some logarithmic work.
You say let’s take logarithms.
You get Log[Sin[x]^Tan[x]].
Pull down the Tan[x]—it’s a power—then apply L’Hospital like before.
You plug in π/2, and things look better.
The answer is 0 for the logarithm, and so the actual limit is 1.
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson.
Basically L’Hospital’s rule is very useful
when you have indeterminate forms of the type,
let’s say, 0/0 and ∞/∞.
But of course if you’ve got something like 0^∞ or other things,
you can work too.
Let’s say with some algebraic manipulation, you can tackle
the case where you have 0 * ∞ and ∞ – ∞.
If you take logarithms, then you can also tackle the cases
where you have ∞^0, 0^0 and 1^∞.
Of course sometimes you need to apply L’Hospital’s rule
multiple times to arrive at a suitable answer.
That’s the end of this lesson.
The next lesson will talk about slope fields and Euler’s method,
but before we do that, do revise L’Hospital’s rule.
It’s a very important rule, a very useful rule,
and you surely will benefit a lot from review.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.