Hello, and welcome to Lesson 11 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is the chain rule, so let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
Recall that if you have two functions f and g, then the composition of f and g will
take the values of g and then plug them into f. Here’s an example. You have f given by x^2,
and g is just a sine function. If you try and work out f[g[x]], that’s going to be Sin[x]
and then the square of it, so Sin[x], the whole squared, or sine squared x.
Now, the rules we have discussed so far—the sum rule, product, et cetera—cannot be used to find
the derivatives of such compositions, but of course D knows about them.
What’s required over here is something called the chain rule. The chain rule is what lets you
find out the derivatives of compositions, and that’s the topic for the lesson:
the chain rule and examples for this very powerful rule.
Let’s begin with a statement of the rule. If you have two functions f and g
and if f is differentiable at g[x] and g is differentiable at x, then the composition is also
differentiable at x. The main point now is that the derivative is given by g'[x] on the right
and f'[g[x]] on the left. Here’s an example in the abstract setting. D[f[g[x]] is f'[g[x]] times g'[x].
So, if I said find the derivative of Sin^2[x], you would first work out the derivative of Sin[x]
and then the derivative of x^2, and then would plug in x with Sin[x]. Okay.
Then you get back the answer 2Cos[x]Sin[x]. Here’s a plot of the function and its derivative,
and notice that the function Sin^2[x] is always non-negative, but its derivative can be
either positive or negative depending upon which portion of the graph you are in.
Okay. As an example of an algebraic function with a composition in it, let’s take
the square root of x^2 − 1. Now in this case, the inner function is going to be x^2 − 1,
and the outer one is square root of x, so that’s the composition in this case, g[h[x]].
What you do is you work out the derivative of x^2 − 1, which is 2x, and then work out
the derivative of the outer function, and there’s the answer. D gives the same result,
and here is a plot of the function and its derivative. Of course because we’re finding
the derivative of the square root of x^2 − 1, there’s nothing on the left of 1 over here.
Okay. Here’s a trig function, Cos[x^2]. Now the inner function over here is x^2;
the outer one is Cos[x]. Let’s first set up the composition, and you get back Cos[x^2] from g[h[x]].
You work out the derivative of h. That’s 2x. Work out the derivative of g,
and then that’s the answer. And of course, D gives just the same result.
Here is a plot of the function and its derivative.
Let’s go on now to talking about the power rule. Now, the power rule is a rule for finding
the derivative of x^n, but you can make it even more powerful by just composing it
with another function g. Okay. If I gave you f[g[x]] with g being some function,
then the chain rule says that the derivative is ng[x]^(−1 − n)g'[x]. For example, if I said
find the derivative of (x^4 + 1)^100, you can find it quite easily because all you do is
you do 100 times that raised to 99 times the derivative of (x^4 + 1), which is 4x^3.
Of course, you don’t have to use a positive here. You could use a fraction like in this example,
or you could even use a negative number, and you get back the answer quite easily.
In this very simple way, you can extend the power rule
to find the derivatives of fairly complicated compositions.
Okay. Now if you have a product like over here—f[x] is a product of two things over here:
(3x − 2)^3 and (9x^4 − x +3)^5. You might think that the best way to do it is to expand f.
Well, you could do that and then find the derivative, but that’s going to be a long, messy answer,
so a much better way is to use the product rule and the chain rule together.
You say first function times the derivative of the second one, and then the second function times
the derivative of the first, and you get back the answer, which is the same as
the earlier long answer. In fact, D prefers to use the product rule,
and of course you should do that too. Given a fairly complicated expression like this,
you must try and use the best rules possible to get the most compact answer in the result
because then you can use it much more easily in future work.
Okay. Let’s go on now to talking about multiple compositions. The chain rule itself
talks about the derivative of f[g[x]] as being g'[x] times f'[g[x]], but of course that will hardly be
a chain which only has two links in it, so you can keep on this way and build up chains
of longer and longer lengths. Let’s say that we’ve got f[g[h[x]]] like over here.
The derivative is going to be h'[x] and then g'[h[x]] and then f'[g[h[x]]]. In every case,
you fix the remaining functions or variables and work out derivative. For example, if I gave you
Sin[Cos[x^2]] as your function, then the derivative would be 2x from the x^2, then −Sin[x^2]
from the cosine and then Cos[Cos[x^2]] from the outer sine wave. The answer over here
is confirmed by D, and that tells you that given any long chain of compositions,
you can apply just the same rule and get the result.
A similar example is one I’ll take up next, which is CubeRoot[Cos[x^2]].
Again, you start from the innermost function, x^2, then work out the next function derivative
in the chain and then the outermost derivative. The answer over here is a fairly complicated function,
but D confirms that it is correct. You can plot the function and its derivative, and you get back
this beautiful plot. Just to recall for you the procedure again, you work out the derivative of x^2,
the innermost one, work out the derivative of Cos[x] and replace x with x^2, and then finally
work out the derivative of CubeRoot[x] and replace x with Cos[x^2].
Okay. As a final example, let’s talk about simple harmonic motion.
Simple harmonic motion is a motion that’s given by the scale of a trigonometric function.
Here A is the amplitude. Think about a pendulum. The amplitude is how far it goes in one direction.
ω is the frequency—that is, how fast it goes—and δ is the phase shift. You could have two pendulums
and they both have drastic different motions because they have different phase shifts.
They started, say, at different times and you get different phase shifts.
Now given such a simple harmonic motion, you can work out the velocity and the acceleration
by working out the first and second derivatives. Here are the velocity and acceleration,
v and A, and notice that the acceleration is almost the same as the position except that
it has this − ω^2 multiplied to it as an extra factor. What that says
is that s'' +  ω^2s[t] is equal to 0, and that’s something called a differential equation,
which you will study much later in calculus. The HoldForm does the following.
It prevents anything from evaluating, so if you do ReleaseHold like I’ve done over there,
then in fact you get back the result True, which says that the differential equation is satisfied by
the simple harmonic motion function over here.
Okay. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson. To summarize, the chain rule lets you
find the derivatives of many more functions because you can work out
the derivatives of products and powers, et cetera, much more easily with the help of this rule.
Now of course you can build up a chain of any length so you can use it more than once
where a function is a composition of more than two functions. Those two statements
summarize the lesson, but today’s lesson is probably the most difficult one in our series so far,
so do review it carefully, look at the exercises and make sure you’re ready for the next lesson,
which is on implicit differentiation. I’ll stop over here.
I hope you enjoyed listening. Thank you.