Hello, and welcome to Lesson 30 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is volumes by cylindrical shells.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In the previous lesson, we learned about the disk and washer methods
for finding the volumes of solids.
As an example of the disk method,
let’s say you have the function f[x] = x^2
and you rotate that around the x axis from 1 to 4.
You get a solid of this type.
To find the volume, what you do is you break up the solid into disks,
and each disk then has a radius of x^2, the value of f[x],
so the area of this disk is πr^2 times, of course, the height,
which is the infinitesimal volume.
Then you get the integral of that giving you the volume of the solid.
The washer method is very simple and similar
because all you do is instead of working with one disk,
you simply subtract the volume of two disks, the outer and inner.
Basically it works on washers or rings or annuli
or whatever you call them.
Now a slightly harder example.
Suppose you have the function shown over here
and you want to revolve it around the y axis, not the x axis.
Then it’s not clear what one means by the inner and outer radii.
The goal of this lesson is to talk about
the so-called cylindrical shell method
which makes this example and similar examples very simple.
Let’s build some intuition for the method.
Let’s say you want to find the volume of the solid.
You break it into pieces, but these pieces
are now going to be shells rather than cross sections.
Because each cell looks like a cylinder,
it’s called the cylindrical shell method.
Here’s a typical cylinder.
It’s very thin.
It has an outer radius of r2 and an inner radius of r1,
so that is the difference in the volumes of outer and inner,
which will give you the volume of that thin shell.
If you factor it a little bit, you could rewrite it as
2πh times the average of r1 and r2
times the difference between r1 and r2 like over here.
Now because it’s very thin, you can let r2 approach r1,
in which case the difference over here becomes dr
and the average becomes just r1.
Now because you only have one r left, you might as well call it r.
The volume now becomes 2πhrdr.
The question is what’s h?
Well, h is the value of the function f as a function of r.
The height h becomes now f[r],
so you have a very nice, simple formula for the volume
by the method of cylindrical shells.
To go back to our example from the introduction,
you have this function, f[x] = 4x^3 – x^4.
You want to work out the volume, so you simply do 2πr
times the value of the function over here times dr.
You work it out with Integrate, and you get back the result.
Okay. Now the question is which method should you use,
the washer or disk method or the cylindrical shell method?
Let’s say here’s an example in which you have two curves,
x^2 and x^3, but you want to revolve it around the y axis.
With the washer method, you could rewrite things
as cube roots and square roots and get the answer,
but in this case, it’s much simpler
to simply work with the cylindrical shell method,
and you get back the same result.
You do get the same answer, but the question is which one to use.
That’s up to you, but typically, the cylindrical shell method
works well when the axis of the cylinder
is the same as the rotation axis.
Okay. Some minor variations.
Let’s say you have a function like over here,
and you want to rotate it around the line x = 6
rather than the y axis, let’s say.
Then what you do first of all is you find the radius.
Keep in mind that the radius is now going to be 6 – x
because you are counting from x = 6, so that’s the radius.
You have 2π times radius times function value,
and you get back the answer with the cylindrical shell method.
On the other hand, if you have a negative axis,
so let’s say you have x = –1 over here, and you have this function.
Now if you if you look at the radius, it’s going to be x + 1.
Your formula is slightly different.
You have 2π(x + 1)f[x]dx.
You work out the answer, and you get back the volume in this case.
We spoke a little earlier about comparing the two methods,
washer/disk and cylinder.
Let’s take an example
where the disk or washer method works a little better.
Let’s say you have f[x] = CubeRoot[x].
You now revolve around the x axis from 0 to 1.
If you try the cylindrical shell method, things become a bit harder
because now the shell height is horizontal rather than vertical.
If you had to apply the cylindrical shell method,
you would first of all rewrite the function as a function of y,
then work out the shell radius, then work out the integral.
But with the disk method, things are much simpler
because you simply have the cube root of x as the function,
so you apply π times r^2dx, integrate from 0 to 1
and you get back the same volume.
In general, both these methods—
the cylindrical shell method and the washer/disk method—
have advantages and disadvantages,
and you must decide which one is better suited for your problem.
Okay. That brings me to the end of the lesson.
Basically, what we’ve learned is that the cylindrical shell method
is another nice way of finding the volume of solids.
This method works by breaking up the solid into cylindrical shells.
Those shells are very, very thin, and the height of the shell
is the value of the function.
Sometimes you’ll find that the cylindrical shell method
is much easier, and it can be very cumbersome or even impossible
to apply the disk/washer method.
But other times, you might find that the disk/washer method
is a lot easier to understand and use, so you might prefer that.
Just to review the formulae for the lesson,
first of all if you revolve around the line x = x0
where x0 is positive, then you get x0 – x as the radius,
so think back to the example involving 6 – x.
On the other hand, if you have a negative or 0 value for x0,
then you’ll have x – x0 over here, so think back to the example
which had an x + 1, which really was an x minus –1.
Those two very simple formulae tell you what you need to do
for the cylindrical shell method,
and that makes it a very simple method wherever it works.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about
the average value of a function with integration,
but before doing that, do review today’s lesson.
It’s a very important lesson.
It tells you how to find the volumes of very difficult-looking solids,
and it really shows you how powerful calculus is.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.