Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 5 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this session is maxima and minima, the mean value theorem and curve sketching.
Let’s begin with the first problem for the session. You have the function 2x – x^2,
and the problem is to find the absolute maximum and minimum for this function
on the interval [0, 4]. What you do is you first of all work out the critical numbers
by setting the derivative equal to 0. There’s only one critical number at 1, so you need to test at 0;
the left-hand point at 1, which is a critical point; and at the right-hand point, 4.
When you do that, then the function values tell you that you actually have an absolute maximum at 1
and you have an absolute minimum at 4. Here’s a plot of the function clearly showing you
that you have a maximum at 1 and a minimum at 4.
Okay. For the second example, let’s talk about local maxima and minima
for this polynomial over here. To find the local maxima and minima,
you first work out the critical points as before. There are three of them, so what you do is
you examine the intervals to the left and right of each of them. At –2, the first critical point,
you pick a point to the left and to the right, et cetera, and work out derivatives over there.
You find that in the first case, the derivative goes from negative to positive, et cetera,
so you have a local minimum at –2 and 6 and a local maximum at 5/2.
Here is a plot of the function, and you can see quite clearly that
you do have local minima at –2 and 6, and you do have a local maximum at 5/2.
Now it’s much easier in general to use the second derivative test, so let’s talk about that now.
You have a function, and you want to work out the local maxima and minima
using the second derivative test. Work out the critical points. There’s just two of them, –4 and 1,
so then you work out the second derivatives at those points. In the first case,
you have a negative second derivative, so that says that you actually have a maximum at x = –4,
and you have a positive second derivative, so that says you have a local minimum at x = 1.
Here is a plot of the function showing the local maximum and the local minimum as we just found out.
On to number 4, which talks about the local maxima and minima for
the absolute value function 2 – 3x. Now this function of course does not have a derivative at 2/3,
so we need to examine that as a critical number, and apart from that,
we have no other points where the derivative is 0. What you do is let’s talk about (2/3, 0)
and check what happens to the left of it, the right of it.
The derivatives are negative in the first case and positive in the second case,
so you have a local minimum at x = 2/3. Here’s a plot. Of course in this case,
you could have guessed the answer, but it’s good to know that you can actually
apply the same ideas from derivatives to find the local minimum in this case.
Okay. On to number 5, and now we switch to the mean value theorem.
We have the function Sin[x] + x, and the question is how do we find the value at which
the tangent line actually has the same slope as the secant line joining endpoints.
Here’s the function. That’s the slope of the secant line joining the endpoints.
What you want to do is to find a point at which the derivative is equal to the slope,
which we just found out, and there are two of them. There’s –π/2 and π/2.
You work out the values at those points. You’ve got two points at which
the tangent line is parallel to the secant line joining the endpoints.
Here’s a plot that illustrates that, and you actually see that
you have the two values we just found out over here.
Okay. On number 6, the same thing, the mean value theorem. You have a function 3/(x – 1),
and you want to find out a point at which the tangent line has a slope equal to the secant slope.
You have the slope of the secant. You set that equal to the tangent slope,
and you find that that happens when x is √5, so the value of f[√5] is –1 + (3/√5).
Here’s a plot that shows the secant line and the tangent line
at the point at which the two are parallel.
Okay. On to number 7, which talks about the asymptotes of a rational function.
Now of course the vertical asymptotes occur where the denominator becomes 0.
You solve that equation, and you find that there are two of them.
Because you have the same degree for the numerator and denominator,
you actually will have a horizontal asymptote.
Let’s confirm that Limit confirms our guess of 1/2 after we got a 1 over here
for the coefficient and 2 over there, so the horizontal asymptote is y = 1/2.
Here’s a plot showing that you actually do have the two vertical asymptotes
and one horizontal asymptote.
Okay. Problem number 8—another problem with asymptotes.
Now you work out the vertical asymptotes by setting the denominator equal to 0,
and there are three of them. On the other hand, because the numerator degree
is one greater than the denominator—you’ve got a power of 4 over there and 3 over there,
so there will be a slant asymptote. To find the slant asymptote,
you actually use the polynomial coefficient with PolynomialQuotient,
and you get that as the expression y = –(11/25) + (3x/5).
Here’s a plot which confirms all the information and shows you the slant asymptote as well.
Okay. Let’s go on to problem number 9, which is a slightly more qualitative problem.
Here you’re given the graph of a derivative of a function, and the question is
what can you say about the original function from this information?
Well, you see over here that the derivative is positive over there and over there,
so it’s positive between (–3, 0) and (2, ∞), and it is negative on the remaining two intervals.
You have a local minimum near –3 and also near 2 because if you look at –3,
then it goes from being negative to being positive, and you have a local maximum at 0
because the derivative goes from being positive to being negative.
Finally you have a local maximum for the derivative near –2
and a local minimum for the derivative near 1, so you actually have inflection points there.
In all, you have three local minima and maxima and two inflection points.
Here are all the five points. The black points are the minima and maxima
and the blue points are the inflection points.
Okay. On to number 10, which talks about finding the points of inflection
for this function xCos[x] between –π and π. What you do is you set the second derivative to 0
and solve between –π and π, and you find that the numerical values are 0, –2.28 and 2.28 roughly.
Then you work out the second derivatives at suitable points, and you find over here
that the second derivative changes sign in each case, as you see over here,
and so you actually do have an inflection point at all those candidates.
Here is a plot which confirms that you actually do have three inflection points for this function.
Okay. On to number 11, which is a rather simple problem.
The question is given the position of a particle, you want to find where the velocity is at maximum.
Now if the velocity has to be maximum, then the acceleration has to be 0 at that time,
so we set the acceleration to be 0, and you find that that happens when t = –2/3.
Now you work out the acceleration at two points over there, and you find that
the acceleration goes from being positive to negative at this point,
so you actually have a maximum over there.
Okay. That’s the picture you have where you are seeing the velocity being maximal.
Okay. On number 12, you have to compute the value of x
for which the function has a minimum at x = 2.
You’ve got a parameter c, so you want to find the value of that c.
You set the derivative to 0, and you find that x should either be –√c or √c,
but if you want a critical point at 2, then that √c better be 2, so c must be 4.
Here’s a plot that confirms that you actually have the correct behavior in this case;
namely, you do have a local minimum at x = 2.
Okay. On to number 13, where you’re given a table of values.
Now let’s say this function given to you over here is differentiable. The question is
what is the minimum number of times that the derivative becomes 0?
Well, if you look over here, then the derivative first decreases from 1 to 3.
It also decreases from 5 to 10, and it increases between 3 and 5.
The derivative must be 0 at least twice on this interval.
Here’s a plot which confirms that
you actually have two points at which the derivative is 0.
Okay. On to the last question, which is about computing the places on this curve
where you have a horizontal tangent.
Now of course you have an implicit function, so you must differentiate implicitly in this case.
You do that, work out derivatives.
Now if that is to be 0, then the numerator must be 0, so you must have x(10 + 3x) = 0
so either x is 0. Now if x is 0, then y too is 0 from the equation,
but then the derivative is not defined over there because you’re dividing by 0,
so that can’t happen. On the other hand, when x = –(10/3),
which  comes from this factor over here, then you can actually work out the value of y,
and you get two values, so in fact, you’ve got two points on the curve
at which the tangent is horizontal.
Here’s a picture of the curve showing you the two points at which
you have these horizontal tangents.
That brings me to the end of today’s problem session.
I’ll stop over here and see you next time.
Thank you.