Hello, and welcome to Lesson 19 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is asmyptotes. Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In the past, we have learned how to calculate the limits of functions at points.
For example, if I said find the limit of 3x as x→2, then the answer of course is just 6.
But you can also take limits at positive or negative infinity. For example, if you said
a limit of 3x as x→∞, the answer is ∞. At –∞, just the opposite happens; you get back –∞.
Now the nice thing is that although you might have infinite limits, the actual answer might be finite.
In this case, you have the limit of 1/x as x→∞ going to 0. There are various kinds of
of interesting behaviors taking place at infinity, and these are so-called end behaviors of functions.
That’s the theme for this lesson, which will be used to sketch graphs eventually.
Let’s begin with some more motivation and talk about horizontal asymptotes.
If you look at this table over here, it’s a table for 1/x as x→∞, and you see that as x becomes larger,
the value of 1/x becomes smaller. As x approaches ∞, 1/x gets closer and closer to 0,
and hence 0 is a horizontal asymptote of 1/x. You can actually check that in a plot.
You see over here you have the graph of 1/x, and that’s the horizontal asymptote.
It’s just a horizontal line to which the plot approaches as x→∞.
Now a more formal definition. The limit of f[x] is L as x→∞ if the value if the values of f[x]
approach L as x becomes sufficiently large. When you add –∞, the same statement holds,
except that you’re now taking x to be sufficiently large and negative. Then a line y = L
is a horizontal asymptote of the curve y = f[x] if the limit of f[x] at ∞ or –∞ is L.
Here’s a plot for the function (x^2 + 1)/(x^2 – 1). When x approaches ∞ or –∞, the values of y
will approach 1. Roughly speaking, when x is very large, you get (x^2)/(x^2), which is 1.
Okay. Now let’s talk about the opposite behavior where you do not have a finite answer at ∞,
you have infinite limits at ∞. Here’s a very simple example which we saw earlier on as well.
When you take the limit of 3x as it approaches ∞, the answer is ∞.
Just the opposite happens at –∞, so the plot over here has no horizontal asymptotes.
Okay. Now one might talk about the laws of limits at ∞ just as before. You remember that
we have talked about mathematical laws that limits obey, and most of these laws
also apply to limits at ∞, but you must be a bit careful. The reason why you must be careful is that
now more than ever, you could have things which are both ∞, and when you try to cancel them,
you do not get back 0. Here’s an example. You have x^3 – x, and as x→∞, you get ∞ – ∞.
But that’s not 0, so you get back a False over here. But if you think of it as being ∞ * ∞,
then the answer really is ∞. Better still, you could think of this as being x^3
as very large compared to x, so the answer is ∞.
Okay. A very important law which you can use for limits at infinity is the following.
You look at the limit of (1/x)^r where r is some positive rational number,
and if you assume that r is positive, then this limit is always 0. Just the same thing happens at –∞.
You get back a 0 over there as well. For example, if you want the limit of 1/x^2
as x approaches either plus or minus infinity, the answer is just 0. This law is the basis of
lot of problem solving which we’ll see in the next few minutes. As my first example,
let’s take a rational function. If you want the limit at ∞, then notice that the highest power
in the numerator and denominator is x^2. You divide by that and use a function called Apart,
which will break apart the expressions. You see over here that as x approaches ∞,
by the previous law, both those terms give you 0, and both those terms give you 0 as well,
so the limit of the numerator is just 2—that’s the 2 from here—and the denominator,
the limit is just going to be 3. That’s the 3 from over there. To summarize, the limit of this
rather difficult-looking function is just 2/3 as x→∞.
Okay. That’s the rational case, and now let’s take a case where you have the combination of
a radical and a rational. Okay. Now that’s your function f[x], and notice that the highest power
is x because you’ve got a square root of x^2 roughly, so if you divide by that, then you see that
the numerator will have a limit of √5 as x→∞ and the denominator will have a limit of 2 as x→∞,
so those are the answers separately. Then if you divide them, you get the limit
for the entire radical rational expression.
Finally, let’s take a pure radical. Here is a radical function. The problem is that as x→∞,
you roughly speaking get ∞ – ∞, and you cannot define that. What we do is we work with
the conjugate radical and multiply f by it. You see over here that if we simplify it,
the answer is just 4. In other words, the function is simply 4/(x + √(x^2 + 4)).
When x becomes very large, the denominator is much larger than the numerator, so the answer is 0
for the limit. You can confirm that with a plot. You see the limit approaches 0 as x→∞.
Okay. How about compositions? Remember that if you have a composition of f and g
and you want to find the limit as x→a, then what you could do is take the limit inside the function f,
so to speak, provided that f is continuous and the limit exists. Here’s an example.
You have a function Cos[1/x]. That’s the composition. If you look at the inner limit as x→∞,
then you get back 0. Then if you take the outer limit, you’ll get back a 1 because the cosine of 0 is 1.
Here is a plot of the function, and you see that as x becomes very large, the function value approaches ∞.
Okay. Now in the last two slides, I’ll talk about two shortcuts for computing
rational function limits at infinity. There are some special tricks which are
well worth knowing in this area. For example, if we have a rational function
and the degree of the numerator is less than the degree of the denominator like over here,
then then whether you are at ∞ or –∞, the answer is going to be 0 because the denominator grows
much more rapidly than the numerator. On the other hand, if the degrees agree
so the degree of the numerator equals the degree of the denominator, then all that you do is
you look at the leading coefficients and you get back the answer 2/7 in both the cases over here.
We’ve covered the case of when the degree is less for the numerator than the denominator
and when they are both equal, but the really difficult case is when they are both
slightly different in the sense that the degree of the numerator is greater than
the degree of the denominator. Now four things can happen. First of all, you have
a positive expression at ∞, so you have x^6 roughly at ∞ and x^2 over here.
Then as you approach ∞, then both of these become ∞ because the difference
between the two degrees is even. If, on the other hand, you have a negative expression at infinity,
–2/3 roughly over here and –2/3 roughly over there, then the answer for both the limits will be –∞.
Now on the other hand, if you have an odd difference for the degrees
and the function is positive for larger values, then you see that the degree will affect the answer
in the sense that we have ∞ at ∞ and –∞ at –∞. After all, roughly speaking, there is x^9 over x^6.
That’s x^3, so as x becomes large, you get ∞, and as x becomes very large and negative, you get –∞.
Finally, if the function is negative for large values of x, then you see that
you get the opposite behavior. After all, when x is large, the negative sign becomes important.
You get –∞ over here and ∞ over here. There are four combinations: both ∞; both –∞;
and one of them ∞, one of them –∞; and then the other way around.
So that’s the end of this lesson. The main point to note is that roughly the same laws hold
for limits at infinity as they do at individual points, but you have to be a bit more careful.
There is a special rule which we saw earlier on for rational functional limits at infinity.
Sometimes you may need to use a bit of algebra to tackle cases where there are radicals,
and then multiplying by conjugates might help. In general, it’s really as easy to work at infinity
as it is with finite points. With what you’ve learned, the next lesson will talk about sketching curves.
But before you do that, do review this lesson and look at the exercises and be ready for
the next lesson on sketching curves. I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.