Hello, and welcome to Lesson 3 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is the elementary functions. Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson.
In the previous lesson, Lesson 2, we learned how our functions can be used to represent change,
and we learned how to define a function, plot it, evaluate it, et cetera, but then we also learned that
there are many different kinds of functions. It’s quite puzzling, the number of functions you might see
at any one time. Here are a few graphs over here. Let’s say that’s a kind of oscillating function,
and you might have an increasing function or a decreasing function, and the question is
what do you really need to study calculus in this course? Well, in this lesson what we’ll do is
we’ll categorize the types of functions that you’ll really encounter later in the course.
These functions are somewhat simpler than what you might encounter in advanced mathematics,
and hence they are called elementary functions, as opposed to what are called special functions.
Our topic of today is elementary functions, which we will study in some detail.
Perhaps the simplest kind of function is a linear function. For example, here is a function
f[x] = x + 3, and if you plot it, what you see is you get a straight line. That’s a linear function,
and in general, the function f[x] = mx + b is called a linear function, and that m over there is the slope
and the b is the y-intercept. Linear functions are rather simple. Their graphs are straight lines,
they have a slope and a y-intercept, and that’s about all.
Okay. To go a step further, let’s talk about power functions. A power function is also very simple.
It has a form x to the power a. Here are some power functions of a simple power
like 1 and 2 and 3 and 4. Let’s plot them, and what you notice is that the graphs depend upon
the kind of power you have. If you have an odd degree or an odd power function,
then the graphs are odd. For example, the graph for x is odd, whereas the plot for x^2 will be even.
These power functions are simple in the sense that the odd degree functions are odd
and the even degree functions are even. Now slightly harder than those are the root functions,
where you have things like x^(1/2), like the square root function basically. That’s just a simple way
That’s just a simple way of saying x^(1/3) in the Wolfram Language. Those functions are
are a little more complicated than the earlier set because now what happens is if you look at the plots,
they look a bit thicker over here than over there. That’s because the odd roots are defined everywhere
while the even ones are only defined for positive—or non-negative, really—values of the variable.
Here’s the square root function, and the square root of a number is only defined
if the number is non-negative. That’s the class of power functions which are quite useful in practice.
To go a step further, let’s talk about polynomials. That over there, the function f, is a polynomial.
Now if you plot the polynomial, you get a graph. It’s a nice smooth graph, and generally speaking
if you want to find a polynomial, you need to set up a sum of this type. The a’s over here
are coefficients, while the powers are right over there—n, n − 1, et cetera.
The highest power is called the degree of the polynomial. This polynomial over here
has coefficients 3, −1, 7 and 6, while the degree is 4 because you have x^4 over there.
In particular, linear functions have degree 1, quadratic functions have degree 2
and cubic functions have degree 3. You have this vast array of polynomials.
They are very simple to work with, but they are incredibly useful. You have linear, quadratic,
cubic polynomials, et cetera, which we encounter all the time in the course.
Okay. To go a step further, we can talk about rational functions. A rational function is
simply a quotient of two polynomials, the ratio of two polynomials.
If you divide a polynomial by another, you get a rational function. Perhaps the simplest kind
of rational function is the reciprocal function, which is 1/x. If you plot it,
you see the plot has got two pieces, and that’s because there is a problem at x = 0
where the function is not defined. You have a piece on the right and a piece on the left,
and together they give you the reciprocal function. In general, rational functions
are defined everywhere, except where the denominator is zero. Whenever the function q over here is zero,
you will find that there are problems and the rational function is not defined. But apart from that,
they are rather simple to work with, and again, they are incredibly useful in calculus.
Okay. Let’s go a step further and talk about algebraic functions. An algebraic function
is obtained by adding, subtracting, multiplying, dividing or taking roots,
and that of course is where all the trouble lies because when you take roots, you can have
you can have all kinds of things going wrong. Here’s a pretty complicated algebraic function.
It’s got square roots, cube roots, et cetera, in it, and if you plot it, there could be issues.
There is an issue over here at zero because of the denominator, and then the function may
not be defined on certain parts, so the domain is rather small typically,
and these algebraic functions come in a variety of shapes. Although they are interesting,
they are somewhat less easy to work with, and we will probably not use them a lot at the start.
Okay. Beyond algebraic functions, we then have the trigonometric functions, which of course
many of you might be familiar with. The sine, cosine, and tangent functions are
the trigonometric functions. Now, just a word of warning. In the Wolfram Language,
we always use the radian measure. If I say Sin[30], that’s not so good; you have to say Sin[π/6]
or Sin[30 Degree] when you really want the sine of 30 degrees. Then of course you get
Then of course you get the correct behavior. The 1/2’s over there came out because you used
the right notation and the right units. Keep in mind that you must always use the radian measure
when working in the Wolfram Language, or else you must say Degree like I have done over here.
Here are the first three plots for trig functions: sine, cosine and tangent.
Okay. You can see that they are all oscillating, both sine and cosine. Then the tangent function
has got these similarities because that’s where you have a problem: when you divide by zero,
the cosine function is zero, et cetera. Okay. Those are the sine, cosine and tangent functions,
and sine and cosine have a period of 2π, while the tangent has a period of π only.
They are repetitious and they have periods, but those periods depend upon the kind of function
you are working with. Of course you could have a Sin[2x], Sin[3x], et cetera,
to get faster and faster oscillations.
Okay. Now if you take a reciprocal of the trigonometric functions, then you get
cosecant, secant and cotangent, which are the reciprocal trigonometric functions.
Here are their graphs. What you see over here is that reciprocal graphs are right over there, and
the problem is that they are not defined wherever the corresponding trig function is 0.
For example, if sine happens to be zero at a point, then cosecant is not defined, et cetera,
so there are gaps in these functions which reflect the zeros of the underlying trigonometric function.
But they are also somewhat similar to trig functions in the sense that secant and cosecant have
got a period of 2π while cotangent has got a period of π.
These functions are quite useful in some parts of calculus.
Okay. Going a step further, we can now talk about the exponential functions,
which are of the form a raised to the power x, so now the exponent is variable.
For example, if we look at 2^x—that’s a case when the base a is greater than 1—
then you have an exponential growth function. Here’s a plot, and you can see quite clearly
that it is growing quite fast. On the other hand, if you take number between 0 and 1 like 0.5,
then you get a decreasing function. But in any case, these functions always pass through
the point (0, 1) because a^0 = 1, as you all know from your study of indices in algebra.
Exponential functions are really useful for capturing growth on one hand and decay on the other.
Things like our population might grow exponentially, and certain other things
might decay exponentially, but together, the exponential functions of different types give you
a powerful way of expressing rates of growth or decay in calculus.
They are incredibly important and you should know them well.
Finally, we’ll talk about the logarithmic functions, which are defined as log[x] to base a,
and they are the inverses of the exponential functions. Here is a graph of Log[x].
Keep in mind that in the Wolfram Language, the base is set to e,
but if you want a different base, then you would say that over here and you would get back Log[x],
but now to the base 1/4. They are very similar in some sense to the exponential functions
because they are in fact the inverses. The logarithmic functions are quite useful, but as you can see,
they grow much slower than the exponentials and they have their own uses.
Okay. We’ve talked about a fairly wide variety of elementary functions,
and to summarize today’s lesson, we have many different forms of functions
and many different kinds of graphs studied today. You can have linear functions,
polynomial functions, rational functions, trig functions, et cetera, and together they already required
for studying calculus in this course, for the most part.
Okay. We are basically done with today’s lesson. In the next lesson we will cover limits,
so you really start doing calculus in this course next time. But before doing that,
do look at today’s lesson in the notebook that’s supplied to you, look at the accompanying exercises,
go over them. You can only learn mathematics by doing, so spend some time reviewing,
solve the exercises, et cetera, and you should be in good shape to join me next time for Lesson 4.
Thank you very much. I hope you enjoyed today’s lesson. I’ll see you next time.