Hello, and welcome to Lesson 6 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is continuity. Let’s begin with a brief overview of the idea for today’s lesson.
Begin by recalling if you have a polynomial like this one over here, then its limit at a point
is simply the value of the polynomial at that point. If you look at the polynomial f[x],
then I simply replace x by a, and I get the limit of f[x] as x approaches a.
That’s a very special property of polynomials and similar functions—namely, that their limit
at any point is just the value of those functions at that point, and such functions are called continuous.
A continuous function is one for which the limit at a point and the function value agree.
This lesson will give examples of continuous functions, functions that are not continuous,
so-called discontinuous functions, and we’ll also give a nice application of continuity.
Let’s begin with the definition of continuous functions in a formal way.
A function is continuous at a point a if the value at a is equal to the limit of f at a.
For a function to be continuous, three things must happen. First of all, it must be defined at that point.
The limit must exist at that point, and that’s not enough; the limit must be equal to
the value of the function at that point. The equality is a very important condition for continuity.
Very informally, a continuous function should have no gaps or breaks in its graph.
If you draw the graph of a function and it looks continuous—it has no gaps or breaks—
then in fact that’s very likely to be a continuous function. For example,
here is a function of x as a polynomial, and its value at 1 is the same as the limit.
You plot it, and sure enough, there is no break in the graph, so that is a continuous function.
That’s just a simple way to tell if a function is continuous or not.
Okay. Some simple examples. Polynomials and rational functions are continuous
wherever they are defined. Here’s a polynomial f[x] and a rational function g[x].
f is of course continuous at every point, but g is continuous everywhere except at −1,
where the denominator is 0, so it’s not defined. Here’s a plot of f[x], nice and continuous,
and a plot of g[x], which has a problem, a discontinuity at −1.
Okay. Next let’s talk about functions which are not continuous. A function that is not continuous
is said to be discontinuous at that point. Here are two examples, f[x] and g[x].
Now if you think about f[x], there’s a problem at 1. If you find the value at 1, sure enough,
the answer is indeterminate. That function has a discontinuity at x = 1.
Now what’s happened with g is that we’ve chained the value at 1 hoping to fix the problem,
but that’s still not good enough because the limit as you approach 1 is −3, while the value is −2.
If you plot the functions, you see that f has a problem at 1, which you can’t really see over here,
but that’s the fact from the definition, whereas g
did not quite fix it because you chose the wrong value at that discontinuity.
Of course you’ve got to fix it, but the whole point is to construct examples
where things can go wrong for continuity.
Okay. A second class of examples here is a piecewise function f[x],
and clearly that’s problematic at 0 because you’re dividing by 0.
That’s the floor function g[x], so f clearly has a discontinuity at 0.
You can see that. You’ve got ∞ over here and 0 over there, whereas g is a bit more complicated.
It’s got discontinuities at all integers. For example, at 0 it’s indeterminate,
the limit, and the value at 0 itself is 0, so clearly there’s a problem at that point. Here are the functions.
f only has a problem at 0, while g seems to have many more problems in its graph.
Okay. Although the floor function is discontinuous, it does have one nice property,
namely that if you approach it from the right, then things are okay, but they are not from the left.
Let’s see that for the floor function. If you try and find the limit from the right,
from above for the floor function at 0, then it’s okay. You get back True.
But if you try and find it from the left, it is not okay. The plot clearly says that we have issues at
all the integers, but in fact you have a function, the floor function,
which is continuous from the right at every integer, but not from the left.
Okay. Root functions are also very similar to polynomials because they’re continuous
everywhere in their domains. Wherever they are defined, you are okay.
Here’s a square root function f[x], and that’s continuous wherever it is defined,
namely, when x is non-negative. But at −1, it’s got an imaginary value i,
so one cannot really talk about continuity at that point. Here’s a graph,
and as long as the function is defined, there is no problem at all; it is continuous.
Okay. Trigonometric functions are pretty simple. The sine function and the cosine function
are both continuous at 0, and in fact, they are continuous at every point. Here’s a graph of
each of these functions. They are clearly continuous—there are no breaks—and one way to prove that
might be to use the addition formulae from algebra, from trigonometry, which can be used
to show that these functions are actually continuous at every point. On the other hand,
the tangent function has a problem because the denominator has cosine, so it is not continuous
whenever the cosine is 0. You can see the problems over here at every place where
cosine becomes 0 like π/2, et cetera, there are problems with the tangent function.
Okay. If you want to go further, then one needs the laws of continuity. Just like you have
the laws for limits, you also have the laws for continuity. You have the sum law, which says that
if f and g are continuous, then so is f + g. You have the difference law,
which says that f − g is also continuous if f and g are so; the scalar multiplication law,
which says you can multiply by constants and still get continuity; the product law for products;
and the quotient law for quotients. Together they give you a nice way of showing that
fairly complicated functions are in fact continuous. Here’s a function f.
It looks pretty complicated, but then you can think about it and say oh yes, cosine is continuous,
so is sine; now you are dividing over here, you are adding there, et cetera,
so by the laws of continuity, this function is continuous. If you find the value at π, the answer is
the same as the limit at π. That’s a powerful way of showing that a function is continuous,
namely, to apply the laws of continuity just like one could apply the laws of limits.
Okay. A slightly harder problem is what happens if a function is a composition,
so it’s f[g[x]]. Well, in that case you simply let the limit go, so to speak, inside the bracket,
and if you still get the same answers then you’re okay, and that’s exactly what’s happening over here
in this case. Basically you have f[x] defined as cosine of a polynomial, but cosine is continuous;
so is a polynomial. This function is a composition of trigs and polynomials. If you look at the graphs,
everything looks fine, and in fact the function is continuous. The point is that
given a composition of functions, you can basically ensure they’re continuous
by looking at each piece separately. In this case, you looked at x^2 − 7x + 10,
and we looked at cosine and then we were done.
Okay. We are almost done with today’s lesson, but one last important theme is that
you can actually apply the idea of continuity in practice to find roots.
The theorem that helps to do that is the intermediate value theorem. That means
the theorem for the values between two values. What it says is that
if you have a continuous function f on an interval a to b and you have any number n
between f[a] and f[b], then you will have a value somewhere in the middle.
That f[c] is equal to n. Basically a continuous function will take every value
between any two of its values. Of course one must assume that they are distinct
to get some kind of interesting behavior, but basically you can assume for continuous functions
that they take every value between any two of their values. Let’s try and find the root of
this rather complicated looking polynomial f[x]. It’s a cubic polynomial. Now you want to find
the root between 1 and 2, so what you do is you first of all evaluate at 1 and 2.
You find that it’s negative here, it’s positive there, so because the function is continuous,
and because 0 lies between those two numbers over here, then there must be a root in the interval.
Using the intermediate value theorem, you can now check by the plot of my Solve
that now there is in fact actually a root, and that root in this case is about 1.63334.
People who try and solve equations will often apply this theorem to try and find a root of a function.
That’s a very powerful application of continuity. It’s not just a theoretical concept,
it’s a very powerful practical concept.
Okay. We are done for today’s lesson. Let’s summarize. Basically, continuous functions
are very common in the real world, and in fact, most functions you’ll meet are going to be continuous.
There really is no problem at all. We did see some examples, but they were somewhat artificial
in some cases, and you don’t need to worry about them mostly.
Informally, a continuous function has no gaps or breaks in its graph. If you look at
polynomials’ root functions, they are continuous wherever they are defined.
That’s no issue for polynomials, but for root functions like the square root, you do need
to worry about where they are defined. Now rational functions and trigs are slightly harder.
They may or may not be continuous. That depends upon the kind of way that they are being set up.
Finally, the intermediate value theorem is a very powerful way to find the roots of functions.
That’s the end of the discussion of continuity for today, and in the next lesson,
we’ll begin discussing differential calculus by using limits to define so-called derivatives.
That’s where calculus really becomes useful in a very profound way. Next lesson is a time
we start looking deeper into calculus, but before doing that, do review today’s lesson,
try and solve the exercises and be ready for the next time. It was great to present this to you.
Thank you very much.