Hello, and welcome to Lesson 10 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is derivatives of trigonometric functions.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson. Recall that the trigonometric functions
are oscillatory—so they go up and down like waves. You would expect that their derivatives
would oscillatory too. Here’s an example that illustrates that.
Here’s a function f which is composed of sine and cosine, and if you plot the function along with
the derivative, then what you see is they are both oscillatory. The blue graph is f
and the orange graph is f', and as f changes in an oscillatory way, so does f'.
But of course I haven’t told you how to find the derivative of f, and that’s the goal of today’s lesson.
The goal of this lesson is to develop a table of derivatives for trigonometric functions.
Let’s begin with the sine function. Here’s the sine function, and to find the derivative,
we simply apply the definition—namely, it’s the limit of the difference quotient as h approaches 0—
and you get back Cos[x].That says that the derivative of sine is cosine.
Let’s confirm that with D. Here’s a plot of both the functions sine and cosine.
Sine is the function and cosine is the derivative of the function.
Let’s go on now to the cosine function. Once again, we apply the definition, and what you get back
this time is the negative of the sine. That’s important: the derivative of cosine
is the negative of the sine function. Let’s confirm that with D.
You get back −Sin[x]. Here is a plot of both the functions Cos[x] and its derivative −Sin[x].
Let’s go on further to the tangent function. Here’s f = Tan[x]. Work out the derivative with the definition
and you get back Sec^2[x]—so that’s to be remembered, that the derivative of Tan[x] is Sec^2[x].
Let’s confirm that with D, and the question is why is there is a square in the answer?
Well, when you plot f and the derivative, you see that the tangent function is always increasing,
so the derivative, as the slope of tangent is always non-negative—and that’s why the derivative
has got a square in it. So Sec^2 lies above the x axis.
Okay. Now we go on to the reciprocals. The secant function has derivative
Sec[x] * Tan[x], and here’s a confirmation with D. Let’s plot them both, and there you are.
Next we go on to the cosecant function. That’s the reciprocal of sine,
and its derivative is negative of cotangent times cosecant. Confirm that with D,
and once again we can plot it to get the function and its derivative.
Finally we got on to the cotangent function. Now its derivative turns out to be −Csc^2[x].
You can confirm that with D, and the question is why is there a negative sign?
Well, the point is that unlike the tangent, the cotangent is always decreasing,
and so its derivative is always negative.
Okay. Let’s summarize a bit. Here you have the six functions that we just spoke about—
sine, cosine, tangent, secant, cosecant, cotanget—and here are their derivatives.
That says that the derivative of sine is cosine, et cetera, and that small table is well worth memorizing
for all your future work. Let’s plot them, and you see that you have all the functions
and their derivatives in just one picture, with the top three being sine, cosine, tangent,
and the bottom being secant, cosecant and cotangent.
Okay. Just a little bit about the higher derivatives of the trigonometric functions.
We know that the trigonometric functions have a cyclical nature. You would expect that
there’s some kind of interesting pattern in their derivatives, and indeed that’s what happens.
Here is a table of the first four derivatives of sine. You’ve got Sin[x]. Its derivative is Cos[x].
Its derivative is −Sin[x], then −Cos[x] and then Sin[x]. You see that you’re back to Sin[x]
after a cycle of four derivatives, and that says that, for example, if I ask you
what is the 1,001st derivative of the sine function, you will say, oh yes, if we divide by 4
we just get 1 as the remainder, so the answer is Cos[x]. In fact, there is a very nice formula for
the nth derivative of the sine function. It’s just Sin[x] + n * y/2, and you can check that
that gives you the correct answers when you plug in the values of n as 1, 2, 3, 4, et cetera.
Finally here is a plot of all the derivatives of Sin[x], and you see quite clearly that
you start off at sine, then you go to cosine, then you go to negative sine,
then you go to negative cosine, then you come back to sine.
That is the end of today’s lesson, but let’s summarize. Because the trig functions are periodic,
then so are their derivatives. The derivative of sine is cosine.
The derivative of cosine is negative sine. The derivative of tangent is secant squared.
The derivative of secant is secant times tangent.
The derivative of cosecant is negative cosecant times cotangent.
The derivative of cotangent is negative cosecant squared. That short list should be enough
for most applications. Now this is a very short lesson, but it’s a very useful lesson
and it’s a very important lesson because the trig functions appear in all kinds of applications,
starting from the motions of particles around circles to the electric currents
that flow through wires, et cetera. Knowing the derivatives for these functions is a great step
in your knowledge of calculus. In the next lesson, we’ll talk about the so-called chain rule,
which deals with compositions of functions. But before then, do revise this lesson and make sure
you understand the trig function derivatives. I’ll stop over here.
Thank you very much. I hope you enjoyed the lesson.