Hello everyone, and welcome to Introduction to Calculus with Wolfram U.
My name is Devendra Kapadia, and I work here at Wolfram Research
as a kernel developer for calculus functions. But I also enjoy teaching mathematics,
and it’s a great pleasure to have this opportunity to talk about calculus with you.
Now today is the first lesson, so I thought we would spend some time talking about what is calculus
and trying to understand what this beautiful subject is all about. I’ll begin by defining calculus,
and then we’ll talk a little bit about the main problems of calculus, some history,
and then I’ll tell you why you might want to study the course, and what the course is all about.
Let’s begin by answering the question what is calculus?
Well, very simply, calculus is the science of change. Now, change is all around us.
For instance, the second hand on this clock changes its position every second, but you could have
more complicated motion. For example, the planets in the solar system change their position
at every instant as they revolve around the sun. Now in the first case,
for the motion of the second hand around a clock, you could use simple arithmetic algebra
to analyze a problem, but in more difficult cases like the solar system motion,
you would need better tools to analyze the motion, and one such tool is calculus.
Calculus is an essential tool for deeply understanding change in a mathematical way, and hence,
it is a tool of choice for many scientific problems. The next question is
what are the main problems that drove the development of calculus?
Well, the four main problems of calculus are first, the problem of finding the tangent line
to a curve at a point. Now if the curve is sufficiently simple like a circle,
you can of course draw the tangent line to the curve at that point, but in more complicated cases,
you would need something like calculus to solve the problem.
Number two is the problem of finding the area under a curve.
Now once again, if, let’s say, you have a circle, then finding the area is not very difficult.
But for more complicated curves, you would need better tools. Now from the point of view
of physics, you might sometimes need to find, let’s say, the velocity the a particle
given either its position or acceleration, and once again,
you can use calculus to solve this problem.
And finally, from time to time, you are going to want to either maximize or minimize some quantity,
and the common word for that is optimizing. For example, a businessman might want
to maximize his profits or minimize his loss, and once again, calculus is the tool
which helps us to study the process of optimization.
Okay. Let’s look at each of these in a bit more detail. Let’s start with tangent to a curve.
Let’s begin with the tangent to a curve. Now to find a tangent line at a point, what we do is
we draw the secant lines from nearby points. Let’s say we want to find a tangent at this point over here.
We start with a point, in this case far away, and let the secant line change
by moving the point along the curve. Let’s run this animation over here.
What you’ll see is that as the point moves to the required point,
the secant becomes closer and closer to the tangent. Okay. To summarize,
as a secant gets closer to the desired point, you’re going to get the tangent line.
Now onto the second problem for calculus, and that’s the problem of finding the area
or length of a curve. Here is an animation in which we can talk about the area
of a regular polygon when the number of sides goes from 3 to 50. Let’s begin with the case of n = 3,
where you have a triangle, and then as you increase the number of sides, you see what happens
the perimeter and the area. Let’s run animation. You see that as the number of sides increases,
the polygon approaches the circumscribed circle. Of course in this case, you know that when you have
an infinite number of sides, then you get the area of the full circle, which is just π if the radius is 1.
Okay. On to the third problem for calculus, and that is what is called the velocity problem.
Here we have a particle that is moving along around a knotted curve. At each stage, you have the velocity
and the acceleration, so you have the tangent and the normal, as we call it,
and the problem might be to compute the velocity and acceleration at any time in a very accurate way.
Once again, you can use calculus for this.
Finally, on to the problem of optimization. Let’s say a farmer has 500 feet of fencing available,
and the farmer wants to fence off a rectangle with the maximum area. The question is
what should the dimensions of the rectangle be? Let’s look at this interactive model over here.
You see that as you change the dimensions, you get more and more area. It increases up to certain point,
and then it starts to shrink again. It would look like the best way to optimize over here would be
to choose a rectangle which is, in fact, a square of 125 feet by 125 feet, but the question is
how would you have arrived at the solution without trial and error?
Calculus gives you a systematic way of solving such problems.
Now of course the ancient Greeks knew quite a lot about solving such problems,
but it was only in the 17th century that mathematicians started to look a little deeper into
how one could solve each of these four problems. The French lawyer and mathematician Pierre de Fermat
developed a method for drawing tangents and finding maxima and minima.
The clergymen John Wallis found ways, for example, to find the value of π/2 and do it quite accurately.
Johannes Kepler, the great astronomer, used the method of the Greeks to find
to find the volume of wine barrels, and in fact in doing so, he touched upon the questions of
finding volumes and finding maxima and minima, so he really is one of the pioneers of calculus.
Of course at that point, geometry was still the method of choice for many problems,
so Isaac Barrow in England showed how to calculate the tangent to a curve
using purely geometrical means. So Fermat, Wallis, Kepler and Barrow were the early pioneers
of calculus, along with many others. Now you might read in books or elsewhere that
Newton and Leibniz discovered calculus. The question is
in what sense are they regarded as pioneers and discovers of calculus in the true sense?
The point is that although the early mathematicians knew about calculus one way or the other,
it was only Newton and Leibniz who gave general methods for doing calculus.
In fact, they put together all the earlier knowledge and found relations between
the various concepts of calculus. One question was who discovered calculus first?
Was it Newton or Leibniz? Well, Leibniz published his paper first,
but then Newton had already shared his ideas on calculus with others. In England people said
oh, Newton discovered calculus, while elsewhere in Europe, the support was all for Leibniz.
Well, today it doesn’t matter a lot, and we regard Newton and Leibniz as the joint creators of calculus,
for it was they who gave a unified way of looking at concepts in this subject to us,
and today we talk of the Newton and Leibniz approach to calculus. Now beyond Newton–Leibniz,
people went on making improvements to calculus.
The Bernoulli brothers were very active in this area. In fact, Johann Bernoulli wrote the first
the first differential calculus textbook informally; it was L’Hospital who actually published it.
Maria Agnesi—lady mathematician—she was the eldest of 21 children, and still found time
to do calculus and write a book that covered both differential and integral calculus.
But the modern foundations of calculus, what made it really nice and precise,
were given by Cauchy and Weierstrass, and it was they who finally told us
how to approach calculus in a very rigorous and complete manner.
Now although all these pioneers did a lot of work, things did not stop over there.
Even today, we have calculus being used in many, many areas. For example, quantum mechanics,
which is the study of matter at the atomic level, uses the Schrӧdinger equation,
which is a product of calculus. If you go to financial markets, then the Black–Scholes equation is used
to find the prices of options. The Black–Scholes equation, in fact, uses what are called
partial differential equations. When Albert Einstein wanted to discover the laws of gravitation,
he had to turn to calculus, something called Ricci calculus, and his friend Marcel Grossmann
taught him the details, but Albert Einstein developed the so-called general theory of relativity
based on calculus. If you study economics and you want to study markets, you need calculus.
If you want to study medicine, you need calculus to figure out dosing strategies.
Of course even if you go to NASA, you would find that they use calculus all the time
to figure out how to design and how to propel their rockets. The point is calculus continues to be
a key tool in many different areas. But you might ask okay, that’s fine;
it’s really useful to some people, but why is it useful to me?
Why should I study calculus? Well, I already gave the first reason. The first reason is that
it has very broad applications in the real world. The other point is a more practical one—
that if you are studying any kind of STEM degree in science or technology, then they would ask you
to first master calculus before doing anything else. It’s a prerequisite which you must go through
if you want to become a technical kind of person. Now on the other hand, you can say that
I’m not going to go into any of these STEM fields; I just am going to pursue my own interests.
Well, that’s fine, but for anyone to master calculus represents a major academic milestone
for that person, and to me, that is the main reason for studying calculus.
It is a major academic milestone. If at any point in your career you can say I know calculus,
that is a great feeling, and I hope you get it after going through this course.
Okay. A little bit about the course itself. This course will have 40 lessons—it’s a 40-part course,
and roughly speaking, the course is based on the AP Calculus AB in this country, the US.
The AP Calculus course is a pretty challenging high-school level course, and I thought that
it would be good to get more people into studying calculus early and preparing themselves
for applying it in their own careers. Now we’ll begin with standard topics like functions and limits,
and having done that, we will move onto differential calculus and finally we will move on to integral calculus.
Don’t worry if you don't follow these terms; they’ll get familiar to you a little later on.
Of course the only way to learn calculus and mathematics is by doing, so there will be lots of
problem sessions and quizzes to help you understand calculus in a deeper and practical way.
But the main point is that we will focus on understanding, and there will be almost no
formal proofs for any theorems, so the advantage of that is that we can focus on visualization,
on calculations, and really get familiar with all the things which are possible
possible with Mathematica and the Wolfram Language. I do hope you’ll take advantage of this course
to really understand fundamentals of calculus, how to compute things,
how to draw beautiful plots, et cetera, using the tools that are available to us today
and were not even a few decades ago.
Okay. Who is this course for? You might wonder is this course really for me?
Am I old enough for it? Am I the right person? Well, it doesn’t matter who you are;
you will enjoy this course. You might be a beginner trying to learn calculus;
you’re welcome to the course. You might be a middle schooler, for example, who is ambitious
and wants to learn calculus at a very early stage. That’s fine; you can learn it. This course is
a good place to begin. Or you might be a doctor or engineer who has learned calculus for sure earlier on,
but just wants to refresh their memory and learn this wonderful subject again.
That’s fine; you’re welcome to. You’ll benefit something from this course.
Now that’s specialized people, but really anyone who wants to understand the Wolfram Language
and how it applies to calculus is going to find this course extremely beneficial. To me,
this course is designed to be for everyone, not any specialty group, and we’ll try and go slow
and explain things very, very carefully at every stage. It’s a good point for me to mention that
this course arose in an internship project with John Clark. John Clark was with me last summer,
and in fact, he was a student at some point at the California Institute of Technology.
John is a remarkable person. He learned calculus when he was in the 7th grade. He is a genius,
and he did a great job producing the basic material for the course. But my point is that if John,
at his age having just finished college, could write the course, you can surely follow
what I’m saying over here. Do not give up. Keep persevering. The rewards will be immense.
I strongly urge you to follow the course all the way through all 40 lessons,
and you will have mastered calculus by the time we are done.
Okay. Let’s summarize what we have learned today. As a piece of mathematics,
calculus shows us what we are capable of if we really put our minds to it.
Whether Newton or Leibniz or Fermat or Maria Agnesi, these individuals took time off from
their daily duties to do what interests them most, which is mathematics and calculus,
and that’s why we have this wonderful subject today. Even today, if you want to do
if you want to do any kind of science in the broadest sense, whether it’s physical science
or social science, you will find calculus is a very useful apparatus which has in fact
changed our whole view of the world. Now if you are a student, you will more or less
certainly at some stage have to do a little bit of calculus, and you should feel proud
to have mastered it yourself—beginning with this course, perhaps. That’s the introduction to calculus
which I have given you today, and in the next lesson, we will begin formally.
It’s all going to be a little more serious and straightforward in some ways because
we will talk about functions and then slowly progress into the other areas of calculus.
With that summary, I will conclude today’s lesson. It’s been a pleasure to discuss
this introduction with you. I hope you have enjoyed a bit from it. Thank you very much.