Hello, and welcome to Lesson 26 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is indefinite integrals.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In the last lesson we talked about
the fundamental theorem of calculus,
which connects differential calculus and integral calculus.
For example, if I said find the integral of this function, 4x^3,
from 2 to 3, then the answer is simply 3^4  – 2^4—
that’s 65—
and that’s because an antiderivative of 4x^3 is x^4.
Let’s just check that with D.
If we try the same thing with Integrate
but now we tell it to find the integral of the function from 2 to 3,
you get back just the same answer.
What we’ve learned is that the antiderivative is, in fact,
a very nice way to do integration.
Hence, we give it a special name.
We call it the indefinite integral.
The goal of this lesson is to review the indefinite integrals
or antiderivatives that you’ve learned so far.
Before going on, just a few notes.
First of all, to repeat myself,
the antiderivative will now be referred to as the indefinite integral,
and sometimes people just say integral.
If you take Integrate and you find Integrate[f[x], x],
then the answer is x^4 for our example
because it’s really computing an indefinite integral
when you do not give it any range.
Notice one thing: that the answer from Integrate does not include
the constant of integration
which you would learn in a course on calculus,
so you must put this in yourself.
So please be careful when you work with indefinite integration.
You will need to put that constant in by hand.
Now if you want to compute a definite integral,
then you must actually put in the lower limit and the upper limit,
and then you get back the same answer you did earlier on,
which is 65.
Here is a plot showing the function and its integral.
Once again, please note that we’ll set the constant
for the integral to be 0, essentially.
Let’s begin now with some examples.
If you take a constant function, then the integral of this function
is just kx where k is the constant.
Again, mentally you must just put in the constant of integration,
so you get kx + C.
For example, if the function is 3, then the integral is 3x.
Here is a picture of the function and its integral.
Notice that I am putting the evaluate over here inside the plot,
and that’s because I’d like Integrate to do its work
before Plot does the plotting.
Okay. On to a linear function.
Suppose you have kx + b.
Then its integral is kx^2/2 + bx + C.
That plus C, again, is coming from the constant in integration.
For example, if you have 5x + 4,  then the answer is (5x^2/2) + 4x.
Here’s a plot of both the function and its integral.
Okay. On to power functions.
If you have x^a, then its integral is x^(a + 1)/(a + 1).
That’s the answer with the constant of integration.
For example, if I give you x^3, then the answer is x^4/4,
which you see in the plot over here.
Okay. On to trigonometric functions now.
If you look at the sine function and the cosine function,
then the integral of sine is negative cosine
because the derivative of negative cosine is sine.
The integral of cosine is sine.
So we have two important indefinite integrals
for sine and for cosine.
Here’s a plot of the functions and integrals.
Okay. On to slightly harder examples.
If I give you secant times tangent
or negative cosecant times cotangent,
then in the first case, the integral is Sec[x]
because the derivative of Sec[x] is Sec[x]Tan[x],
and similarly for the second example.
We’ve now found two more trig integrals.
Here’s a plot of all the functions involved over here.
As my final example, let’s take even harder trig functions.
If I give you Sec[x]^2 and –Csc[x]^2,
then the first integral is Tan[x]
because the derivative of Tan[x] is Sec[x]^2,
and similarly, the derivative of Cot[x] is –Csc[x]^2.
Again, here’s a plot of all the functions and their integrals.
Okay. That’s all that there is for today’s lesson.
It’s a short lesson where we’ve talked about
the antiderivative of a function and given it a special name,
namely, the indefinite integral.
What we have learned is that you can find
the indefinite integrals of many functions—the constant function,
the linear function, the power function
and several trigonometric functions.
Now in most cases you can simply call the Integrate function
and it will find the indefinite integral for you,
but make sure you put the constant of integration.
That’s really the core of indefinite integration.
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about the substitution rule,
which actually makes things easier when you have
more difficult examples
and perhaps more interesting examples to talk about.
I’ll stop over here.
Do review this very important lesson.
It’s not very difficult, but it’s important
and basically everything that follows,
and then the next time, we’ll talk about the substitution rule.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.