Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 7 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this session is integrals and the fundamental theorem.
Let’s begin with problem 1 for the session,
which says compute the integral of 5x^3 from –2 up to 3.
Now the indefinite integral of 5x^3 is 5x^4/4 from the power rule,
and so you can use the fundamental theorem of calculus
to simply plug in the upper and lower limits.
That’s the value from the upper and lower limits,
and you get the answer 325/4.
Let’s check that with Integrate, and we do get the same result.
Here is a plot of the region that we just integrated.
On to problem number 2, which says here is a function
and that’s the graph of the function.
The question is compute the integral of this function
from –5 all the way up to 3.
Now the integral over here is the net area,
so it’s the sum of the positives, and then you’ve got to subtract
the negative areas where required.
There are four shapes over here.
There’s a triangle on the left, and that’s got a base and height
of 1 as you can see, so its area is 1/2.
You have a semicircle over here.
Its radius is 2, so its area is 2π.
There’s a quarter circle over there with radius 1,
so its area is π/4.
Then there’s a trapezoid whose heights are 1 and 2
and the base is 2, so the area is 3.
When you do an algebraic sum, so you subtract off the negative area.
Then the answer is 7/2 – 7π/4.
Let’s compare that with Integrate,
and we do get back just the same answer.
Number 3 says here is the velocity of a particle,
and the question is find the displacement of this particle
in the time interval 1 to 4.
We first of all work out the displacement
as the integral of the velocity.
That’s t^4/2 – 7t^3/3 + 3Sin[t] + C.
For example, this term over here gives you 3Sin[t].
Then you plug in the upper and the lower limits
and work out the answer, which is right at the end of the line.
Let’s check that the answer is correct through Integrate,
and here is a plot of the velocity function on that time interval.
Okay. On to number 4, which says compute the integral of √16 – x^2
from –4 to 4, but this is just the area of a semicircle
That’s the semicircle over here.
You have –4 to 4.
Of course if you work out the area, it’s just πr^2/2.
That’s 8π in this case.
Let’s check the answer with Integrate,
and you will get back the same result.
Number 5 says compute the integral of –Csc[x]Cot[t]
on the interval given over here.
Now we first of all work out the indefinite integral,
which is just Csc[x] + C, of course.
Plug in the upper and lower limits.
Get an answer.
Check that the answer is correct with Integrate.
Here is a plot of the region for which we have integrated.
Number 6.
You’re given the marginal profit for a product,
so that’s the change in profit for a unit value of x,
and you want to find the change in profit
when the sales increase from 64 all the way up to 81.
That’s just an integral like the one shown over here.
You first work out the indefinite integral,
which is 50x – 3√x^(3/2), et cetera, and then you get the answer,
and the answer turns out to be 416.
Let’s check that with Integrate, and here is a plot
of the marginal profit and the region being integrated.
Okay. The next one says compute the integral given over here.
There’s an absolute value, so first of all,
let’s plot the function.
You see that the function has got three triangles.
There’s one here, one there.
They are both going to have positive areas,
and then there’s one negative area over here.
The first area is just 1.
The second one is 2—that’s this one.
The third one is 9, but you need to subtract the second area,
and so the net area is just 8.
Let’s check the answer with Integrate,
and you do get back 8, so the answer correct.
Problem number 8 says compute the integral of Sin[x]^4Cos[x].
Now in this case, we do a little substitution.
We set u to be Sin[x], so du is Cos[x]dx.
That’s this part over here, so the answer is simply Sin[x]^5/5 + C.
Let’s check the answer through Integrate.
Remember that the C is set to 0 by Integrate.
There’s no C over here.
Here is a plot of the function and the indefinite integral.
On to number 9, which says compute the integral given over here.
Obviously we need to put x^2 – 4 as u.
When you do that, then the du, the differential for u, is 2xdx,
so with a small adjustment, you get 3xdx = 3du/2.
You work out the indefinite integral over here.
Now the point is you can either
work in the u picture or in the x picture.
If you use the u limits, then when x is 3, then u is 5.
When x is 7, u is 45 because 49 – 4 is 45.
You plug in those limits and you get 130√5.
Let’s check the answer in the u coordinates.
You could also work with the original x answer,
and you get back just the same result.
Here is a plot of the region integrated.
Okay. On to number 10, which says compute f'[5]
where f is given by this integral over here, this integral function.
If you apply the fundamental theorem,
then f' will simply be the expression inside the integral
with the t replaced with x.
Let’s check that.
Then you plug in the value of 5 and you get back 376.
Here’s a plot of the integral function
and its derivative on the given interval.
Okay. On to number 11,
which says you have a balloon which is losing air at a certain rate.
That rate is given over here.
You want to find the total change in air from t = 4 to t = 10.
That’s an integral over here.
We need to plot just to get an idea of what’s happening,
and then you set u to be 35t + 10.
That’s the denominator over here.
So du = 35dt.
Make a small adjustment,
and you work out the integral in the u picture.
Then you work out the change in air,
and that turns out to be 1/360.
Let’s check that with Integrate, and you get back the same result.
That’s a simple substitution
to get the total change in air for this balloon.
On to number 12,
which says compute the derivative of this integral.
Since you have a 4x^2 on top, you need to apply the chain rule.
The chain rule says that the answer is the integrand
with t replaced by x times 8x, which is the derivative of 4x^2.
Let’s check that with Integrate, and you get back the same result.
Then what you do is you plot the function over here,
and that’s a beautiful plot of that answer.
Okay. Number 13, which says compute the integral over here.
Now in this case, we set u to be 4 + x, so du is dx.
Now the x over here becomes u – 4.
We have (u – 4)√u.
You expand that, and you get u^3/2 – 4√u.
Integrate further and then replace u with 4 + x,
and so you get back an answer.
Now Integrate gives a slightly different answer,
so let’s check that our answer is the same as the one from Integrate.
That’s the Integrate answer.
That’s our answer.
Let’s check that they are the same by using Simplify,
and you get back True, so everything seems fine over here.
Let’s plot the function with Integrate over here,
and you get back this nice plot.
On to number 14, the final problem for today.
The question is you’re given the graph of a function,
which is our semicircle over here and a straight line,
and the question is to compute the linear approximation
of the integral of this function from 0 to x near 5.
Now when they say near 5, what they mean is
to compute the linear approximation at the point 5.
Remember you have a straight line approximation,
in this case, to compute.
You know that x0 is 5.
Work out the value of y0 from the integral,
and if you do that from the integral, you see that you’ve got
this area over here and a triangle area over there,
so the total area is (2π + 9)/4.
Now what remains is to compute the slope,
but the slope is just the derivative of the integral function at 5,
which is just the value of f at 5.
If you plug in the value of f at 5, which is right over here,
then you get back 3/2 or 1.5.
Okay.
That is the linear approximation, and if you plot it,
you see the linear approximation is really good near 5,
but not so good far away from it.
Linear approximations are very good approximations,
but they’re only good near the point at which you compute them.
That brings me to the end of this problem session.
I hope you learned all the nice ideas
in this topic of integrals and the fundamental theorem.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.