Hello, and welcome to Lesson 7 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
Our topic for today is derivatives and rates of change.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson. At the start, we said that
calculus is the science of change. The primary goal of calculus is to study change.
Now there is one way to study change, and that’s to use functions. Functions tell us
how one quantity changes with respect to other quantities. For example, here’s a function
which relates x to f[x] or y, and that’s the plot of the function. That tells you
how y changes with respect to x, but of course we need more than that often.
We need to know how the function changes with point to point. We need the rate of change,
so to speak. If you have a straight line, that’s simple; you simply find the slope.
Here’s a straight line, the slope is 3, and that’s a very nice measure of
the rate of change of that function. In this lesson, we’ll show you how to do that
for more general functions. In other words, we’ll try and generalize the idea of slope
using what are known as derivatives. That’s the theme for today, derivatives and rates of change.
Let’s begin with the notion of a derivative. The derivative is a special kind of limit, and that limit,
roughly speaking, is linked to the tangent to a curve. I haven’t told exactly how,
but we’ll see that later. For example, if you have a straight line, the simplest kind of curve,
then the slope of the straight line is rise over run. That’s difference in y over difference in x,
and in the f notation, that’s f(x) − f(a) over x − a. The question is,
is that good enough for a general function f, and the answer is no. This only gives you
the slope of the secant line for an arbitrary function f. Let’s see that.
Here’s a function f[x] = 1/x, a very simple function, and let’s take two points on it, (1/2, 2) and (3, 1/3),
and work out the slope of the secant line between those two points. That’s −2/3.
Now if you draw the graph of the function and that secant line, you see it’s not quite what we need.
It’s just a little too far off to be useful. What’s missing over here is that the two points
need to be really close by, and so really what we need is the notion of limits that we studied earlier on.
To find the tangent line to a curve at a point, you really need to take the limit of secant lines.
To be more precise, you need to find the difference in f between x and a
over the difference in x itself, and then take the limit as x approaches the given point a.
This is what will give you the slope of the tangent line that goes through the required point (a, f[a]).
Here’s an example to show you that you have a secant line over here, and then as you let
the points come closer and closer, you will then get the tangent line.
It’s only in the limit that you actually get the tangent line starting from a secant line.
Okay. As an example of a tangent line, let’s take the curve of f[x] = x^3, and here’s a slope of
the secant line through the point (1, 1) and the limit, and that’s the slope of the tangent.
If the slope is 3, then the equation is y − y1 equal to slope times (x − x1), and if you plot that,
you surely do get the tangent line to the curve x^3 at this point (1, 1). Just to summarize,
given a point on a curve, what you do first is you work out the limit of this quotient over here.
You get the slope. That slope can be used to find the equation of the line, and that line
is then the tangent line. It’s slope times (x − x1) + y1 in this plot over here.
Okay. In practice, of course, we use something called the difference quotient to find derivatives.
Here’s the difference quotient, but it says you want the limit as this number h approaches 0
of the difference between f at a nearby point and at the given point over h.
It’s still a slope, but it’s a slope in a slightly different form. As an example, suppose f[x] = 1/x.
Work out the slope over here, and you get −1. Now once you’ve got the slope, what you can do is
you can plug in and find the equation of the tangent line, and here you are.
That is the correct tangent line at the point.
Okay. Now a couple of places where you might find this notion. First of all, the idea of velocity.
The instantaneous velocity of a position function is given by the slope of a tangent line
to the positional curve. If a particle is changing position and you want to find
the speed or the velocity at a particular time, then all you do is you work out the tangent line
to the curve at that point. For example, suppose that the position is this very simple function s[t] = 5t.
You work out the velocity by doing the difference quotient calculation we did earlier on,
and then you find out that in fact the position is, in this case, a linear function
while the velocity is constant, which of course we could have guessed from earlier work
in your class on physics or other subjects. This is the notion of velocity as the derivative of position.
Okay. A slightly harder problem. Suppose a ball is dropped from a building 100 m above the ground,
and you want to find the velocity of the ball after two seconds, let’s say,
and you want to find out how fast it’s going when the ball hits the ground.
There are two problems over here. You want to find what the velocity is after two seconds
and you want to find out how fast it is going, the ball is going, when it hits the ground.
Now, you can work out the equation of motion as 100, the initial height, minus 4.9t^2—
that comes from the acceleration of gravity—and then what you can do is you can work out
the speed at time t = 2 by using the difference quotient calculation. Now the question is
why is it negative? It’s negative because the ball is going down. If you plot the position
and the tangent equation we saw just now, that’s the velocity over here. Okay. The question now is
what happens when the ball hits the ground? When the ball hits the ground, the displacement is 0.
You solve that equation, which just says that the displacement is 0 when the time is about 4.517.
Now you can plug into the derivative the speed, and you get back −44.2719.
That’s the way to find out what happens to the ball when it hits the ground, what the speed is.
Okay. Now the question is what is the slope of the tangent line at a point?
Well, it is the derivative at that point. When people say derivative at a point, what they really mean is
the slope of the tangent line and vice versa. Now we have a shorthand for it.
We use the notation f'[x] over there. If you say f[x] = x^3, then in the Wolfram Language,
f'[1] is the derivative at x = 1. The derivative of x^3 at (1, 1) is 3.
You can plot that and check that it in fact is the correct answer.
A couple of more concepts over here. First of all, we have a notion of a tangent line
to a more general curve like over here. You’ve got the tangent line to a parabola,
and you want to work out a tangent equation for that parabola. What you do is
you set up an equation, which is y equal to slope, the derivative, times x − x1 plus y1,
and you work it out. Then you get actually the required plot of the parabola
with the tangent line at x = 2.
Now sometimes people talk about the average rate of change. Suppose you’ve got a function y[x],
and let’s say x changes from x1 to x2. Naturally y changes from some y1 to y2.
The increment over here means that change in x, and the increment over there means the change in y,
so you’ve got Δx and Δy telling you what the change in x and the change in y are.
Their ratio is what is called the average rate of change of y with respect to x, as you go from x1 to x2.
This average rate of change is exactly the slope of the secant line between the two points.
For example, if you want to find the average rate of change over this interval, you simply find
the difference in the function values divided by the difference in the x values, and you get back
the average rate. Here is a plot of the secant line along with the original curve.
As the secant line goes closer to the point, then of course we get the instantaneous rate of change.
The instantaneous rate of change is the change that you get when Δx, the change in x, goes to 0.
That is exactly the slope of the tangent line at that point. In our case,
if we take the limit in the calculation, then you get back the tangent line at the point.
The instantaneous rate of change is exactly the derivative of y at x.
Finally, an example involving tables. Here is the table showing the US national debt in billions
between 1980 and 2015, measured at 5 year increments. Here’s a plot.
It’s clearly going up. The question is can you estimate the instantaneous rate of change at the year 2010?
As a first step, what you do is you make a piecewise function from it, because that lets you
you build the function starting from the data. You want to find the derivative,
so you set up the quotient like we did earlier on. You want to find 2010,
so that’s where that comes from. Then you can kind of interpolate—in other words,
in other words, find an average of the values between 2005 and 2015, and that, roughly speaking,
is the instantaneous rate of change at 2010. Roughly speaking, the rate of increase of debt
is about 1.1 trillion dollars in the year 2010.
Okay. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson, and the point is that the derivative of a function
is simply the slope of the function at that point. You can think of this derivative as being
the limit of the slopes of secant lines. You start a secant line, then you take the limit,
then you get the derivative of the tangent line. Now the derivative idea is very useful
in lots of places, like we saw for speed and that kind of thing in physics, and also for calculating,
let’s say, debt in economics. Often the only data you have is a table of values, in which case
you can approximate the derivative. The idea is that starting with a table of values,
you can find the approximate value, but of course you cannot calculate
the exact value of the derivative. That’s the idea for today, the idea of a derivative
and the notion of rate of change. In the next lesson, we’ll talk about the derivative itself
as being a function just like function that you start with. I’ll stop over here.
Do go over today’s lesson, try the exercises and you should be in good shape for the next lesson,
which is lesson number 8. Thank you.