Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 6 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic of this session is optimization, antiderivatives and Riemann sums.
Let’s begin with problem number 1 for the session.
A rectangle has its base on the x axis and the upper two corners lie on a parabola.
The question is compute the largest possible area of that rectangle.
Here’s a picture. Here’s the parabola and the rectangle,
and if you think of this portion as being x, then the rectangle has base 2x,
and the height is 6 – x^2—after all, you are on a parabola.
The area function is 2x(6 – x^2).
What you do is you compute the critical numbers
by setting the derivative equal to 0,
and you find that x is either √2 or –√2.
You work out the area at those two points.
That’s obviously the maximum area, 8√2,
and this occurs when the base is 2√2 and the height is 4.
All that’s clear from the information over here.
Okay. Number 2.
The question is to compute the closest point
on the curve x^2 – y^2 = 3 to the point (1, 2).
Obviously we need to use the distance formula like over here
and you’re computing to the point (1, 2), but the main point is that
you can actually minimize the square and get just the same answer.
Here’s the square distance, and we plug in y as being √(x^2 – 3)
because y follows the equation over here,
and you work out the distance function in terms of x.
Compute the critical numbers by setting the derivative equal to 0,
and you get back two answers.
You can check that. The second one is
the one that’s going to give you the nearest point.
Work out the corresponding y values, and then this value of y,
which is positive and paired with 2.16574, is clearly the point
at which you will have the minimum distance.
The closest point is roughly (2.16, 1.30), and here is a picture
showing the points on the curve and the given point.
Okay. Problem number 3.
The question is a window consists of an open rectangle topped by a semicircle,
and it has a perimeter of 100 cm.
The question is compute the radius of that semicircle
so that you get the maximum area.
Now if the radius is r, then the perimeter of the semicircle is πr.
On the other hand, the base of the rectangular part will obviously be
2r because it shares that side with the diameter of the circle.
The area function is given by the area of the semicircle
plus the area of the rectangular portion,
so that’s the base of the rectangle and that’s the height of the rectangle.
Okay. Now we find the critical numbers, and you find there’s just one.
You check that in fact you have a negative second derivative,
so you have a local maximum, and in fact there’s just one of them,
so you have an absolute maximum at radius equal to 100/(4 + π).
Here’s a plot which shows the same information.
That is the radius at which the area becomes maximum, and that’s the area.
Okay. On to number 4, which says that you have an open-top box
with a square bottom and rectangular sides,
and the volume has to be 456 cm^3.
The question is to compute the dimensions of the box
that will minimize the surface area.
If you let the side length be s and the height be h,
then you have just one area for the bottom, s^2, and 4 of them for the sides—
after all, the box is open-top.
You still need to eliminate one of the variables, so you use the fact that
the volume is equal to s^2h, and you solve for h.
You get get h in terms of s, and you replace that expression
to get a single function s for the surface area.
Okay. Now compute the critical numbers.
You find that it’s roughly 9.7.
Work out the second derivative,
and you do have a local minimum at that critical number.
Once you’ve worked out the value of s,
then you work out the value of the height using the volume,
and you find that the height is about 4.85.
The dimensions are 9.7 times 9.7 times 4.85.
Okay. On to number 5, which talks about a swimmer
who is at a point 400 meters
from the closest point on a straight shoreline.
This swimmer needs to reach a shop
which is located 200 meters downshore from the closest point.
The shop is here. Now the point is that he swims at 5 m/sec
and walks at 6 m/sec.
The question is how far from the shop should he come ashore
so as to arrive at the shop in the least amount of time?
Now obviously the Pythagorean theorem says that the third side over here
is √(x^2 + 160,000) where x is the distance at which he lands on the shore.
The time function is equal to the first distance over here
divided by the corresponding speed
plus the second distance divided by the corresponding speed,
so that’s the time function for the problem.
We compute the critical numbers, and we find there’s just one.
Work out the second derivative, and you find out it’s positive,
so in fact you have a local and absolute minimum at that critical number.
Now you subtract off that value, and you find that
the swimmer should come ashore roughly 597 m from the shop.
Okay. Number 6. Now we go into antiderivatives.
The question is find the general antiderivative of 4x^3 – 2x^2 + 7x + 1.
The answer is x^4 from there, from 4x^3, and then 2x^3/3 from the second term,
7x^2/2 from the third term, x from the fourth term
and plus C for the constant in the antiderivative.
Let’s check that. That’s correct.
If you plot the antiderivative, then of course there is a family of them,
so there are lots of curves over here, each of which is an antiderivative,
and that’s the original function given to you.
Okay. Number 7.
The question is solve the differential equation y' = Sin[x]
given that y[0] = 3.
Now the antiderivative of Sin[x] is –Cos[x].
After all, if you compute the derivative, you get back Sin[x],
and the plus C is just the arbitrary constant.
Use the fact that the value of y at 0 is 3
to find the value of C. C is 4.
The solution is y = –Cos[x] + 4.
You can check the answer with DSolveValue.
Here is the equation.
That’s the initial value given to you, that’s the unknown function
and that’s the independent variable.
DSolve says that the answer is just the same
as the one that we obtained earlier on by hand,
and here is a plot of the solution.
It’s vertically shifted by 4 due to the 4 term over there.
Okay. Number 8 talks about the velocity of a particle given in terms of t,
and the question is to compute the position of the particle
at t = 10 given that the position at t = 1 is 5.
As a first step, you work out the antiderivative.
This term over here gives you –1/t,
and the second term gives you –8t^(3/2)/3,
and of course the plus C comes from the arbitrary constant.
Let’s check that.
Looks correct.
Solve for C given the fact that when t is 1, the position is 5.
You find that C is 26/3.
That’s the expression over here of the position function,
so its value at 10 is given right over here as an exact number.
Now let’s plot both the position and velocity function over here.
On to number 9.
You have a differential equation for y'' that’s given to be 4Cos[x],
and you’re given the values of y at 0 and y' at 0.
For the first step, we find the antiderivative,
and we find the answer is 4Sin[x] + C.
Next find another antiderivative of 4Sin[x] + C,
and you get –4Cos[x] + Cx + D.
Check the answer.
That looks correct.
Now having found the general antiderivative, you want to work out
what the values of C and D are,
so you use the fact that y[0] = –1 and y'[0] = 1,
so that’s the equation over here.
You know that y'[0] is 1 and y[0] is –1,
so you find that C is 1 and D is 3.
You plug them back and you get –4Cos[x] + x + 3.
Confirm the answer with DSolveValue, and here is a plot.
In this case, because you have the term x over here,
the graph gets translated upwards as you progress along the x axis.
Number 10.
Once again you’re given y'' and you’re given y at 0
and, in this case, y at 2.
The question is to solve this differential equation.
Find the first antiderivative.
You get back x^4/2 – x^2/2 + C from each term.
Check the answer.
Find another antiderivative, and this time you get x^5/10 – x^3/6 + Cx + D.
Check that answer as well,
and then you use the conditions given to you over here.
y[0] is 3—that’s the 3—
and y[2] is 7—that’s the 7 at x = 2.
Work out C and D.
The solution for the problem is right over here.
You can check that the answer is correct with DSolveValue.
I did use an Expand over here to make sure it looks just the same,
but it is the exact same expression.
You have 3 + (16x/15) – (x^3/6) + (x^5/10).
Number 11, and now we are onto left-aligned rectangles.
We are talking about Riemann sums.
You want to estimate the area under this function from 4 to 7.
Because you have left-aligned rectangles,
so you have an xi – 1 over here—
and of course, each rectangle has width 3/4
because the total length is 3  and you are using 4 rectangles.
You can compute the Riemann sum over here.
Put in a numerical value.
Here is a plot of the curve and the approximate area.
Those white areas over here are
the areas which get left uncovered by the Riemann sum.
On to number 12, which says compute the value of b
with b lying between 0 and π,
which will make the area under Cos[x] from 0 to b equal to 1.
That’s the Riemann sum.
Compute the limit as n→∞,
because that’s the actual area, and then you want to find out
when Sin[b] is equal to 1 between 0 and π,
and of course the answer is just π/2.
Here is a plot of the region which we just spoke about.
Number 13 says use six right-aligned triangles to estimate the area
from 2 to 14 for this function over here.
Now because you have 6 rectangles, the width of each rectangle is 2,
so you work out the Riemann sum.
You go in steps of 2 starting from 2, and the 2 over here is
the width of each rectangle.
Compute the Riemann sum,
and then here is a plot of the region and the rectangles.
Number 14, which talks about a racecar which speeds up
in the first 10 seconds of a race.
You have the first 10 seconds over here,
the speed in miles per hour over there, and the question is
to find the lower and upper estimates
for the distance traveled by the racecar in the first 10 seconds.
To find the lower estimate, what you do is
you start at the beginning of each 1-second interval in the computation.
You have 0, 2.3, et cetera, and you times that by 1 second.
The answer is 0.184.
Then you do the same thing for the upper estimate,
but this time you take the right endpoints—2.3, 9.3, et cetera—
and you get back 0.249.
So the racecar traveled between 0.1845 and 0.249
in the first 10 seconds of the race.
That’s roughly between 972 feet and 1,320 feet.
That brings me to the end of this problem session.
I hope you have had a better understanding of the topic
with these problems.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.