Hello, and welcome to Lesson 32 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is approximate integration.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
So far, you’ve been using integration to calculate
the area under curves, et cetera, and the point is
if you can compute an integral, then you can work out the area.
For example, if you can work out the integral of x^2,
which is of course x^3/3, then you can work out
the area under the curve for y = x^2 between,
let’s say, 2 and 5 in two ways:
either you can actually plug in the upper and lower limits 5 and 2
in the answer on the earlier step or you can use Integrate,
and you get back just the same result.
The point is that some functions have no known closed form
for their integrals.
Here’s an example: e^e^x^2 does not have an integral.
The question is what do we do in such a case?
How do you find the area under the curve in such cases?
In this lesson, we’ll go over some ways
to evaluate such integrals numerically or approximately.
As a first step, let’s look at so-called left and right approximations.
When we began integration, we talked about the area of a region
as being a kind of Riemann sum, so you have the function value
at some sample points times the length of each subinterval,
and then the sample points could be chosen in various ways.
In the first case over here, if I choose i – 1 over here,
then basically I get the left-end sample points,
so the rectangles have their upper left-hand corners
lying on the curve.
If you have an i over here,
then you get upper-right corners lying on the curve.
Here’s a plot to show all that.
In this first case, you have the left approximations,
and in the second case, you have the right approximations.
It’s clear in the first case you’re kind of under approximating,
and in the second case you’re over approximating.
Let’s now actually work out the answers using the sum over here,
and you get back the answers 1.285 and 1.385.
That’s the left sum.
That’s the right sum.
The actual answer is sandwiched between those two numbers.
It’s 1.3333, which is somewhere between
the left and the right answers.
The question is can we do any better?
Well, what we could do is to take
the midpoints of each subinterval as the sample point.
Here’s the midpoint in each case.
Then the rectangles have the middle of their tops
going through the curve.
Here’s a plot with our function,
and you can see over here that things are better
because you have some extra area over here, for example,
and some less area over there, so it looks like this might give you
a better approximation than the earlier method.
Let’s do that, and you do find that you get a better approximation.
Another method might be to use the so-called trapezoidal rule.
Earlier we spoke about the left and right approximations,
and that’s the actual integral.
If you work them out, you can get back 1.285, 1.385, 1.3333.
But what you could do is to take an average of the right and left
and compare it with the actual integral,
and that definitely looks much better.
Effectively what you’re doing is you’re taking a trapezoid
in each case with the height of the trapezoid equal to Δx
and the two lengths over here being
the lengths of the function heights at those points.
Here’s the answer for that trapezoidal rule,
and you get back just the same result.
Now to go a step further, one could actually try and use polynomials,
and that’s what is called Simpson’s rule.
With Simpson’s rule, what we’ll do is use parabolas
to approximate the area under the curve.
But that’s a much harder problem,
so you get back a slightly more complicated formula.
You do need to take an even number of points,
and then basically you take x0, x1, x2 et cetera in triples
to compute the sum for the area.
That’s a particular combination.
You have 1, 4, 1 as the combination on your subinterval.
Here’s the computation with our earlier example
and, let’s say, 10 subregions.
What you get back is the exact answer.
Simpson’s rule is extremely powerful.
It tries to use parabolae to compute the approximation,
and in this simple case, it actually gets to the exact answer.
Now whenever we do any kind of approximation,
you need to worry about errors.
For the midpoint rule, it turns out that if you have
an upper-bound K for the second derivative,
then that’s the error for the length of b – a for the interval
and n rectangles.
The trapezoidal rule has a very similar formula,
but in fact the error is exactly twice the midpoint rule error.
Simpson’s rule is a lot better
because now you look at the fourth derivative,
and you get back an error term over here.
Those are the maximum errors
for each method that we have spoken about.
The midpoint case and the trapezoidal case,
you can work out the errors—they’re quite small—
and compare them with the actual errors,
namely, the difference between the actual integrals
and the midpoint method and the trapezoidal method,
and you get back just the same result.
The question now is
why did Simpson’s rule give you no error?
The point is that you have a quadratic polynomial,
so its fourth derivative is 0,
and so there is no error in the Simpson’s method.
Okay. Fortunately in the Wolfram Language,
we have a wonderful function called NIntegrate
which actually computes numerical integrals very nicely.
For the example in our introduction, e^e^x^2,
you get back a nice answer quite quickly.
Here is a plot of that area.
In general, NIntegrate uses very highly optimized methods.
It does not use any particular method, but it might use
some very general, efficient algorithm to compute the answer.
You do get back the best possible answer,
and I strongly recommend you check your answers with NIntegrate.
But of course you might say oh, I really want to have
my own function done my way to compute integrals.
Well, you can do that.
You can make your own functions.
We’ll learn that in a later lesson.
For numerical integration, you can either make up your own functions
or simply call NIntegrate.
They are both fine, but you must decide
how accurate you want your answer to be.
Okay. Finally, one might sometimes only have a table of values.
Here’s an example.
You’re given a table of values for the speed of a particle
at 11 instances of time.
Those are the times and the speeds,
and you’ve got the trapezoidal rule.
Basically what happens over here is you have the left endpoint
and the right endpoint of the intervals,
and then you have everything else getting counted twice.
For Simpson’s rule, you have the left endpoint, the right endpoint
and then everything else getting counted four times.
That’s the Simpson’s rule answer.
They are pretty close.
Here’s a plot of the data.
Basically you can compute a numerical approximation
given only a table of values.
After all, all of today’s formulas depend only upon
knowing the values at a certain fixed number of points.
That brings me to the end of this lesson,
and the main point is that if you can’t find
the integral of a function,
then you certainly can approximate it by various methods.
There are various techniques available.
You could use left or right approximations.
You could use the midpoint rule,
the trapezoidal rule or Simpson’s rule.
You could also use NIntegrate, which is a very powerful function
and will give you the best possible approximation
that it came up with while finding the integral.
Finally, you can use a table of values
to compute a numerical approximation.
That’s good enough.
In the next lesson, we’ll go over exponential functions.
But before doing that, do review today’s topic.
It’s a very interesting, useful part of calculus
because very often in practice, you cannot find an exact answer.
In that case, a numerical method is the best that you have.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.