Hello, and welcome to Lesson 33 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is exponential functions.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
In the past, we have talked about polynomials
and other kinds of functions.
For example, over here the function f is a polynomial function,
the function g is a rational function,
the function h is an algebraic function
and the function p is a trigonometric function.
Here are the plots of these functions.
In this lesson, we’ll go a step forward
and talk about so-called exponential functions.
Let’s begin with a definition.
An exponential function is a function with the form a^x
where a is a non-negative value.
Of course what that means depends upon what that x is.
If x is a positive integer, then all you do is
you multiply the number a by itself x times.
Here’s 3^4, and that’s just 81.
But if x is a negative integer, then you take a reciprocal.
In this case, you have 3^–4, giving you 1/81.
Finally if x is 0, then a^0 is just 1.
Of course, we can go beyond that.
If x is a fraction like p/q, then you can either take
a pth power and then a qth root or the other way around,
and in the Wolfram Language, we have the Surd function
which does that nicely for you.
The main point is that these exponential functions grow very fast.
In fact, they grow faster than any polynomial function.
Here are some plots of these functions.
If a is greater than 1 like 3^x,
then you have a very rapidly growing function.
But if a is between 0 and 1,
then the function is a decreasing function.
Of course if a is 1, then you only have a constant function.
So increasing, decreasing, constant.
The next point is there are several laws of exponents.
If you have a^(x + y), then that’s the same as a^x * a^y.
If you have a difference like a^(x – y),
then you simply divide to get (a^x)/(a^y).
If you have (a^x)^y, then you simply multiply the exponents
and you get a^(x * y) like over here.
Finally if you have (a * b)^x,
that’s the same as a^x * b^x like over here.
Okay. Now let’s talk a little bit about some deeper properties.
First of all, the exponential function is always continuous,
which means that there are no breaks in its graph.
The domain of the function is all real numbers,
and the range is from 0 to ∞.
But of course what happens to the function
when you approach infinity depends upon the value of a.
If a is greater than 1, then as you approach ∞,
you get an infinite value.
As you approach –∞, you get 0.
Just the opposite happens if you have a number a between 0 and 1.
Now when you approach ∞, you get a 0;
when you approach –∞, you get ∞.
Okay. On to the derivatives of these functions.
The point is that the derivative of a^x
is not x * a^(x – 1) as you might think,
but in fact it is a^x * Log[a].
Here’s the derivative from D.
Now the question is in which case does this logarithm term become 1?
That happens when the number a has got a special value called e,
and this e is named in honor of
the great Swiss mathematician Leonhard Euler.
If you solve Log[x] = 1 with the Solve function,
you get back that x is actually e.
In the Wolfram Language, we use E for the number
and use Exp to represent the exponential function
whose derivative is e^x.
The point is that this is the one function whose derivative is itself.
You just get back e^x when you try and differentiate it.
Of course if you’ve got something more complicated like over here,
then you can use the chain rule and get back the answer.
How about integrals?
Well, the integral of e^x is, again, e^x, plus of course the C.
But if you have a more general exponential function a^x,
then you get back a^x/Log[a].
Okay. Let’s go a step deeper into the number e.
There are many ways to define e.
The simplest one is of course to just say that
e is a number for which the Log[x] = 1,
but you can also define it using limits.
This limit over here becomes 1 when x is e.
So does the other limit over here, which really is the sequence limit.
n is a natural number, so when n becomes very large,
then ((1 + 1)/n)^n becomes e.
Also, the area under the curve 1/x from 1 to a
becomes 1 when a is the number e.
Finally, you should know that
the approximate value of e is about 2.71828.
That’s a very important approximation
well worth memorizing.
The number e is really, really important
in mathematics, science and engineering,
and you will come across it all the time
when you try and apply mathematics to practical situations.
As examples of where it occurs,
we can talk about exponential growth or decay.
Now, for example, you’ve got bacteria,
and initially there are 10 bacteria,
and then they double every hour.
That’s the law of growth.
That’s the initial number.
That’s the growth rate.
Here’s a plot showing that we actually have
exponential growth in this case.
But on the other hand, if you have a radioactive material,
then you begin with some quantity like over here, and the quantity,
let’s say, halves every time  period,
then you have radioactive decay.
There’s growth and there’s decay, and both of them can be modeled
very nicely using exponential functions.
To summarize, an exponential function is
a function is of the type a^x.
If a is greater than 1, it’s increasing.
If a is less than 1, it is decreasing.
Of course there are many laws of exponents
which are useful in practice.
Now in general, the derivative and integral
for an exponential function are constant multiples of the function,
but the special number e has a property that e^x
has got integral and derivative both equal e^x
plus of course the constant C for the integral.
The number e is really useful in many different fields.
For example, you can talk about exponential growth and decay,
and you might want to use the number e
or some other base for the exponential.
In the next lesson we’ll talk about logarithmic functions,
but before that, do revise today’s lesson.
It’s an important lesson.
Exponential functions are got all the time,
and you should know them really well.
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.