Hello, and welcome to Lesson 20 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic of this lesson is curve sketching.
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
Suppose you have a function f like the one shown over here, x^2/(x^2 – 4).
Then you can do several things. For example, you can work out the zeros of the function
simply by solving for f[x] = 0, and you find that they’re 0 at 0.
Or you could work out the vertical asymptotes simply by finding out whether
the denominator x^2 – 4 is 0. Then we get the answer either –2 or 2.
Or you could work out the horizontal asymptotes by using the limit and letting x go to either ∞ or –∞,
and you find that you actually have horizontal aymptotes, only at 1.
Okay. Now with all that information, you can plot by hand or, like I’ve done over here,
just use the Plot function to get back the same plot showing all the information.
For example, there’s a 0 at 0, et cetera. The goal of this lesson is to help you to sketch functions
using derivatives and then perhaps use the Plot function to confirm that all your ideas are correct.
Okay. As a set of guidelines that you’ll require for today’s lesson, let’s make a list of things.
First of all, when you want to sketch a function, you should find the domain of the function.
Where is the function defined? Next find the x and the y intercepts.
Where does it meet the x and y axes? Next, is the function even? Is it odd? Is it periodic?
If it’s any one of these, then of course everything becomes much simpler.
Now does the function have either a vertical or horizontal asymptote,
or perhaps even a slant asymptote? I haven’t told you what a slant asymptote is,
but let’s take that for granted for now. Okay. Next find out the intervals where the function
either increases or decreases, and to do that, you could actually use the first derivative
of the function and then apply the increasing or decreasing test.
Next find the local maxima and minima, for which of course you will first find the critical numbers
and then use either the first derivative test or the second derivative test.
Next you’ll want to check the concavity of the function, and for that you’ll use
the second derivative of the function. Then if the second derivative is positive,
then you have a concave upward graph, and if it’s negative, then you have a concave downward graph.
Finally you might want to find the inflection points, and those are the points at which
either the second derivative is 0 and switches signs, or in some cases
it might not even be easy to calculate. With all that information,
you can then sketch your curve by hand, or as we’ll do over here, use the Plot function.
Okay. Let’s take an example now. Here is a rational function very similar to
the one we took earlier on: 3x^2/(x^2 – 4). Now of course this function is defined everywhere
except at –2 and 2, so the domain is those three pieces over here right up to –2,
then between –2 and 2, and then all the way from 2 to ∞, but not including either –2 or 2.
To find the intercepts, you solve f[x] = 0 and also find the value of f[0], and you find that
those are the x and y intercepts. Next we can check that the function is even simply by
equality testing over here, so f[–x] is the same as f[x]. That’s clear from the function itself.
We have an x^2, so that’s an even function. Next we can work out the vertical asymptotes
at –2 and 2, and you can check that there’s a horizontal asymptote at y = 3.
Having done that, we go on to the problem of finding out the critical points.
Critical points are the points at which f'[x] is 0. You have one critical point, and the function is
not defined at 2 and –2, so in all, you have three critical points. What you do is you test
the derivative on each part of the real line depending upon those. You take one point to the left of –2,
one point between –2 and 0, et cetera, and you find that you actually have
some positive and negative signs.
That says that the function is increasing on (–∞, 2) and (–2, 0) because those derivatives
are positive, and it’s decreasing on the other two parts over there because the first derivative
is negative. Now the question is are there any local maxima or minima?
Well, if you work out the second derivative at 0, then the answer is negative, so you do have
a local maximum at 0. The function has no inflection points, as you can check for solving f''[x] = 0,
and then you can also check that it is concave upward between (–∞, 2) and (2, ∞)
and concave downward between the two values. That’s the information about
inflection points and the concavity. Finally you can put that all together and get a nice plot
of a function which shows all the information that we gathered earlier on.
Okay. A second example. Let’s take a slightly harder function which is trigonometric.
You’ve got Sin[x]/(2 + Cos[x]). Now that’s never problematic because
the denominator never becomes 0, so the domain is all the real numbers. The question is
what are the intercepts? Well, you solve for f equal to 0 and find the value at f[0],
and you get back that in fact, it’s going to be multiples of π for the x intercepts
because that’s where the sine function is 0, and the y intercept is just at 0.
Okay. That conditional expression over here is telling you the condition for there to be an x intercept.
Next the function is certainly odd and periodic because the sine function is odd.
Because it’s periodic, you can afford to look at the interval  [0, 2π],
and that’s quite an equality. The function has no vertical asymptotes
because the denominator is never problematic, and there are horizontal asymptotes
at no points because the limits don’t even exist; they are intervals.
Okay. Now the question is what are the critical points? Well, if you check between 0 and 2π,
you find two critical points, and then if you take sample points, then you find out that
in fact your have an increasing behavior between (0, 2π/3) and (4π/3, 2π)
and decreasing between those two values. That’s the information about the first derivative,
and that’s going to tell you that you have a local maximum at 2π/3 and a local minimum at 4π/3.
You can check that with the second derivative. You have a negative second derivative at
the first point and a positive second derivative at the second point, so you have a local maximum
in the first case and a local minimum in the second case. Finally you can check there are
inflection points at 0, π and 2π by solving for the second derivative equal to 0.
Now the concavity test can be applied, and you see that you actually have
a concave upward behavior on (π, 2π) and a concave downward behavior on (0, π).
Now we can put that all together and get this plot of the function, which shows all the earlier information.
Now I haven’t really spoken about slant asymptotes in the course earlier on,
but let’s define a slant asymptote. A slant asymptote is a line such that the limit of f
approaches mx + b where mx + b is the right-hand side for the line.
Basically the graph of the function approaches that straight line, but that straight line
may not be vertical or horizontal. Okay. Now the question is how do you find the slant asymptotes?
Luckily if you have a rational function, then slant asymptotes can occur only when
the degree of the numerator is one more than the degree of the denominator.
In that case, you can simply use polynomial long division. You can work out the quotient.
For example, over here you have the function (x^2 + 1)/x. Then if you find the quotient,
the answer is just x, so y = x is a slant asymptote. You can check that with the plot,
and you see that you have a slant asymptote at y = x over here.
With that information, we can now take up a slant asymptote problem
and try and draft the function 2x^3/(x^2 + 2). The function is defined everywhere;
no problem at all. The denominator is never zero, so the domain is all the real numbers.
The x and the y intercepts are both at 0. That’s easy to show. It’s certainly an odd function.
It’s an odd function because we have an x^3 over there.
There are no vertical or horizontal asymptotes, but you do have a slant asymptote
that you can work out by division, and you see over here that actually
the function does approach 2x as x→∞, so that is a slant asymptote for this example.
Okay. Now the question is when is the first derivative 0? You put 0 in; you are at 0.
You can check that. If you take sample points at –1 and 1, then you have an increasing function
between (–∞, 0) and (0, ∞). The first derivative test tells you that there are
no local maxima or minima. The second derivative test doesn’t tell you anything
because the second derivative of 0 is 0. It looks like there might be some inflection points,
and sure enough, there are three inflection points over here: at 0, √6 and –√6.
You can check that it’s concave upward on two intervals and concave downward on two others.
You have a positive derivative over here and you have a positive derivative over there
for the second derivative. In that case, you have a concave upward behavior,
and the reverse happens in the other two cases. With all that information,
one can plot this rather complicated function, and that is the plot showing the asymptote y = 2x.
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson. What we’ve learned is that we can use
many of the properties that we’ve learned earlier on to sketch the graph of the function.
For example, the intercepts will determine where the function is 0 or where it crosses the y axis.
Of course to find the asymptotes, you would just use the limit function.
To find local maxima and minima, you would use the first and second derivatives,
and you can also find inflection points and intervals of increase or decrease.
All of that information together will let you get a nice sketch of your function.
In the next lesson we’ll be talking about optimization problems, but before we do that,
do practice curve sketching—it’s an important topic—and be ready for the next lesson.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.