Hello, and welcome to Lesson 18 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is derivatives and the shapes of graphs.
Let’s begin with an overview of the lesson. In the last lesson we spoke about the mean value theorem,
and you might have gotten just a hint as to how powerful this theorem is, but in this lesson,
we’ll actually see that power in action. We’ll actually learn how the derivative of a function
can be used to sketch its graph. That’s a very beautiful application of all the calculus ideas
we’ve learned so far. For example, here’s the function f[x] = x^2. That’s the derivative of the function.
Now the function itself, of course, is just a parabola in terms of its graph, and the derivative is
a straight line graph. The point is that starting from this derivative, you can actually plot
the original function, and that’s the theme of this lesson. The goal of this lesson is
to develop a way for sketching such graphs. Let’s begin by building some intuition.
Let’s again look at the graphs of x^2 and its derivative. We have the function on the right,
the derivative on the left. You see that when x is negative, the derivative is negative,
and that says that the function is decreasing. When x is positive, the derivative is positive,
and that says that the function is increasing. Finally, when x is 0, the derivative is 0,
and that says that the function is horizontal just at that point. With that background,
we can now talk about the increasing and decreasing function test.
But let’s begin with the mean value theorem, which says that f(b) – f(a) = f'(c)(b – a)
for some value c between a and b. If f'(c) happens to be positive for all c, then assuming that (b – a)
is positive—so b is greater than a—then we have f(b) greater than f(a), so the function is
increasing on that interval. Using the mean value theorem, we can show that if the derivative is positive,
then the function is increasing. In just the same way, if the derivative is negative,
then the function is decreasing on that interval. These two facts together are called
the increasing/decreasing test. As an example, here is the plot for x^3 and its derivative.
You see that the function is increasing everywhere, and if you look at f', the derivative,
then it is non-negative at all points. The function is increasing everywhere except at 0,
where it’s horizontal, and that’s what we see from looking at the derivative for the function.
The derivative of a function tells you where the function increases or decreases.
Now as an example, here is a cubic function, and you want to find out where it increases or decreases
without actually plotting the function. For the first step, let’s find where the derivative is 0,
and you find that it’s 0 when x is either –2 or 1. In other words, we now know that
the graph must be horizontal at those two values of x. What we’ll do is
we’ll break the horizontal line up into three parts: the part from –∞ to –2, then from –2 to 1
and then 1 to ∞. Now you pick a typical point on each of these intervals. You pick, let’s say, −3
in the first case, 0 in the second case and 2 in the third case. –3 lies between –∞ and –2, et cetera.
Work out derivatives, and you find that at the first point, the derivative is positive,
and so it is at the third point as well, while the second point is negative.
That says that the function is increasing on the first interval and the third interval,
and it’s decreasing on the second interval. Here’s a plot of the derivative and the function.
You see over here that the orange graph is the function itself. When the function increases,
the derivative is going to be positive. When the function decreases, the derivative dips down
below the x axis, and then as it increases again, the derivative becomes positive. That says that
the derivative gives you pretty good information about the increasing or decreasing nature of the function.
Okay. How about maxima and minima? Let’s talk about maxima and minima, and look again
at the earlier function. You see that it’s got a maximum over here at –2 and a minimum at 1,
and they are both local maxima and minima. What you notice is that when x is –2,
the derivative goes from being positive to being negative. It’s positive initially,
then becomes negative. Just the opposite happens at the minimum where the derivative is
first negative and then positive. Now if you look at, on the other hand, the graph of x^3,
then you see over here that the derivative does not change signs as it goes through 0.
That says that you do not have a local maximum or minimum roughly.
Okay. Now we can talk about the first derivative test, which says that if the first derivative
changes from positive to negative at a point, then that point has a local maximum for the function,
and just the opposite happens at a local minimum where the derivative changes
from being negative to being positive. On the other hand, if the derivative
does not change signs at a point, then the function neither has
a local maximum or minimum at that point. As an example, look at the sine function and its derivative.
It’s just the cosine function. Here’s the sine function, and you see over here that
you have a maximum at π/2 and the derivative goes from being positive to being negative.
On the other hand, you have a minimum at 3π/2, and the derivative goes
from being negative to being positive. Okay. That’s about first derivatives.
How about second derivatives? Here is the graph of x^3, and its second derivative is 6x.
You see over here that when the second derivative is negative,
the slope becomes progressively smaller. It slows down, so to speak, the function.
When the second derivative is positive, the slope progressively gets bigger.
You can see that over here. In the first case, you would say that the curve is concave downward,
and in the second case, you would say it’s concave upward. It’s concave downward over here,
and concave upward over there. As another example, let’s look at the sine function
and its second derivative. You see over here that it’s concave downward when
the second derivative is negative and concave upward when the second derivative is positive.
Now we can put all that together and talk about the concavity test,
which says that if the second derivative is positive on an interval,
then the graph is concave upward. The short form of that is cup, just like a cup of water.
If the second derivative is negative, then the graph is concave downward. That’s like a frown.
It cannot hold any water in it. That’s a nice test for concavity. Another way of looking at it
is to look at tangent lines. Here’s a function x^2, and the second derivative is 2, which is positive.
You see over here that all the tangent lines lie below the graph when you have
a concave upward graph. All the tangent lines lie below in this case, and if it happened to be
concave downward, then of course all the tangent lines would lie above the curve.
Okay. Now on to inflection points, where you neither have concave upward or concave downward
just at that point. In fact, the curve will switch from being concave upward to being concave downward
at an inflection point. Here’s an example of such a function where you have an inflection point
at 1 roughly. You have concave downward over here and concave upward over there.
Now what’s happening over here is that the slope will reach a maximum or a minimum value
at a point of this type where you have an inflection point, and so the slope is of course a derivative,
and hence the inflection points are precisely those where the second derivative
is either 0 or not defined. In the case of this function over here, let’s just check what happens
if you set the second derivative to be 0 and solve for x.
You find that at x = 1, you actually have an inflection point.
Okay. Finally let’s talk about the second derivative test, which says that
if you have a particular point and the second derivative is positive, then the function has
a local minimum, and if it’s negative, the second derivative, then you have a local maximum.
Looking again at the earlier function, you see over here that when you’re at 0, then you have
the slope of 0 and the graph is concave downward, so you have a local maximum.
Just the reverse happens at 2 where you have a local minimum. That’s how the second derivative
is quite a powerful tool for distinguishing between a maximum and a minimum.
It’s time to summarize. You learned quite a lot in this lesson. First of all, we learned that
the mean value theorem is crucial for understanding how to graph a function starting from its derivative.
We learned about the increasing/decreasing test for when a function increases or decreases.
We learned the first derivative test for finding local maxima and minima.
We talked about the concavity test for figuring out when the function is concave upward or downward,
and that relies on the second derivative. We spoke about inflection points,
where the curve kind of changes shape. Finally, the second derivative test tells us that
you can use the first and second derivatives together to find the local maxima and minima.
That’s the end of this lesson. The next lesson will talk about
limits at infinity and horizontal asymptotes. Before doing that, do review this lesson, do look at
the exercises and make sure you follow this topic really well before you begin the next lesson.
Thank you very much. I’ll stop here.